<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    To AMK: My Best Beloved Friend
Everything my mind and heart may wish to produce shall be dedicated to you, my comrade! Although my opinions on many subjects differ from yours, your heart beats sympathetically with mine — and you are my friend.
I looked about me — my heart was troubled by the sufferings of humanity. I turned my eyes inward I saw that man’s woes arise in man himself, and frequently only because he
does not look straight at the objects around him. Is it possible, I said to myself, that nature has been so miserly with her children as to hide the truth forever from him who errs innocently? Is it possible that this stern stepmother has brought
us into the world that we may know only calamities, but never happiness? My reason trembled at this thought, and my heart thrust it far away. I found a comforter for man in himself: “Remove the veil from the inward eye — and I shall be
happy!” This voice of nature resounded loudly within me. I arose from the despair into which sensitivity and compassion had plunged me; I felt within me strength enough to with-
stand this delusion, and — unspeakable joy! I felt that it was possible for anyone to strive for the well-being of his fellows. Such is the thought which moved me to sketch out what you
are going to read. But, I said to myself, if I find a man who will approve of my intention, who for the sake of the good cause will not condemn my imperfect rendering of my
thoughts, who will share my compassion for the sufferings of his fellow beings, who will support me in the quest before me: will not my undertaking have borne abundant fruit?
Why, why should I seek some one who is far away? My friend, you live close to my heart—and may your name illumine this beginning!

<place_1>[*1] THE DEPARTURE</place_1>
Having supped with friends, I took my place in the post
chaise. As was his custom, the driver urged the horses on to
the utmost, and in a few minutes I was outside the city. It is
hard to part, even briefly, from someone who has become
necessary to us in every moment of our being. It is hard to
part, but blessed is he who can part without smiling, for love
or friendship will console him. You weep as you say farewell,
but think of your return, and may your tears vanish at the
thought of it as the dew vanishes before the face of the sun.
Blessed is he who sobs, hoping for a consoler; blessed is he
who sometimes lives in the future; blessed is he who lives in
dreams. His whole being is enriched, his joys multiply, and
calm soothes the gloom [*2] of sorrow, creating images of
gladness in the mirror of the imagination.
I lay back in the carriage. The ringing of the post bell, after
tiring my ears, at last summoned kindly Morpheus. The sad-
ness of parting remained with me in my deathlike slumber
and made me feel utterly alone. I beheld myself in a broad
valley, which from the sun’s heat had lost all its charming and
variegated verdure; there was no spring in which to cool my-
self, no shade trees to temper the heat. Alone, deserted, a her-
mit amidst nature! I shuddered.
“Miserable one,” I cried, “where are you? Where is every-
thing that used to attract you? Where is that which used to
make your life pleasant? Is it possible that the joys which you
once felt were only dreams and fancies?”
Fortunately a rut in the road, which jarred my carriage,
awakened me. [*3] The carriage stopped. I raised my head.
I saw in an open space a three-story building.
“What is it?” I asked my driver.
“The post station.”
“Where are we?”
“In Sofiya.”
Meanwhile he was unhitching the horses.
<place_2>[*4] SoFIYA</place_2>
Silence everywhere. Lost in contemplation, I had not no-
ticed that my carriage had been standing for some time with-
out its horses. The driver who had brought me thither roused
me from my reverie.
“A few kopeks, Master, for a drink?”
Although such exactions are not legal, everybody pays will-
ingly to avoid vexatious travel regulations. Twenty kopeks
served me well. He who has traveled by post knows that the
permit to use post horses is a protective letter, without which
any purse, excepting possibly a general’s, is subject to great
strain. Taking the permit from my pocket, I carried it the
way they sometimes carry a cross for protection.
I sought the stationmaster and found him snoring. I touched
him lightly on the shoulder.
“Is the Devil after you? What’s the idea of leaving the city
at night? There aren’t [*5] any horses. It’s still very early;
so please go to the inn and have some tea, or go to sleep.” Say-
ing this, Mr. Stationmaster turned to the wall and started
snoring again. What was to be done? Once more I shook him
by the shoulder.
“What do you mean, waking me up again? I’ve already told
you there aren’t any horses,” and Mr. Stationmaster covered
his head with a blanket and turned away from me.
“Tf all the horses are out,” I thought, “it is not fair to dis-
turb the stationmaster’s slumber. But if the horses are in the
stable —”
I made up my mind to find out whether Mr. Stationmaster
had told me the truth. Stepping into the yard, I hunted up
the stable, where I discovered some twenty horses. True
enough, you could count their bones, but they could have
dragged me to the next station. From the stable I returned
to the stationmaster and shook him harder than before. It
seemed to me I had a right to, since I had caught him lying.
He jumped up quickly and, still half asleep, [*6] asked me
who had arrived — but on coming to his senses and seeing me,
he said: “My good fellow, you seem to have been used to treating
drivers like this in the old days. They used to beat them with
sticks, but the times have changed.”
And Mr. Stationmaster angrily went back to bed. I felt like
treating him the way they used to treat drivers whom they
caught cheating; but my generosity to the city driver had in-
spired the Sofiya drivers to hitch up the horses in a hurry, and
at the very moment that I was going to commit a crime on the
stationmaster’s back, a bell tinkled in the yard. I remained a
good citizen. Thus the twenty copper kopeks saved a peace-
able man from judicial investigation, my children from an ex-
ample of uncontrolled anger; and I learned that reason is a
slave to impatience.
The horses carry me quickly; my driver has started a song,
as usual [*7] a melancholy one. He who knows the melodies
of Russian folk songs must admit that there is something in
them which suggests spiritual sorrow. Nearly all the tunes of
such songs are soft and melancholy. Learn how to establish
governmental rule in accord with this musical inclination of
the people. In these songs you may discover the very soul of
our people. Look at a Russian; you will find him pensive. If
he wishes to purge his melancholy, or, as he would say, to
have a good time, he goes to the tavern. In his pleasures he is
impulsive, daring, quarrelsome. If anything happens not to
suit him, he immediately starts an argument or a fight. A barge-
hauler who goes to the tavern with downcast head and returns
blood-spattered from blows in the face may help to explain
much that has seemed puzzling in Russian history.
[*8] My driver was singing. It was past two in the morning.
His song lulled me to sleep as the bell had done before. O
nature, who wrappest man in a shroud of sorrow at his birth,
and draggest him over the rugged crags of fear, boredom, and
grief all through his life, thou hast given him sleep as a con-
solation. When one falls asleep, all is over. Intolerable to the
unfortunate one is his awakening. O how pleasant death is to
him! But is it the end of sorrow? Most gracious Father, wilt
Thou turn Thine eyes away from him who manfully puts an
end to his miserable existence? This sacrifice is offered unto
Thee, the source of all good things. Thou alone givest strength
when nature quakes and trembles. It is the Father’s voice call-
ing His child unto Himself. Thou gavest me life, and I return
it unto Thee, for on earth it has become useless.
<place_3>[*9] TosNA</place_3>
When I set out from Petersburg, I flattered myself that I
was going on the best of roads. Such it was considered to be
by everyone who had traveled on it in the wake of the Em-
peror. Such indeed it had once been, but only for a short time.
The dirt, which covered the road and made it smooth in dry
weather, turned it into a muddy bog under the softening rains
of summer, and made it impassable. — Wearied by the bad
road, I left the carriage and entered the post hut in order to
take a rest. In the hut I found a traveler who, as he sat at the
usual long peasant table in the front corner, was looking
through some papers and was asking the stationmaster to let
him have some horses as quickly as possible. When I asked
who he was, I learned that he [*1o] was a lawyer of the old
school, going to Petersburg with a great heap of ragged papers,
which he was then sorting. I immediately entered into a con-
versation with him, and here is the substance of what he said:
“My dear sir! As a registrar in the Razryadny Archive,’ I,
your most humble servant, had an opportunity to use my place
to good advantage. With great effort I have collected the
genealogies of many Russian families, based on indisputable
‘evidence. I can prove their princely or noble ancestry for
several centuries. Frequently I can establish princely dignity
by proving descent from Vladimir Monomakh or Rurik him-
self.” My dear sir!” he continued, pointing to his papers, “all
the Great Russian nobility ought by rights to buy my work at
a better price than they [*1i] would give for any other wares.
But with your permission, Your Honor, Your Excellency, or
Your Highness (for I do not know your rank), they do not
know what is good for them. You know how the Orthodox
Tsar Fyodor Alekseevich,* of blessed memory, offended the
Russian nobility by abolishing mestnichestvo.t This severe
legislation placed many princely and royal families on a par
with the Novgorod nobility.? The Orthodox Sovereign Em-
peror Peter the Great threw the old nobility into total eclipse
by his Table of Ranks.* Through the military and civil serv-
ice he opened the way for everyone to obtain a noble title,
and, so to speak, trampled the old nobility into the mud. Now
our most gracious Reigning Mother has confirmed the former
decrees by an Imperial Charter to the Gentry,’ which has dis-
tressed our ancient [*12] noble families, because they have
been placed below all the others in the Book of the Nobility.
But it is rumored that a new, complementary decree will soon
be issued, whereby those families that can trace their line for
two or three hundred years will be granted the title of marquis
or some other illustrious title and will thus have some distinc-
tion from the other families. For that reason, dear sir, my work
should be very acceptable to all the old noble society; but
everyone has his enemies.
“In Moscow I fell in with a company of young gentlemen
and offered them my work, hoping by their favor to make up
at least for the paper and ink which I had used; but instead
of a warm response I met only with derision, and I sorrow-
fully left that elder capital, and am now on my way to Peters-
burg, where, as you know, there is a great deal more enlightenment.” [*13] So saying, he made me a low obeisance and
then, straightening up, stood before me in a most respectful
attitude. I knew what he was thinking, took something out of
my purse — and giving it to him, advised him, on his arrival
in Petersburg, to sell his notes to the peddlers by the pound,
for wrapping paper; for the prospective marquisates would
turn many a head, and he would be the cause of a recrudes-
cence of an evil eradicated from Russia: boasting of one’s
ancient lineage.
<place_4>[*14] LYUBANI</place_4>
I suppose it is all the same to you whether I traveled in
winter or in summer. Maybe both in winter and in summer.
It is not unusual for travelers to set out in sleighs and to re-
turn in carriages. In summer. The corduroy road tortured my
body; I climbed out of the carriage and went on foot. While
I had been lying back in the carriage, my thoughts had turned
to the immeasurable vastness of the world. By spiritually leav-
ing the earth I thought I might more easily bear the jolting of
the carriage. But spiritual exercises do not always distract us
from our physical selves; and so, to save my body, I got out
and walked. A few steps from the road I saw a peasant plough-
ing a field. The weather was hot. I looked at my watch. It was
twenty minutes before one. I had set out on Saturday. It was
now Sunday. [*15] The ploughing peasant, of course, be-
longed to a landed proprietor, who would not let him pay a
commutation tax.t The peasant was ploughing very carefully.
The field, of course, was not part of his master’s land. He
turned the plough: with astonishing ease.
“God help you,” I said, walking up to the dlauenmala. who,
without stopping, was finishing the furrow he had started.
“God help you,” I repeated.
“Thank you, sir,” the ploughman said to me, shaking the
earth off the ploughshare and transferring it to a new furrow.
“You must be a Dissenter,” since you plough on a Sunday.”
“No, sir, I make the true sign of the cross,” he said, showing
me the three fingers together.? “And God is merciful and
does not bid us starve to death, so long as we have strength
and a family.”
“Have you no time to work during the week, then, and can
you not have any rest on Sundays, in the hottest part of the
day, at that?”
“In a week, sir, there are six days, and we go six times a
week [*16] to work on the master’s fields; * in the evening,
if the weather is good, we haul to the master’s house the hay
that is left in the woods;-and on holidays the women and girls
go walking in the woods, looking for mushrooms and berries.
God grant,” he continued, making the sign of the cross, “that
it rains this evening. If you have peasants of your own, sir,
they are praying to God for the same thing.”
“My friend, I have no peasants, and so nobody curses me.
Do you have a large family?”
“Three sons and three daughters. The eldest is nine years
old.”
“But how do you manage to get food enough, if you have
only the holidays free?”
“Not only the holidays: the nights are ours, too. If a fellow
isn’t lazy, he won’t starve to death. You see, one horse is rest-
ing; and when this one gets tired, [’ll take the other; so the
work gets done.”
“Do you work the same way for your master?”
“No, sir, it would be a sin to work the same way. On his
fields there are [*17] a hundred hands for one mouth, while
I have two for seven mouths: you can figure it out for your-
self. No matter how hard you work for the master, no one
will thank you for it, The master will not pay our head tax;
but, though he doesn’t pay it, he doesn’t demand one sheep,
one hen, or any linen or butter the less. The peasants are much
better off where the landlord lets them pay a commutation tax
without the interference of the steward. It is true that some-
times even good masters take more than three rubles a man;
but even that’s better than having to work on the master’s
fields. Nowadays it’s getting to be the custom to let villages
to tenants, as they call it. But we call it putting our heads in
a noose. A landless tenant skins us peasants alive; even the best
ones don’t leave us any time for ourselves. In the winter he
won’t let us do any carting of goods and won’t let us go into
town to work; all our work has to be for him, because he
pays our head tax. It is an invention of the Devil to turn your
peasants over to work for a stranger. You can make a com-
plaint against [*18] a bad steward, but to whom can you
complain against a bad tenant?”
“My friend, you are mistaken; the laws forbid them to
torture people.”
“Torture? That’s true; but all the same, sir, you would
not want to be in my hide.” Meanwhile the ploughman
hitched up the other horse to the plough and bade me good-
bye as he began a new furrow.
The words of this peasant awakened in me a multitude of
thoughts. I thought especially of the inequality of treatment
within the peasant class. I compared the crown peasants with
the manorial peasants.° They both live in villages; but the for-
mer pay a fixed sum, while the latter must be prepared to pay
whatever their master demands. The former are judged by
their equals; the latter are dead to the law, except, perhaps, in
criminal cases. A member of society becomes known to the
government protecting him, only when he breaks the social
bonds, when he becomes a criminal! This thought made my
blood boil.
[*19] Tremble, cruelhearted landlord! on the brow of each
of your peasants I see your condemnation written.
While absorbed in these thoughts I happened to notice my
servant, who was sitting up on the box in front of me, sway-
ing from side to side. Suddenly I felt a chill coursing through
my veins, sending the blood to my head and mantling my
cheeks with a blush. I felt so ashamed of myself that I could
scarcely keep from bursting into tears. “In your anger,” I said
to myself, “you denounce the proud master who wears out
his peasants in the field; but are you not doing the same or
even worse yourself? What crime has your poor Petrushka
committed that you should deny him sleep, the consolation
for our miseries, and nature’s greatest gift to the unfortunate?
He gets pay, food, and clothing, and you never [*20] beat
him with a whip or cudgel. (O moderate man!) And you
think that a piece of bread and a scrap of cloth give you the
right to treat your fellow human being as though he were a
top, and you merely boast that you do not often whip it up
while it is whirling. Do you know what is written in the funda-
mental law, in the heart of every man? He whom I strike has
the right to strike me. Remember the day when Petrushka was
drunk and did not come in time to dress you. Remember how
you boxed his ear. If only he had then, although intoxicated,
come to his senses and answered you as your question de-
served! And who gave you power over him? The law. The
law? And you dare to defile that sacred name? Miserable one! ”
— Tears gushed from my eyes, and while I was in this state
the post nags brought me to the next station.
<place_5>[*21] CHUDOVO</place_5>
I had barely entered the post hut when I heard the sound
of a post bell in the street, and a few minutes later my friend
Ch * came in. When I had left him in Petersburg, he had
had no intention of leaving there so soon. It was an extraor-
dinary occurrence which had caused a man of firm habits, like
my friend, to leave Petersburg, and here is what he told me.
“You were ready to depart when I betook myself to Peter-
hof. I spent the holidays as happily as possible in the smoke
and swirl of pleasures. But wanting to turn my journey to
advantage, I decided to go down to Kronstadt and Sisterbek,
where they told me great changes had been made lately. I spent
two very pleasant days [*22] in Kronstadt, feasting my eyes
on all the foreign ships, the stone enclosures of the Kronstadt
fortress, and the rapidly rising buildings. I was curious to see
the plan of the new Kronstadt, and happily I saw in my mind’s
eye the beauty of the future development; in a word, the
second day of my visit ended happily and pleasantly. The
night was calm and bright, and the fragrant air permeated my
senses with a peculiar gentleness which it is easier to experience
than to describe. I intended to make the best use of nature’s
favor and at least once more in my life to enjoy the superb
spectacle of the rising sun, which I had never yet been able
to see over the smooth horizon of the water. I hired a twelve-
oared marine sloop and set out for S
[*23] “For about four versts * everything went well. The
monotonous sound of the oars made me sleepy, and my drowsy
eyes hardly noticed the momentary gleam of the drops of
water falling from the raised oars. A poetic fancy was already
transporting me to the lovely meadows of Paphos and Ama-
thus.* Suddenly the shrill whistle of the wind rising in the dis-
tance dispelled my dreams, and before my drowsy eyes ap-
peared a mass of dense black clouds which seemed to be gath-
ering and threatening to break over our heads. The mirror-
like surface of the water began to ripple, and the calm gave
place to an incipient plashing of the waves. I rejoiced at this
spectacle, too; and watching the majestic features of nature,
I confess without boasting that what was beginning to frighten
the others was giving me pleasure. Now and then I cried out,
like Vernet, ‘Oh, how beautiful!’* But as the wind grew
[*24] steadily stronger, we had to think about getting to
shore. Dense, opaque clouds completely obscured the sky. The
impetuous motion of the waves deflected the direction of the
rudder, and the gusts of wind, now raising us on the watery
crests, now plunging us into the steep furrows of the swelling
sea, inhibited the forward movement of the rowers. We fol-
lowed willy-nilly the direction of the wind and drifted at ran
dom. Then we began to be afraid of the shore; indeed the very
thing which would in favorable sailing have given us hope
now threw us into despair. It seemed to us that nature was
miserly at this hour, and we were indignant that she did not
reveal her awful majesty in flashes of lightning and did not
make our ears ring with peals of thunder. But hope, which fol-
lows man in his extremity, now gave us strength, and we en-
couraged one another as much as we could.
[*25] “Borne by the waves, our vessel suddenly came to a
stop and was stuck fast. All our combined efforts failed to dis-
lodge it from the place where it was stranded. While trying
to get our boat off the shoal, as we thought it was, we did not
notice that in the meantime the wind had almost completely
died down. The sky was gradually cleared of the clouds which
had veiled its azure. But the returning light, instead of bring-
ing joy, only revealed our perilous situation. We saw clearly
that our sloop was not on a shoal, but jammed in between two
large rocks, and that no force could release it intact. My friend,
imagine our situation! Anything I might say would be feeble
compared to what I felt. Even if I were able to give an ade-
quate account of all my sensations, it would [*26] still be too
weak to arouse in you feelings like those which then arose and
stirred within my soul. Our vessel stood in the middle of a
rocky bank which shut in the bay and extended as far as
S . We were about a verst and a half from the shore. The
water began to enter the boat from all sides and threatened
ultimately to sink us. At the last hour, when our flame sinks
low and eternity opens before us, all the distinctions invented
by men’s minds begin to disappear. Man becomes simply man:
thus as we saw our end drawing near, we all forgot our rank
and stations and thought only how we might save ourselves,
helping to bail the water as best we could. But what was the
use? As fast as the water was bailed out by our combined
efforts, it poured in again. To the extreme [*27] distress of
our hearts there was no ship to be seen passing by us, either
near or far. But even if one had given us hope by heaving into
sight, it would only have deepened our despair by forsaking us
in order that they might not share our fate.
“At last the captain of our boat, who was more accustomed
to the dangers of the sea than anyone else, and who, in the
various marine engagements in the late Turkish War in the
Archipelago,” had probably been forced to learn to look with
_ indifference upon death, decided either to save us by saving
himself, or to perish in this noble endeavor: for if we stayed in
that place, we were doomed to perish. He left the boat and,
making his way from rock to rock, walked toward the shore,
accompanied by our heartfelt prayers, At first he went rapidly
on his way, leaping from stone to stone, fording the [*28]
water where it was shallow, and swimming where it was deep.
We did not take our eyes off him. At last we saw that his
strength was beginning to fail, for he went from rock to rock
more deliberately and frequently stopped and sat down on a
rock to rest. It seemed to us that he was lingering in doubt and
indecision whether to continue on his way. This impelled one
of his comrades to follow the captain in order to help him if
he found him exhausted before he could reach the shore, and,
in that case, to try to reach the shore himself. Our eyes fol-
lowed now one, now the other, and we devoutly prayed for
their safety. Finally the second of these emulators of Moses in
crossing the watery depths on foot (though without a miracle)
stopped still on a rock, and we entirely lost sight of the first
one.
[*29] ‘““The secret, innermost emotions of each one of us,
heretofore imprisoned, so to speak, by terror, started to come
to the surface as our hopes waned. Meanwhile the water was
rising in our boat, and our straining efforts to bail it out were
clearly exhausting our strength. An excitable and impatient
man tore his hair, bit his fingers, and cursed the hour of his
departure. A man with a timid soul, who, perhaps, had long
felt the weight of crushing oppression, wept bitterly, and
drenched with his tears the bench on which he sprawled with
his face downward. Another, remembering his home, his chil-
dren, and his wife, sat as if petrified, thinking not of his own
destruction but of theirs, for they were supported by his la-
bors. You yourself, my friend, may guess what was the con-
dition of my mind, for you know me well. All I will say to
you is that I fervently prayed to God. At last we all began
to give way to despair, for our vessel was more [*30] than
half filled, and we were standing up to our knees in water.
Frequently we thought of leaving the boat and proceeding
over the stony ridge to the shore, but our fellow traveler’s long
hours of waiting upon that rock and the disappearance of the
captain made the danger seem greater to us than it perhaps
was in reality. In the midst of these woeful reflections, we ob-
served near the opposite shore, although I could not definitely
determine at what distance, two black spots which seemed to
be moving on the water. The moving black spots appeared to
grow larger as we watched them; at last as they came nearer
we clearly saw two small boats making straight for the very
place where we were waiting in a despair which surpassed
our hope a hundredfold. As when a door is suddenly opened
in a dark temple that is utterly impervious to light, [*31] and
a ray of sunlight in a twinkling penetrates and dispels the
darkness and spreads over the whole building to its farthest
corners — so, at the sight of the boats, a ray of hope pene-
trated our souls. Despair gave way to exaltation, sadness to
joy, and there was danger that our joyous bodily movements
and splashings might cause our destruction before we could be
removed from jeopardy. But the returning hope of life brought
back the memory of our distinctive stations in life, which had
been dormant while we were in danger. For the present it
redounded to our common advantage. I restrained the exces-
sive rejoicing, which might have been a cause of injury. After
a while we beheld two large fishing smacks, and, when they
reached us, we saw in one of them our savior who, having
reached the shore over the stony ridge, had found these boats
to save us [*32] from our imminent danger. We abandoned
our vessel without delay and made for the shore in the fishing
smacks, not forgetting, however, to take off from the rock
our comrade, who had been there for about seven hours. Not
half an hour had elapsed when the sloop, relieved of the weight
of its passengers, floated out from between the rocks and fell
_ completely to pieces. As we approached the shore in joy and
exaltation at being saved, Pavel, our companion who had
brought us rescue, told us the following tale:
“When I left you in imminent danger, I hurried over the
rocks to the shore. My desire to save you gave me supernat-
ural strength, but about seven hundred feet from the shore
my strength began to give out, and I began to despair of sav-
ing you or myself. But after resting on a rock for about half
an hour, I leaped up with renewed vigor, and, without resting
any more, crawled, so to speak, [*33] up to the shore. There
I stretched out on the grass and, after ten minutes’ rest, got
up and ran as fast as I could along the shore to S . Al-
though fairly exhausted, I thought of you and continued run-
ning until I reached the place. It seemed that Heaven wanted
to put your firmness and my patience to the test, for neither
along the shore nor in S itself did I find any boat with
which to save you. Almost in despair, I thought there was no
better place to look for help than at the local commander’s.
I ran to the house where he lived. It was already after six
o'clock. In the anteroom I found a sergeant of the local com-
mand. I briefly explained to him your plight and the reason
for my coming, and I asked him to wake Mr. , who
was still sleeping. The sergeant said to me: “My friend, I do
not dare to.”
“What? You do not dare to? When twenty men are
drowning, you do not [*34] dare to wake the man who can
save them? But you, worthless fellow, are lying; I will go wake
him myself —.” The sergeant took me by the shoulder, not
very politely, and pushed me out the door. I almost burst with
anger. But thinking more of your danger than of the insult
to me and the hardheartedness of the commander to his sub-
ordinate, I ran to the guardhouse, which was about two versts
distant from the accursed house whence I had been ejected.
I knew that the soldiers living there had boats in which the
rowed about the bay collecting cobblestones to sell for pav-
ing, and I was not mistaken in my hope. I found these two
small boats, and now, to my unutterable Joy, you are all saved.
If you had drowned, I would have hurled myself into the
water after you.’ So saying, Pavel burst into tears.
“Meanwhile we reached the shore. Upon leaving the boat,
I fell upon my knees and raised my hands to [*35] Heaven.
‘Almighty Father,’ I cried, ‘it is Thy will that we live; Thou
hast tried us; Thy will be done.’ This, my friend, is a feeble
description of what I felt. The terror of the last hour had
pierced my soul, and I saw the moment when I should cease
to exist. But what shall I be? I do not know. A terrible uncer-
tainty. Now I feel; the hour strikes; I am dead; motion, life,
feeling, thought, all vanish in an instant. Imagine yourself,
my friend, at the brink of the grave: will you not feel a with-
ering chill flowing through your veins and cutting life off
before its time? O my friend! But I have strayed from my
story.
“After I had finished my prayer, fury seized my heart. ‘Is
it possible,’ I said to myself, ‘that such inhumanity should
occur in our time, in Europe, next door to the capital, under
the eyes of the Great Sovereign?’ It reminded me [*36] of
the English shut up in the dungeon of the Bengal Subab.
[*37] “I sighed from the depths of my soul. Meanwhile we
reached S . [thought that when the commander awoke, he
would punish his sergeant and would at least give the ship-
wrecked men a chance to rest. In this hope I went straight to
his house. But I was so irritated by the conduct of his sub-
ordinate that I was unable to moderate my speech. When I
saw him, I said, ‘Sir, have you been informed that a few hours
_ago twenty men were in danger of losing their lives [*38]
at sea, and appealed to you for help?’ Smoking away at his
pipe, he answered me as coolly as possible, ‘I have been told
of it since, for then I was asleep.’ At that I trembled with the
anger of outraged humanity. ‘If you are a hard sleeper, you
should have yourself waked with a hammer on your head
when people are drowning and crying for your help.’ My
friend, guess what his answer was! I thought I would have a
stroke from what I heard. He said to me: “That is not my
duty.’ I lost my patience. ‘Is it your duty to kill people, you
vile man? And you wear tokens of distinction, you are in
command of others! —’ I was unable to finish my speech, al-
most spat in his face, and walked away. I tore my hair with
rage. | made a thousand plans to wreak vengeance on this
beastly commander, not on my account but on behalf of all
humanity. But when I came to my senses, I realized, from
many similar instances, [*39] that my revenge would be fruit-
less and that I would only be taken for a madman or an evil-
doer; so I calmed myself.
“Meanwhile my men went to the priest, who received us
with great joy, warmed us, fed us, and gave us a place to rest.
We passed a whole day with him, enjoying his hospitality
and good cheer. Next day we found a large sloop, in which
we reached Oranienbaum without any mishap. In Petersburg
I told this tale to one man after another. They all sympathized
with my plight and berated the commander’s hardheartedness,
but no one would speak up to him. If we had drowned, he
would have been our murderer. ‘But his duty does not pre-
scribe that he should save you,’ someone said. Now I am bid-
ding the city good-bye forever. Never again will I enter that
den of tigers. Their sole joy is in devouring one [*4o] an-
other; they delight in torturing the weak to their last gasp
and in groveling before the powers that be. And you wanted
me to settle in the city! No, my friend,” said the story-teller,
jumping up from his chair, “I will go where people do not
go, where they do not know what man is, where his name is
unknown. Farewell!” With these words he got into his car-
riage and was off.
<place_6>[*41] SPASSKAYA POLEST’</place_6>
I drove so fast after my friend that I overtook him at the
next post station. I tried to persuade him to return to Peters-
burg, tried to prove to him that small and occasional imperfec-
tions in society do not destroy its bonds, just as a pebble fall-
ing upon the expanse of the sea cannot disturb its surface. But
he cut me off sharply, saying, “If I, a small pebble, had gone
to the bottom, of course it would not have caused any storm
in the Gulf of Finland, and I would have gone to live with the
seals.” And with an indignant look he bade me good-bye, lay
back in his carriage, and hastily departed.
The horses were already hitched up, and I was on the point
of stepping into my carriage when it suddenly began to rain.
“No great misfortune,” I thought; [*42] “I will cover myself
with matting and keep dry.” But this thought had barely
entered my mind, when I felt as though I had been immersed
in an ice-hole. Without asking my advice, the sky unloosed
the clouds and the rain poured down in buckets. You can’t
argue with the weather, and, considering the proverb, “the
slower you travel, the farther you'll get,” I left the carriage
and ran to the nearest hut. The proprietor had already gone to
~ bed, and it was dark in the hut. But even in the darkness I
obtained permission to dry myself. I took off my wet clothes,
put what was still dry under my head, and soon went to sleep
on a bench. But as my bed was not made of down, I could not
pamper myself very long. As I awoke I heard some whisper-
ing. I could distinguish the voices of two people conversing
with each other.
“Go ahead, husband, and tell me,” said a woman’s voice.
“Listen, wife. Once upon a time —and really it goes like
a fairy tale.”
“But how can you believe a fairy tale?” said the wife, half-
aloud, yawning from [*43] sleepiness. “You can’t make me
believe there was a Polkan, Bevis, or Nightingale the Rob-
ber. (2
“Who’s making you? You may, if you want to. This much
is certain, that in the old days bodily strength was respected,
and strong men used it for evil. There you have Polkan. As
for Nightingale the Robber, my dear, read those who tell
about Russian antiquity. They will tell you that he was
called Nightingale because of his eloquence. Now don’t in-
terrupt my story. And so, once upon a time there lived a
Viceroy.” In his youth he had loafed around in foreign coun-
tries, had learned to eat oysters, and had become very fond of
them. So long as he had but little money of his own, he re-
strained his passion and ate only ten at a time, and that only
when he was in Petersburg. As soon as he began to climb up
the ladder of ranks, the number of oysters at his table began
to increase. And when he became Viceroy and had a lot of his
[*44] own money and government funds at his disposal, he
craved oysters like a pregnant woman. Asleep or awake, he
thought only of eating oysters. While they were in season no-
body had any rest. All his subordinates became martyrs. No
matter what happened, he had to have oysters. He would send
an order to the office to furnish him a courier at once, to dis-
patch with important reports to Petersburg. Everybody knew
that the courier was sent to fetch oysters, but he had his travel-
ing expenses granted anyhow. The government’s purse has
many holes. The courier is provided with a traveling permit
and money; he is all ready, and appears before His Excellency
in a tunic and riding breeches.
“ ‘Be off, my good fellow,’ says he of the string of medals,
‘take this packet to the Great Morskaya.’
“To whom shall it go, sir?’
“ ‘Read the address.’
“ *To His His
[*45] ‘“ “You are not reading it right.’
“ “To the Honorable ,
“ ‘Wrong again. It goes to Mr. Korzinkin, honorable shop-
keeper, in St. Petersburg, Great Morskaya.’
“7 know, Your Excellency.’
“ ‘Then be off, my good fellow, and as soon as you get it,
return at once, without delay. I’ll show my gratitude to you.’
“And he gallops and gallops, as fast as the troika * can carry
him, to Petersburg and right into Korzinkin’s yard.
“ ‘Welcome! What a joker His Excellency is, to send you
a thousand versts for some trash or other. But he is a good
master. I am happy to serve him. Here are the oysters, fresh
from the market. Tell him I can’t sell them for less than 150
a keg; they come pretty high to me. We will settle the account
with His Grace later.’
“They loaded the keg in the carriage, turned the shaft about,
and off went the courier again; he barely [*46] had time to
go to the inn and drink two cups of brandy.
“Tinkle, tinkle — As soon as they caught the sound of the
post bell at the city gates, the officer on duty ran to the
Viceroy (nothing like doing everything properly) and re-
ported to him that the carriage had been seen in the distance
and the post bell could be heard. He had not finished his report
when — whish — the courier was at the door.
“‘T have brought it, Your Excellency.’
“Most opportunely,’ and, turning to those present, ‘indeed
a worthy, dependable man, and not a drunkard. How many
years now, he has been making two trips a year to Petersburg,
and I cannot even remember how many to Moscow. Secre-
tary, take down this recommendation: “For his numerous mis-
sions as a courier and their punctual execution, I recommend
him for advancement in rank.” ’
“In the treasurer’s record of disbursements it is written:
‘At the recommendation of His [*47] Excellency, courier
N.N., sent to St. Petersburg with most important dispatches,
was granted traveling expenses from the special funds for
journeying both ways with three horses.’ The treasurer’s rec-
ord has gone to the audit, but there is no odor of oysters in it.
“ “At the recommendation of His Excellency, General, etc.,
etc., IT IS ORDERED, that Sergeant N. N. be promoted to the
rank of Lieutenant.’
“You see, wife, how they manage to get their promotions.
What good does it do me to serve honestly and not get ahead
by a finger’s breadth? According to the regulations, I should
have been rewarded for good service. But the Tsar is merciful,
while the dogkeeper is not.* Neither is our treasurer: this is
the second time that they have sent me to the criminal court
on his recommendation. If I were in cahoots with him, life
would be a regular carnival.”
“Klement’ich, stop talking nonsense! If you want to know
why he doesn’t like you, it’s because you [*48] take tips
from everybody and don’t share with him.”
“Softly, Kuzminichna, talk softly. Somebody might hear
you.” Both voices fell silent, and I fell asleep again.
In the morning I learned that the couple who had passed
the night with me in the hut were a courthouse functionary
and his wife, and that at daybreak they had left for Novgorod.
While they were hitching the horses to my carriage, an-
other equipage, drawn by a troika, drove up. From it leaped
a man in a large cloak, and his broad-brimmed hat pulled
down over his head made’it impossible for me to see his face.
Without a traveling permit he asked for horses; and while a
number of drivers were standing around him haggling about
the price, he did not wait for the end of their bickering, but
impatiently exclaimed to one of them: “Hitch the horses at
once. I'll give you four kopeks for every verst.” The driver
ran away to fetch the horses. The others, seeing that [*49]
there was no use making any new offer, all left him.
I was not more than ten yards away from him. He came up
to me and, without taking off his hat, said: “Dear Sir, won’t
you give something to an unfortunate man?”
This surprised me beyond measure, and I could not help
saying to him that I was surprised at his appeal for help, since
he had not haggled about the stage fees and had offered double
the usual rate.
“I see,” he said to me, “that you have never had any hard
luck in your life.”
I was pleased with this firm reply, and without hesitation
took something from my purse —. “Pardon me,” I said, “I
cannot help you out with more at present, but when we reach
our destination I may be able to do a little better by you.” I
hoped in this way to make him more open-hearted, and I was
not [*50] disappointed.
“I see,” he said to me, “that you still have generous feeling,
that contact with the world and the pursuit of your own ad-
vantage have not barred the way to your heart. Permit me to
take a seat in your carriage, and let your servant ride in mine.”
Meanwhile our horses were hitched up, I carried out his wish
— and we’re off.
“Oh, sir, I can hardly realize yet that I am unhappy. Not
more than a week ago I was gay and cheerful, I felt no want,
I was loved, or at least so it seemed; for my house was filled
_ every day with people who had already attained proofs of
distinction, and my table was always like some glorious feast.
But if pride had such a measure of satisfaction, my soul like-
wise enjoyed true bliss. After many false starts, attempts,
[*51] and failures, I had finally won as my wife the lady
whom I desired. Our mutual passion, satisfying us in body and
soul, presented everything to us in a bright light. We beheld
no clouded day. We had reached the acme of our bliss. My
wife was with child and the hour of her delivery was near.
Fate had decided that all this happiness should be destroyed in
an instant.
“I gave a dinner, and a multitude of so-called friends had
come to glut their idle appetites at my expense. One of those
present, who secretly disliked me, began to talk to his neigh-
bor, in a whisper, but loudly enough so that my wife and many
others could hear him. ‘Don’t you know that our host’s case
in the criminal court has already been decided?’
[*52] “It must seem strange to you,” said my fellow trav-
eler, addressing his words to me, “that a man not in the gov-
ernment service and in the situation I have described ® could
be subjected to criminal prosecution. For a long time I thought
so myself, even when my case had gone through the lower
courts and reached the court of highest instance. This is how
it happened: I was registered in the merchants’ guild; putting
my capital into circulation, I became a partner in a lease con-
cession. My inexperience led me to trust a dishonest man who,
having been personally caught in a crime, was excluded from
the concession, and who, as his books showed, had large debts.
He went into hiding; I was on hand; and they decided to re-
cover the debts from me. I looked into the matter:as best I
could and found that in fact either none of the debt at all or
only a very small part of it was mine, and so I petitioned for
a proportionate settlement, [*53] since I was surety for him.
But instead of granting my petition, the authorities ordered
me to make good the losses. This was the first injustice. But
to it they added a second. At the time when I had become a
surety for the lease, I had had no landed property; but now,
under the usual rules, my landed property was attached in
the civil court. A strange thing, to forbid one to sell what one
does not own! After that I bought a house and made other
acquisitions. At the very same time chance permitted me,
upon my receiving rank,° to pass from the merchants’ guild
to the gentry. Watching my chances, I took the opportunity
to sell my house on favorable terms and passed the deed in the
very same court where the attachment was entered. This was
held against me as a crime; for there were people whose pleas-
ure was [*54] darkened by the happiness of my life. The gov-
ernment attorney reported against me, claiming that in selling
the house I had tried to evade paying the debts due to the
treasury, and that I had deceived the civil court by giving my
present status rather than my status at the time I had purchased
the house. In vain did I plead that there could be no attach-
ment of that which had not been part of the estate; * in vain
did I plead that at least the rest of the estate should be sold
first and the debts paid out of the proceeds of this sale, and
that only after that should other measures be taken; and that
I had not deceived them about my status, since I was already
a nobleman when I bought the house. All this was disallowed,
the sale of my house was voided, for my dishonest behavior
I was sentenced to be deprived of my ranks, and” — the story-
teller proceeded — “ ‘our host is now summoned to court to
be held under arrest until final disposition of the case.’ ®
[*55] “While telling this last part of the tale, our dinner
guest had raised his voice. My wife had scarcely heard it when
she embraced me and cried out: ‘No, darling, I will go with
you.’ She could not utter another word. Her body grew limp
and she fell senseless into my arms. I lifted her from the chair
and carried her into the bedroom. I do not know how the
dinner ended.
“When she came to after a while, she felt the pains which
_ heralded the imminent birth of the fruit of our love. But how-
ever severe they were, the thought that I should be under
arrest troubled her so much that she kept repeating: ‘I will
go with you.’ This unfortunate affair hastened the birth of the
child by a whole month, and all the efforts of the midwife
and doctor who were called in to help were in vain, and could
not keep my wife from giving birth to the child within twenty-
four hours. Her anguish of soul was not assuaged [*56] by
the birth of the child; indeed it grew even more violent and
threw her into a fever. What is the use of dragging out the
miserable story? My wife died the third day after the child
was born. Seeing her suffering, you may believe me, I did not
leave her for a moment. In my grief I had completely forgot-
ten my trial and the decision against me. On the day before
the death of my beloved, the premature fruit of our union
had also died. I was completely absorbed in the sickness of
his mother, and the child’s death did not at that time appear
so great a loss to me. Imagine, imagine,” cried the narrator,
pulling his hair with both his hands, “imagine my situation
when I saw my beloved leaving me forever. Forever!” he
cried out in a wild voice. “But why am I running away? Let
them put me in prison; I am no longer vulnerable; let them
take my life. O cruel barbarians, tigers, [*57] serpents, gnaw
my heart, inject your slow poison! Forgive my outbreak; I
think I shall soon lose my mind entirely. Whenever I think of
the moment my beloved left me, I forget everything, and the
light in my eyes is extinguished. But I shall finish my story.
While I lay prostrate in deep despair over the lifeless body
of my beloved, one of my true friends came running up to
me and said, “They’ve come to arrest you; they’re waiting for
you outside. Run from here; a carriage is ready for you at
the back gate; go to Moscow or wherever you want and stay
there until it is possible to get your sentence reduced.’ I paid
no attention to his remarks, but, with the help of his servants,
he carried me out by force and put me in the carriage. Then,
remembering that I would need money, he gave me a purse,
which, however, contained only fifty [*58] rubles. He went
to my study to get me more money, but finding an officer
already in my bedroom, managed only to send me word that
I should get away. I do not remember how I got to the first
station. My friend’s servant told me all that had happened and
bade me farewell, and now I am going, as the proverb says,
whither my eyes look.” 
My fellow traveler’s story moved me inexpressibly. “Is it
possible,” I said to myself, “that such cruelties could be per-
petrated in such a merciful reign as ours? Is it possible that
there can be judges so brutally unjust that, to fill the treasury
(indeed one may thus dignify every illegal seizure of property
to satisfy the demands of the government), they would de-
prive people of their property, honor, life?” I considered how
this incident might be brought to the ears [*59] of the supreme
power. For I justly believed that in an autocratic government
only the supreme power could be impartial. “Why can I not
undertake his defense myself? I will write a petition to the
highest governmental authorities. I will give a detailed account
of the whole matter and demonstrate the injustice of the judges
and the innocence of the defendant. But they will not accept
the petition from me. They will ask what right I had to draw
it up; they will demand a power of attorney from me. What
right have I? Why, that of suffering humanity! A man de-
prived of his property, his honor, half his life, in voluntary
exile to escape a disgraceful incarceration. And for this you
need a power of attorney? From whom? Is it not enough that
one of my fellow citizens is suffering? But there is no need of
that. He is a man: therein is my right, therein is my power of
attorney. O God-man! Wherefore didst Thou write Thy
[*60] law for barbarians? They make the sign of the cross
in Thy name and bear bloody sacrifices to evil. Wherefore
wert Thou merciful to them? Instead of threatening future
punishment, Thou shouldst have increased their present pun-
ishment and, tormenting their conscience in proportion to their
wickedness, Thou shouldst have given them no rest by day
or night until by their suffering they had atoned for all the
evil they had wrought.” ‘These reflections so wearied my body
that I fell sound asleep and did not wake up for a long time.
While I was sleeping, the humors stirred up by my thoughts
streamed to my head and, stimulating the tender substance
of my brain, aroused a variety of images. In my dream ap-
peared innumerable pictures, but they disappeared like light
vapors in the air. At last, as often happens, a certain fiber of
my brain, firmly touched by the fluids arising from the inter-
nal vessels of my body, throbbed more than the others, and
this is what I dreamed.
[*61] I imagined that I was a tsar, shah, khan, king, bey,
nabob, sultan, or some such exalted being, sitting on a throne
in power and majesty.
My throne was of pure gold and, cleverly set with vari-
colored precious stones, it shone resplendent. Nothing could
compare with the luster of my raiment. My head was crowned
with a laurel wreath. Around me lay the regalia of my power.
Here lay a sword on a column wrought of silver, on which
were represented battles at sea and on land, the capture of
cities, and other triumphs of this sort, everywhere my name
could be seen on high, borne by the Genius of glory, who was
hovering over all these exploits. Here one could see my scepter
resting upon sheaves heavy with abundant ears of grain,
wrought of pure gold and perfectly imitating nature. [*62] A
pair of scales hung from a rigid beam. In one of the scales lay
a book with the inscription “The Law of Mercy”; in the other
likewise there was a book with the inscription “The Law of
Conscience.” The orb was carved from a single stone and was
supported by a circlet of cherubim sculptured in white mar-
ble. My crown was raised above everything else and rested
on the shoulders of a mighty giant, and its rim was supported
by Truth. A serpent of enormous size, forged of gleaming
steel, wound all about the foot of my throne and, holding the
tip of its tail in its jaws, represented eternity.
Not these lifeless emblems alone proclaimed my power and
majesty. About my throne stood the estates of the realm, tim-
idly submissive and anxious to catch my glance. At some dis-
tance from my throne crowded a countless multitude of
people, whose [*63] various attires, facial features, bearing,
appearance, and stature indicated their diversity of race. Their
trembling silence assured me that they were all subject to my
will. On the sides, upon a somewhat higher level, stood a great
number of charming, splendidly garbed women. Their glances
expressed their delight upon seeing me, and their very wishes
strove to anticipate mine ere they arose.
The deepest silence reigned in this assembly; it seemed that
all were anxiously expecting an important event upon which
depended the peace and happiness of the whole common-
wealth. Self-centered and bored to the bottom of my soul by
the cloying monotony of existence, I paid my debt to nature
and, opening my mouth from ear to ear, I yawned with all my
might. They all [*64] responded to my mood. Suddenly con-
fusion spread its somber veil over the face of joy, the smile
flitted away from the lips of tenderness and the sparkle of
merriment from the cheeks of pleasure. Twisted and furtive
glances betrayed the sudden approach of terror and imminent
misfortune. Sighs were heard, the stinging forerunners of grief,
and groans, restrained by fear. Despair and mortal terror, more
agonizing than death itself, rushed in with giant strides to take
possession of all hearts. I was moved to the depths of my soul
by this sad spectacle; my facial muscles involuntarily con-
tracted toward my ears and, stretching my lips, produced in
my features a twitch that resembled a smile, after which I
sneezed loudly. Just so the midday sun breaks through the
thick, dark, foggy atmosphere. [*65] Its vital heat disperses
the condensed moisture, which, divided into its component
particles, is in part lightened and swiftly borne into the im-
_ measurable space of ether, while the rest, retaining in itself
only the weight of its earthly particles, swiftly falls down. The
darkness, which had prevailed everywhere before the radiant
globe broke through, suddenly disappears and, hastily throw-
ing off its impenetrable shroud, flies away on rushing wings,
leaving no trace of its presence. Even thus my smile dispelled
the looks of sadness which had settled on the faces of the as-
sembled company; joy quickly filled the hearts of all, and not
an oblique sign of displeasure was left. All began to cry:
“Long live our mighty Sovereign! May he live forever!” Like
the gentle midday breeze which stirs the foliage and produces
[*66] an amorous whisper in the oak grove was the joyful
murmur that passed through the gathering.
One said in a low voice: “He has subdued our enemies
abroad and at home, he has expanded the frontiers of the
fatherland, he has subjected thousands of men, of many races,
to his power.” Another exclaimed: “He has enriched the realm,
he has expanded internal and foreign commerce, he is a patron
of the arts and sciences, he encourages agriculture and indus-
try.” Women tenderly said: “He has saved thousands of use-
ful citizens from destruction by preventing their death even
at the breast.” One announced with dignity: “He has increased
the income of the government, he has reduced the people’s
taxes, he has provided the people with a secure livelihood.”
Youths, ecstatically raising their hands to heaven, cried: “He
is merciful and just, his law is equal for all, and he considers
himself its first servant. [*67] He is a wise legislator, a rightieous judge, a zealous executive, he is greater than all eee
kings, he gives liberty to all men.”
Speeches like these, striking my eardrum, resounded loudly
in my soul. To my mind the praises seemed true, since they
were accompanied by outward expressions of sincerity. Re-
ceiving them as such, my soul rose above the usual circle of
vision, expanded in its essence, and, embracing all, touched
the threshold of divine wisdom. But nothing could be com-
pared with my self-satisfaction as I uttered my commands.
I ordered my commander-in-chief to proceed with an innum-
erable host to the conquest of a country separated from me
by a whole celestial zone. “Sovereign,” he replied, “the glory
of thy name alone will conquer the people who inhabit that
land. Terror will [*68] go before thine arms, and I will return
bearing the tribute of mighty kings.” To my lord admiral
I spake: “Let my ships spread sail over all the seas, so that
strange peoples may see them; let my flag become known in
the north, east, south, and west.” “It shall be done, Your
Majesty.” And he flew to execute my command like a wind
sent to swell the sails of a ship. ““Proclaim to the farthest limits
of my realm,” I said to the keeper of the laws, “that this is the
day of my birth; let it be forever famous in the chronicles
as the day of universal amnesty. Let the prisons be thrown
open, set the prisoners free to return to their homes as people
who have strayed from the true path.” “Thy mercy, O Sover-
eign, is the mark of an infinitely generous being. I hasten to
publish the glad tidings to the fathers grieving for their chil-
dren, to the wives grieving for their husbands.” To my chief
architect I said, “Let magnificent buildings be erected [*69]
as homes for the Muses, let them be adorned with various imi-
tations of nature; and may they be as inviolate as the celestial
beings for srhior they were built.” “O wise ruler,” he replied,
“even as the elements have obeyed thy commands and, joining
forces, have in swamps and solitudes founded vast cities which
surpass in magnificence the most famous cities of antiquity,
so this labor will be light to the zealous executors of thy com-
mandments. Thou hast spoken, and the raw building materials
are already hearkening to thy voice.” “Let the hand of gen-
erosity be opened now,” I said, “and let the surplus of super-
abundance flow out to the needy, let the treasure which we
do not need return to its source.” “O most gracious ruler,
given us by the Almighty, father of thy children, enricher of
the poor, thy will be done!” At each of my commands all the
people there shouted for joy, and [*70] applause not only
accompanied my speech but even anticipated my thoughts.
Of all this company, one woman alone, who stood leaning
hard against a column, sighed grievously, while scorn and
anger flashed across her countenance. Her features were stern
and her garments simple. Her head was covered with a hat,
while all the others stood with their heads bare. “Who is
she?” I asked one who was standing near me. “She is a pil-
grim, a stranger to us; she says she is an oculist, named Clear-
of-Eye. But she is a very dangerous witch who carries venom
and poison, and gloats over grief and affliction; she is always
frowning, and she scorns and reviles everyone; in her abuse
she spares not even thy sacred head.” “Wherefore, then, is
this evildoer tolerated in my realm? But we shall deal with
her tomorrow. This is a day of grace and rejoicing. Come, my
comrades in bearing the heavy burden of government, receive
the rewards your labors and [*71] accomplishments deserve.”
Then I arose from my throne and conferred various honors
upon those present; nor were the absent ones forgotten, but
those who had received my commands with joyful counte-
nance were granted ampler signs of grace.
Then I continued my speech: “Let us go, props of my
power, buttresses of my rule, let us go and be merry after our
labor. For he who has labored deserves to partake of the fruit
of his labors. The Monarch should partake of joy, since he
dispenses joy so bountifully to all. Show us the way to the
feast you have prepared,” I said to the master of the revels.
“We shall follow you.” “Wait,” the pilgrim called to me
from her place, “wait, and come to me. I am a physician sent
to thee and thy like to open thine eyes. Oh, what blindness! ”
she exclaimed. An invisible power urged me to approach
[*72] her, although all those who surrounded me held me
back and some even used force.
“On both thine eyes there are cataracts,” said the pilgrim,
“and yet thou hast passed unhesitant judgment upon every-
thing.” Then she touched both my eyes and took off from
them a thick film, like horny skin. “Thou seest,” she said
to me, “that thou hast been blind, stone-blind. I am Truth.
The Almighty, moved to pity by the groans of thy subject
people, has sent me down from the heavenly regions to drive
away the darkness which impenetrably obscured thy vision.
I have done so. Now everything will appear before thine
eyes in its true form. Thou shalt see into the heart of things.
No longer will the serpent that hides in the deep recesses of the
soul escape thee. Thou shalt know thy faithful subjects who,
far from thee, love not thee, but their country; [*73] who
are always ready for thy defeat, if it will avenge the enslave-
ment of man.’° But they will not stir up untimely sedition
to no purpose. Call them to thee, to be thy friends. Drive
away this haughty mob that stand before thee and hide the
infamy of their souls under gilded garments. They are thy
real enemies, who dim thine eyes and bar my entry to thy
palace. Once only do I appear to kings during their whole
reign, that they may know me in my true form; but I never
abandon the dwellings of mortals. My stay is not in royal
palaces.* The guard that surrounds and watches them with
a hundred eyes by day and by night bars my entry thither.
If and when I succeed in breaking through this dense crowd,
all those who surround thee raise the scourge of persecution
and seek to cast me out of thy dwelling; therefore beware
lest I leave thee again. For then [*74] words of flattery,
emitting poisonous vapors, will again bring back thy cata-
racts, and a film impenetrable to light will cover thine eyes.
Then will thy blindness be very great and thy vision barely
suffice for one step. Everything will seem joyful to thee.
Thine ears will not be troubled by groans; every hour thy
hearing will be soothed by sweet songs. The sacrificial incense
of flattery will hover about thy vulnerable soul. Thy touch
will always feel smooth softness. Never will beneficent rough-
ness irritate thy sense of feeling. Tremble now in the face of
this imminent peril. A storm cloud will rise above thy head,
and avenging thunderbolts will be ready to strike thee down.
But I promise thee, I will remain within the borders of thy
realm. Whenever thou desirest to see me, whenever thy soul,
besieged by the wiles of flattery, thirsts for the sight of me,
call [*75] me from afar; wherever my harsh voice is heard,
there wilt thou find me. Never be afraid of my voice. If from
the midst of the people there arise a man who criticizes thy
acts, know that he is thy true friend. With no hope of re-
ward, with no servile trembling, with a sturdy voice he will
proclaim me to thee. Beware and do not dare to put him to
death as a rebel.’? Call him to thee, be hospitable to him as
to a pilgrim. For everyone who criticizes the Sovereign in
the fullness of his autocratic power is a pilgrim in the land
where all\tremble before him. Treat him well, I say, honor
him, so that he may return and tell thee ever more truth.
But such stout hearts are rare; hardly one in a whole cen-
tury appears in the world’s arena. But in order that the im-
passioned delight in the exercise of power may not put thy
vigilance to sleep, I give thee this ring, which will warn thee
against thine [*76] injustice, if thou wilt fight against it.1*
For know that thou hast it in thy power to be the greatest
murderer in the commonweal, the greatest robber, the great-
est traitor, the greatest violator of the public peace, a most
savage enemy who turns his malice against the lives of the
weak. Thine is the blame if a mother lament for her son, or
a wife for her husband, killed on the field of battle, for the
danger of being subjected to a conqueror’s yoke hardly justi-
fies the murder called war.1* Thine the blame if the field be
deserted, if the peasant’s little ones starve at their mother’s
breast, withering from lack of food. But look now at thyself
and those around thee, observe how thy commands are
executed, and if thy soul quake not with terror at the sight,
I will leave thee and forget thy palace forever.”
[*77] As she spoke, the pilgrim’s countenance seemed
radiantly happy. The sight of her filled my soul with joy. No
longer did it feel the surge of vanity and the swell of pride.
I felt at peace; the tumult of vainglory and the storm of ambi-
tion no longer disturbed my soul. My glittering garments
seemed to be stained with blood and drenched with tears.
On my fingers I saw fragments of human brains; my feet
were standing in slime. The people around me looked still
more odious. They seemed all blackened and seared within
by the dark flame of greed. At me and at one another they
threw fierce looks full of rapacity, envy, sly cunning, and
hate. My commander-in-chief, whom I had sent forth to
conquer, was wallowing in luxury and pleasure. The army
was without discipline; my soldiers were [*78] valued less
than cattle. No pains were taken to care for their health or
their provisioning; their lives counted for nothing; they were
deprived of their fixed and proper pay, which was misspent
on unnecessary military frippery. A majority of the new re-
cruits died as a result of neglect by their superiors or because
of their unnecessary and untimely severity. The money in-
tended for the maintenance of the troops was in the hands of
the master of the revels. Medals for military distinction were
awarded, not for bravery, but for base servility. I saw before
me a renowned military commander, whom I had honored
with outstanding marks of my favor. Now I saw clearly that
his whole distinction lay in pandering to the lust of his supe-
rior. He had had no occasion to show bravery, for he had
not even seen the enemy from a distance. From such warriors
[*79] I had expected new laurels. I turned away from a thou-
sand calamities that unfolded before my eyes.
My ships, which I had ordered to sail the farthest seas,
I saw coasting near the mouth of the harbor. The admiral
who had flown on the wings of the wind to carry out my
orders was stretching his limbs on a soft bed, intoxicated
with voluptuous desire, in the embraces of a hired inciter
of his lust. On a chart, executed at his command, of a com-
pletely imaginary voyage, there were already visible in all
parts of the world new islands abounding in fruits appropriate
to their various climates. Vast lands and innumerable peoples
were created by the pens of these new voyagers. By the gleam
of nocturnal lights they had already written a glowing descrip-
tion, in a flowery and splendid style, [*80] of this voyage
and the discoveries made on it. Golden covers had already
been prepared to adorn this very important work. O Cook!
Why did you pass your life in travail and privations? Why
did you end it so miserably? If you had boarded these ships,
you would have begun your voyage in delightful ease, and in
delightful ease you would have ended it, and you would have
made just as many discoveries while sitting in one place, and
(in my kingdom) you would have been just as famous, for you
would have been honored by your Sovereign.”
The achievement of which, in my blindness, my soul was
most proud, namely, the abolition of the death penalty and
the granting of amnesty to prisoners, had hardly any visible
effect on the vast complex of governmental activities. My
commands had either been completely violated by being mis-
applied, or had not had the desired effect because of distorted
interpretation and dilatory execution. Mercy had come to be
bought and sold, and [*81] the auctioneer’s hammer knocked
down compassion and generosity to the highest bidder. In-
stead of being thought merciful by my subjects because of
the amnesty I had ordered, I passed among them for a cheat,
hypocrite, and wicked play-actor. “Keep thy mercy,” thou-
sands of voices shouted, ‘“‘do not proclaim it to us in high-
sounding words, if thou dost not intend to carry it out. Do
not add insult to injury, do not make our burden heavier by
making us feel it more keenly. We were peacefully asleep,
thou hast disturbed our sleep when we did not want to wake
up, since we had nothing to wake up for.” In the construction
of cities I saw only the waste of the government’s money, fre-
quently drenched with the blood and tears of my subjects.
In the erection of magnificent buildings the waste was often
accompanied by a misunderstanding of true art. I saw that
their internal and external arrangements lacked even the
slightest particle of taste. They seemed to belong to the age
of the Goths and Vandals. In the home prepared for the
Muses [*82] I did not see the inspiring streams of Castalia
and Hippocrene; ** limping art crept, earthbound, scarcely
daring to raise its glances above the levels sanctioned by tra-
dition. Bending over the drawings of the building, the archi-
tects were not thinking about how to make it beautiful but
about how to make money out of it. I was nauseated with
my ostentatious vanity and turned my eyes away. But my
soul was hurt most of all by the results of my liberality. In
my blindness I had thought that public funds not needed for
governmental purposes could not be spent in any better way
than on succour for the indigent, clothing for the naked, food
for the hungry, rescue for those suffering under adverse cir-
cumstances, or to reward excellence and merit that do not
find their joy in wealth. But how sad it was to see that my
generosity poured more wealth upon the rich, the flatterer,
the false friend, the murderer, sometimes indeed the secret
murderer, [*83] the traitor and violator of the public trust,
the clever sycophant who knew my desires and pandered to
my weaknesses, the woman who gloried in her shamelessness.
Barely, almost imperceptibly, the thin wellsprings of my gen-
erosity trickled down to modest worth and bashful merit.
Tears poured from my eyes and hid from me the miserable
objects of my foolish generosity. Now I saw clearly that the
honors I had given out always fell into the hands of the un-
worthy. In the quest for honors, which mortals dream of, in-
experienced worth, struck with the first gleam of these sup-
posed blessings, began the race evenly with flattery and mean-
ness of soul. But starting awkwardly, it was always exhausted
after the first few steps and was fated to content itself with its
own approval, in the conviction that [*84] worldly honors
are dust and ashes. Seeing that the world was out of joint as
a result of my weakness and the trickery of my ministers;
that my affection was wasted upon a woman who sought
in my love satisfaction only for her vanity and who sought
to please me only with her outward appearance, while her
heart felt only loathing for me, I shouted in the madness of
my anger. “Unworthy criminals, evildoers! Tell me, where-
fore have you abused your Sovereign’s trust? Stand now
before your judge. Tremble, ye who have grown hardened in
evil. How can you justify your deeds? What can you say in
excuse? Here he is; I will call him from his:hut of humility.’*
Come,” I called to an old man whom I saw at the border of
my vast realm, half-hidden in a moss-covered hut, “come and
lighten my burden; come and restore peace to my anxious
[*85] heart and troubled mind.” As I said this, I saw afresh
the responsibility of my high office, recognized the vastness
of my duty, and understood whence proceeded my right
and my power. I trembled inwardly and was terrified by the
responsibility of my stewardship. My blood surged wildly,
and I awoke. Even before I was fully conscious, I clutched
my finger, but it bore no ring of thorns.”® If only it would
always stay on the little finger of a King!
Ruler of the world, if, when you read my dream, you
smile scornfully or knit your brow, know that the pilgrim
whom I saw has flown far away from you and disdains your
palace.
<place_7>[*86] PODBEREZ’E</place_7>
I could hardly wake up from the heroic sleep in which |
had dreamt so much. My head was heavier than lead, worse
than a drunkard’s head would be after a drunken bout a week
long. I was in no condition to continue my journey and be
jolted in a hard wooden cart (for my carriage had no springs).
I picked up my book of home remedies and looked for a cure
for headache caused by delirium while asleep or awake. Al-
though I always carry a stock of medicine with me, yet, in
accordance with the proverb, “enough stupidity in every wise
man,” * I had taken no precautions against delirium; hence
my head, when I reached the next post station, was worse than
a wooden block.
I recalled that my nurse of blessed memory, [*87] Pras-
kov’ya Klement’evna, called Pyatnitsa in honor of the Saint,”
had been very fond of coffee, and that she used to say it was
good for a headache. “When I have drunk five cups,” she
would say, “I can see straight again, but without it I’d be
dead in three days.”
I was taking my nurse’s medicine, but, not being used to
drinking down five cups in a row, I offered what was left of
the coffee they had made for me to a young man who was
sitting on the same bench with me but in the other corner by
the window. “Thank you very much,” he said, as he took the
cup of coffee. His friendly appearance, frank expression, and
polite manner seemed out of keeping with his long coat and
hair slicked down with kvas.* Reader, forgive my inference:
I was born and grew up in the capital, and if a man’s hair
is not curled and powdered, I think he is not worth noticing.
If you too are a country bumpkin and do not powder your
hair, do [*88] not condemn me if I do not notice you and
pass by on the other side.
After exchanging a few words with my new acquaintance,
we soon found ourselves on friendly terms. I learned that he
was from the Novgorod Seminary and was walking to Peters-
burg to visit his uncle, who was a secretary in the provincial
administration. But his chief purpose was to find a chance
to study. “We still need a great deal of aid to learning in our
country,” he said. “The knowledge of Latin alone cannot
satisfy a mind hungry for learning. Virgil, Horace, Livy,
even Tacitus I know almost by heart, but when I compare the
information of my fellow seminarists with what I have had the
good luck to learn, I see that our school belongs to a bygone
age. We know all the classical authors, but we know more
of the critical interpretation of their texts [*89] than of
what still makes them so appealing today, and promises them
eternal life. We are taught philosophy, we go through logic,
metaphysics, ethics, theology, but, as Kuteykin says in “The
Minor,’ * we shall reach the end of our philosophical training
and then turn back again. Is it any wonder? Aristotle and
scholasticism still hold sway in the seminaries. By good luck
I became acquainted with the family of a government official
in Novgorod, had a chance to read some of his books, and
learned some French and German. What a difference there
is between the enlightenment of the times when Latin alone
was used in the schools, and the present! What a help it is to
learning, when the sciences are not mysteries open only to
those who have mastered Latin, but are taught in the native
tongue! But why,” he continued, [*9o] after interrupting his
own speech, “why do they not, in our country, institute
higher schools of learning in which the sciences are taught
in the vernacular, in Russian? The instruction would be more
accessible to all; enlightenment would reach everyone sooner,
and after one generation there would be two hundred edu-
cated men instead of one Latin scholar; at least in every court
there would be one member who understood what juris-
prudence or legal science is. My God!” he continued ex-
citedly, “if one were to cite examples from our judges’ decrees
? and opinions on cases! What would Grotius, Montesquieu,
or Blackstone say?”
“Have you read Blackstone?”
“I have read the first two parts, in the Russian translation.®
It would not be a bad idea to compel our judges to have this
book instead of the calendar of saints, and to make them con-
sult it more frequently than the calendar. [*91] How can
one help being sorry,” he repeated, “that we have no schools
in which the sciences are taught in the native tongue!”
The entrance of the postilion made it impossible to continue
our conversation. I had just time enough to tell the seminarist
that his wish would soon be fulfilled, that a decree had already
been issued for the foundation of new ‘universities where the
sciences would be taught as he wished.® “It’s high time, sir,
it’s high time — .”
While I was paying my fare to the postilion, the seminarist
went out. As he left, he dropped a small bundle of papers. I
picked them up and did not give them back to him. Don’t give
me away, gentle reader. On this condition I'll tell you what I
pilfered. When you have read it, I am sure you will not be-
tray my theft, for it is written in the Russian law that not
only he who has stolen is a thief, but also he who has received
the stolen goods. I must confess that my hands are [*92]
not clean: whenever I see something that looks sensible, I im-
mediately appropriate it; see to it that you do not leave your
ideas lying around unguarded. Read what my seminarist has
to say: ‘He who compared the moral world to a wheel expressed
a great truth. Perhaps he did nothing else but this: he observed
the circular shape of the earth and of the other great bodies
borne in space and simply gave expression to what he saw.
Advancing in the knowledge of nature, men may perhaps
discover the secret connection between spiritual or moral
and physical or natural substances, and learn that the cause of
all changes, transformations, and perversions in the moral or
spiritual world may perhaps be dependent on the circular
form of our terrestrial abode and of the other bodies belong-
ing to the solar system, which, like the earth, are globular and
revolve [*93] on their axes. This sounds like a Martinist,
a pupil of Swedenborg.’ No, my friend, I eat and drink
not merely to sustain life, but because in doing so I find a con-
siderable sensual enjoyment. And I will confess to you, as
I would to my spiritual father, that I would much rather
spend the night with a pretty girl and fall asleep in her em-
brace, intoxicated with passion, than bury myself in Hebrew
or Arabic letters, in ciphers, or Egyptian hieroglyphics, or try
to separate my soul from my body and wander about over the
vast stretches of fantastic speculation, like the ancient and
modern spiritual knights. When I die there will be time
enough for the incomprehensible, and my soul will have its
fill of wandering about.
“Look back; the time is still close behind our shoulders
when superstition reigned, and all its followers: ignorance,
slavery, the Inquisition, and many others. Has it been long
[*94] since Voltaire cried out till he was hoarse, against su-
perstition? Has it been long since Frederick was its implacable
enemy not only in his words and deeds, but, with still more
terrible effectiveness, by his sovereign example? ® But in this
world everything reverts to its former state, for everything
has its origin in destruction. An animal, a plant, is born, and
grows, in order to beget its kind; then dies and yields its
place to them. Nomadic peoples gather in cities, found king-
doms, mature, become famous, grow weak, become exhausted,
and fall. Their dwellings are lost to sight, their very names are
forgotten. Christian society at first was meek and peaceful,
and hid in desert places and caves; then grew strong, strayed
from its path, and fell into superstition. In its deviation it went
the usual way of all nations; it exalted its chieftain, [*95] ex-
tended his power, and the Pope became the mightiest of kings.
Luther began the reformation, created a schism, withdrew
from under the papal power, and had many followers. The
structure of prejudice in favor of the papal power began to
crumble, and superstition, too, began to disappear. Truth
found its devotees, made a breach in the thick wall of preju-
dices, but did not long persist in this path. Freedom of thought
turned into unbridled license. Nothing was sacred; violent
hands were laid on everything. When it reaches its utmost
limits, free thought will turn back in the other direction. This
change in the manner of thinking is imminent in our time. We
have not yet reached the farthest extreme of unchecked free
thought, but already many are beginning to turn to supersti-
tion. Open the latest mystical works, and you will think we
are back in the days of scholasticism and disputations, when
the human mind busied itself with arguments without con-
sidering whether there was any sense in [*96] these argu-
ments; when, as a problem worthy of philosophy, to be solved
by seekers after truth, they posed the question how many
angels could stand on the point of a pin.
“If aberration is to be the fate of our descendants, if they
abandon nature and chase after phantoms, then it would be a
very useful labor for a writer to show us from former events
the progress of the human mind, when it broke through the
mist of prejudices and began to pursue truth in its loftiest
flights, and when, so to speak, wearied by its vigils, it began
once again to abuse its strength, and, gripped by fear, to
descend into the mist of prejudice and superstition. The
work of such a writer will not be in vain, for, in disclosing the
progress of our thoughts toward truth and falsehood, he will
save at least some from following the path of destruction
and will obstruct the advance of ignorance. Happy [*97] the
author if by his work he is able to enlighten even one man,
happy if he has implanted virtue even in one heart.
“We may consider ourselves fortunate, for we shall not
live to see the extreme disgrace of intelligent beings. Our im-
mediate descendants may be even more fortunate than we. But
the miasma which has been gathering in the mire of decay
is already seeping up and is predestined to overcast the whole
horizon. We shall be fortunate if we do not live to see the
new Mohammed; the hour of aberration will be delayed for a
time. Know that when in speculative thought, in judgments of
things moral and spiritual, there begins a ferment, and a strong
and enterprising man appears — a man strong for truth or for
falsehood — then there will follow a change of powers, and
a change of creeds.
“If, on the ladder on which human reason must descend
into the darkness of error, we point out [*98] what is ridic-
ulous and do some good by laughing at it, we shall be thought
worthy of praise.
“Wandering from speculation to speculation, my beloved
brethren, beware lest you stray into the path of the following
investigations.
“Akiba said: ‘I once followed Rabbi Josua into the secret
place and learned three things from him. I learned, (1) that
we must turn ourselves, not Eastward and Westward, but
Northward and Southward. I learned, (2) that we must
evacuate, not standing, but sitting. I learned, (3) that we
should wipe our rear not with our right hand, but with our
left.’ Upon this Ben Hasas objected, ‘Are you so hardened in
impudence as to watch your master when he is evacuating?’
He replied, “These are secrets of our Law, to learn which I
was obliged so to do.’ ”
<place_8>[*99] Novgorod</place_8>
Be proud, ye vain founders of cities, be proud, ye founders
of kingdoms! Dream that the glory of your name will endure
forevermore. Pile stone upon stone, to the very clouds. Carve
in stone images of your exploits, and inscriptions that proclaim
your deeds. Lay firm foundations of government in unchange-
able laws. Time with its sharp rows of teeth laughs at your
presumption. Where are the wise laws of Solon and Lycuregus,
which established the liberties of Athens and of Sparta? In
books. And in their former abode slaves are pastured under
the scepter of autocracy. Where is rich Troy? Where is Car-
thage? You can hardly see the place where once they proud-
ly stood. Does the imperishable sacrifice send its smoke to the
One Being in the famous temples of ancient Egypt? Their
magnificent ruins serve [*1oo] as a place of refuge for bleat-
ing cattle at the time of the midday heat. They are not
watered by joyous tears of thanksgiving to the Almighty
Father, but by the stinking evacuations of animals. O pride, O
human arrogance, behold this and learn how contemptible
you are!
With such thoughts I reached Novgorod and looked at the
multitude of monasteries which lay around it.
They say that all these monasteries, even those which now
are fifteen versts distant from the city, were at one time within
its precincts, and that a hundred thousand warriors could come
forth from within its walls. It is known from the Chronicles
that Novgorod had a popular government. They had princes,
but these had little power. All the power of government was
centered in the posadniki and tysyatskie.' The people in its
assembly, the Veche, was the real sovereign. The territory of
Novgorod extended [*1o1] even beyond the Volga in the
north. This free state belonged to the Hanseatic League.” ‘The
ancient saying, “Who can stand against God and Great Nov-
gorod?” may serve as proof of its power. Trade was the cause
of its rise. Internal discord and a rapacious neighbor brought
about its fall.
While crossing the bridge, I left my carriage to enjoy the
sight of the flowing Volkhov. I could not help remembering
the deed of Tsar Ivan Vasil’evich after the capture of Nov-
gorod. Stung by the resistance of the republic, this proud,
bestial, but clever ruler wanted to destroy it completely. I
can see him standing on the bridge with his battle axe, as some
report, sacrificing the elders and chief men of Novgorod
to his fury. But what right did he have to rage against them?
What right [*102] did he have to take Novgorod for him-
self? * Was it because the first Russian grand princes had lived
in this city? Or because he styled himself Tsar of all Russia?
Or because the Novgorodians were of Slavic origin? But what
avails right, when might prevails? Can right live, when a de-
cision is sealed with the blood of the nations? Can right exist,
when no force exists to make it effective? Much has been
written about the law of nations, and it is often referred to,
but the teachers of the law have not considered whether
there can be a judge between nations. When hostility arises
between them, when hatred or self-interest drives one against
another, their judge is the sword. He who has fallen or been
disarmed is guilty, and without gainsaying obeys this decision,
and there is no appeal from it. That is why Novgorod be-
longed to Tsar Ivan Vasil’evich. [*103] That is why he de-
stroyed it and appropriated its smoking ruins. Necessity, the
desire for safety and security build kingdoms; discord, cun-
ning, and force destroy them. What then is the law of nations?‘
The nations, say the learned in the law, stand in the same re-
lationship to each other as one man to another in the state of
nature. Question: What are man’s rights in the state of nature?
Answer: Look at him, He is naked, hungry, thirsty. He ap-
propriates everything he can seize for the satisfaction of his
needs.’ If anything tries to stand in his way, he removes the
obstacle, destroys it, and takes what he wants. Question: If, on
the way to satisfy his needs, he meets his like, if, for example,
two hungry men try to satisfy their appetite with the same
morsel, [*104] which of them has the greater right to it? An-
swer: [he one who takes it. Question: Who takes the morsel?
Answer: The stronger one. Is it possible that this is the law
of nature, is it possible that this is the foundation of the law of
nations? The examples of all times bear witness to the fact that
law without power has always been considered, in practice, as
an empty word. Question: What is civil law? Answer: He
who travels by post does not trouble himself about nonsense
but thinks only about getting his horses as quickly as possible.
From the Chronicle of Novgorod. The Novgorodians waged
war with the Grand Prince Yaroslav Yaroslavich and con-
cluded a written treaty of peace.
The Novgorodians composed a charter for the defense of
their liberties and confirmed it with fifty-eight seals.
The Novgorodians prohibited the circulation within their
territory of coined money introduced by the Tatars.
[*1o05] Novgorod began to coin its own money in the year 1420.
Novgorod belonged to the Hanseatic League.
In Novgorod there was a bell, at the tolling of which the
people assembled at the Veche for the consideration of public
business. Tsar Ivan took the charter and the bell away from the
Novgorodians. Then: In the year 1500, in the year 1600, in the year 1700,
in the year —, in the year —, Novgorod still stood in the same
old place. But one can’t think always of times past, one can’t always
think hopefully of the morrow. If —I reflected —I look at
the sky all the time, without noticing what’s under foot, I'll
soon stumble and fall into the mire. No matter how concerned
I am, Novgorod cannot be restored to its ancient glory. The
future will show what God will grant. Now it is time for
supper. I will go to see Karp Dement’ich.
“Well, well! Welcome! Whence has God brought you?”
my friend Karp Dement’ich, formerly a merchant of the third
guild, but now an honorable citizen,” said to me. As the prov-
erb has it, [*106] the lucky fellow arrives when the table
is set. “I beg you to dine with us.”
“But what is the occasion for this feast?”
“My benefactor, I married off my son yesterday.”
“Benefactor indeed,” I thought; “not without good cause
does he call me that.” I helped him, together with many an-
other, to be enrolled as an honorable citizen. In 1737, I think,
my grandfather apparently gave somebody a promissory note
for one thousand rubles; to whom he gave it, I do not know.
In 1780 Karp Dement’ich bought the note somewhere and had
it protested. He came to me with a clever lawyer, and they
were exceedingly kind to me, for they took only the interest
for fifty years, and let me keep the principal. Karp Dement’ich
is a grateful man. “Daughter-in-law, some vodka for the un-
expected guest!”
“T do not drink vodka.”
“At least a sip.”
“To the health of the newlyweds!” And we sat down to
supper. On one side of me sat the host’s son, and on the other Karp
Dement’ich seated his young daughter-in-law.
[*107] Let us interrupt the story, dear reader. Give me a
pencil and a small sheet of paper. For your amusement I will
sketch the whole honorable company, and so make you a
participant in the marriage feast, even if you are trapping
beavers in the Aleutian Islands.® If I do not give you exact por-
traits, I shall content myself with silhouettes. Lavater ® has
taught us how to tell from them who is clever and who is
stupid. Karp Dement’ich has a gray beard, extending fourteen
inches downward from his lower lip. His nose is a knob, his
eyes are deep-set, his eyebrows pitch-black; he greets every-
one with a handshake, strokes his beard, calls everybody his
benefactor. Aksin’ya Parfent’evna is his beloved spouse. At
sixty she is white as snow and red as a poppy; she constantly
compresses her lips in a circle. She drinks no wine, only half a
cup before dinner to keep the guests company, and a glass of
vodka in the pantry. Her husband’s clerk keeps a record of it
for his master. [*108] At Aksin’ya Parfent’evna’s order they
buy an annual supply of three poods of face powder from
Rzhev *° and thirty pounds of rouge. Her husband’s clerks
are her lackeys. Aleksey Karpovich is my neighbor at the
table. He has neither moustache nor beard, but his nose is
already crimson; he blinks, his hair is clipped in a circle, he
bows like a goose, shakes his head, and smoothes his hair. He
had once been a clerk in a liquor shop in Petersburg. When he
measures goods, he measures some two inches short on each
yard: that’s why his father loves him like himself. When he
was fifteen, he boxed his mother’s ears. Praskov’ya Denisovna,
his bride, is white and red. Her teeth are black as coal. Her
eyebrows are thin as thread and blacker than soot. In com-
pany she sits with downcast eyes, but all day long she never
leaves the window, where she stares at all the men. In the eve-
ning she stands at the gate. She has one black eye — a first-day
present from her beloved [*109] bridegroom; if you are
quick-witted, you will know what for.
But, dear reader, you are already yawning. I had better
stop making silhouettes. You are right, there will be nothing
but nose after nose, lips and still more lips. And I don’t know
how you will be able to tell face powder from rouge on a
silhouette. “Karp Dement’ich, what are you dealing in nowadays?
You don’t go to Petersburg, don’t haul flax, nor buy sugar,
coffee, or dyes. I had thought your business was not unprofit-
able.” “I was almost ruined by it, but God just saved me. One
year I made a tolerable profit and built my wife this house
here. Next year the flax crop was a failure and I couldn’t de-
liver what I had contracted to, That’s why I went out of
business.” “I remember, Karp Dement’ich, in payment for thirty
thousand rubles advanced to you, you sent your creditors one
thousand poods of flax to divide up [*110] among themselves.”
“Believe me, on my conscience, I couldn’t do any better.”
“Of course, that was the year when there was a shortage
of foreign goods, too. You had received advances of twenty
thousand — . Yes, I remember; then came the headache.”
“Truly, my benefactor, my head hurt me so badly that it
almost cracked. How can my creditors complain? I gave them
all my property.”
“Three kopeks on the ruble.” ™
“Not at all: fifteen.”
“And your wife’s house?”
“How could I touch it? It is not mine.”
“But tell me, what business are you engaged in?”
“None, really none. Ever since I went bankrupt, my son has
been carrying on the business. ‘This summer, thank God, he
has delivered twenty thousand rubles’ worth of flax.”
“Next year, of course, he will contract for fifty thousand,
have half the money advanced to him, and build a house for
his young wife.”
Aleksey Karpovich just smiled.
“My benefactor, you are an old joker. [*111] We've talked
enough nonsense. Let us fall to.”
“You know I do not drink.”
“At least a sip.”
“A sip, a sip!” I felt that my cheeks were beginning to glow,
and before the end of the feast I would have been as drunk
as the rest. But fortunately one cannot sit forever at the
table, just as one cannot always be wise. And for the same
reason that I sometimes play the fool and wander in my mind,
I remained sober at the wedding feast.
When I left my friend Karp Dement’ich I fell to musing.
The commercial law, now universally established, that is, the
law imposing severe and swift punishment for defaulting on
commercial obligations, I had until now considered as a piece
of legislation which upheld confidence. I had considered it a
happy invention of modern times for the promotion of trade,
an invention which had never occurred to the ancients, But
why, if a man who gives a promissory note [*112] is dishonest,
is it only a worthless scrap of paper? Would trade disappear,
if there were no stern punishment for defaulting on notes?
Should not the creditor know whom he can trust? For whom
should the law be more concerned, the creditor or the debtor?
Who deserves more consideration in the eyes of humanity,
the creditor who lost his capital because he did not know his
borrower, or the debtor in chains, in prison? On the one side,
credulity; on the other, almost theft. The former lent money,
depending on the sternness of the law, and the latter —.
But if the punishment for defaulting on notes were not so
severe? Then there would be no place for credulity, and there
would perhaps be no cheating in transactions concerning
notes. . . . I began to think again, the old system went to the
Devil, and I went to bed with an empty head.
<place_9>[*113] BRONNITSY</place_9>
While they were changing the horses for my carriage, I
decided to visit the high hill near Bronnitsy, on which they
say —in ancient times, I think before the coming of the
Slavs — there stood a temple famous for its oracles, which
many northern rulers came to hear. It is said that in the place
where the village of Bronnitsy now stands, there stood the
city of Kholmograd, which was renowned in the ancient his-
tory of the North.* Now a small church is built on the site of
the famous ancient fane.
As I climbed the hill, I imagined that I was transported into
antiquity, and that I had come to have the future revealed to
me by the Almighty, and to find peace from my perplexity.
Divine awe [*114] seized my limbs, my breast began to heave,
my eyes grew dull, their light was darkened. I heard a voice
like thunder proclaiming: “Fool! Wherefore dost thou desire
to pierce through the mystery which I have hid from mortals
behind the impenetrable shroud of the unknown? Where-
fore, audacious one, wilt thou learn that which only eternal
thought can grasp? Know that thine ignorance of the future
is in accord with the frailty of thy nature. Know that fore-
known bliss loses its sweetness through long expectation,
that the charm of present joy, when it comes upon exhausted
senses, can never produce in the soul the delightful flutter that
unexpected joy produces. Know that foreknown sorrow pre-
maturely robs one of peace, and poisons the pleasures which
one might have enjoyed if one had not known when they
would end. What seekest [*115] thou, foolish child? My wis-
dom has implanted in thy mind and heart all that thou needest.
Appeal to them in the day of sorrow, and thou wilt find com-
forters. Appeal to them in the day of gladness, and thou wilt
find restraints upon thy presumptuous happiness. Return to
thy home, return to thy family; quiet thy troubled thoughts,
enter into thine innermost soul, and there thou wilt find my
Godhead, there thou wilt hear my prophecy.”
The peal of a mighty thunderbolt hurled by Perun? re-
sounded down the valley. I regained my senses. As I reached
the top of the hill and beheld the church, I raised my hands
to heaven. “O Lord,” I cried, “this is Thy temple, a temple,
they say, of the one, true God. In this place, which is now
Thy house, they say there once stood a temple of error. But
I cannot believe, Almighty God, that man ever addressed his
soul’s prayers to any other being but Thee. Thy mighty right
hand [*116] extends invisibly in all directions and compels
even him who denies Thy all-powerful will, to recognize the
architect and preserver of nature. If a mortal in his error calls
Thee by strange, unbecoming, and bestial names, his worship
nonetheless aspires to Thee, Ever-living Lord, and he trem-
bles before Thy might. Jehovah, Jupiter, Brahma, God of
Abraham, God of Moses, God of Confucius, God of Zoroaster,
God of Socrates, God of Marcus Aurelius, God of the Chris-
tians, O my God! Thou art everywhere the same, the One. *
When mortals in their error seemed to be worshiping not
Thee alone, they were deifying Thine incomparable forces,
Thine inimitable deeds. Thy almighty power, felt every-
where and in everything, has everywhere and in everything
been worshiped. The atheist who denies Thee, but recognizes
the immutable law of nature, thereby proclaims Thy glory,
[*117] lauding Thee even more than our songs of praise.
For, moved to the depths of his soul by Thy wondrous works,
he stands trembling before them. Most gracious Father, Thou
seekest a true heart and spotless soul; they are open every-
where for Thy coming. Descend, O Lord, and enthrone Thy-
self in them.”
I stood for a few moments, removed from the objects around
me, lost in profound contemplation. Then, raising my eyes
and glancing at the nearby dwellings, I cried, “Behold the
miserable hovels of the downfallen, in the place where once
a great city reared its proud walls. Not even the smallest trace
of them remains. Reason, demanding conclusive and palpable
evidence, refuses even to believe the story. And all that we
see will pass away; all will fall to ruins; all will become dust.
But a certain mysterious voice says to me, ‘Something will
forever live.’ ”
[*118] The stars shall fade away, the sun himself
Grow dim with age, and nature sink in years,
But thou shalt flourish in immortal youth,
Unhurt amidst the wars of elements,
The wrecks of matter, and the crush of worlds.*
<place_10>[*119] ZAYTSOVO</place_10>
In the post station at Zaytsovo I found my old friend Mr.
Krestyankin, I had known him since childhood. We were
not often in the same town, but our conversations, although
infrequent, had been frank. Mr. Krestyankin had long been
in the Military Service, but becoming disgusted with its
cruelties, especially in time of war, when great violence 1s
justified in the name of military necessity, had had himself
transferred to the Civil Service. Unfortunately for him, even
in the Civil Service he did not escape what he had sought
to avoid in leaving the Military. He had a very sensitive soul
and a humane heart. His admittedly excellent qualities pro-
cured for him the position of presiding judge in a criminal
court. At first he had not wanted to accept this post, but
after some reflection he had said [*120] to me: “My friend,
what a vast field is opened up to me for the satisfaction of my
heart’s desire! What an exercise for a gentle heart! We will
break the scepter of cruelty, which so often oppresses the
shoulders of innocence. Let the prisons be opened, and may
awkward weakness and careless inexperience never see them,
and may accident nevermore be accounted a crime! O my
friend! In the execution of my duty I will wring tears from
parents for their children and sighs from husbands and wives
for their mates, but these tears will be blessed tears of regen-
eration. And the tears of suffering innocence and simplicity
of soul will dry up. How this thought delights me! Come,
let us hasten my departure. Maybe my immediate presence is
needed there. By procrastination I may become a murderer,
if I fail to anticipate an imprisonment or an accusation by a
pardon or a release from chains.”
[*121] With such thoughts my friend had started out for
the scene of his labors. How surprised I was to learn from him
that he had resigned from the service and intended to live
the rest of his life in retirement. “My friend, I had imagined,”
Mr. Krestyankin said to me, “that in the execution of my
duties I would reap a rich harvest of spiritual satisfaction.
Instead of that I found in it only gall and thorns. Now, hav-
ing grown sick of it and no longer being able to do any good,
I have abandoned my place to a truly rapacious beast. In a
brief time he has won praise by his speedy decision of long-
delayed cases, while I was considered a procrastinator. Some-
times they even considered me venal because I did not hasten
to aggravate the lot of those unfortunates who are frequently
driven into crime against their will. Before I entered the
Civil Service, I had won the flattering name of a humane com-
manding officer. Now the very quality [*122] of which my
heart was so proud is called weakness or intolerable indul-
gence. I saw my decisions ridiculed for the very thing which
made them valuable; I saw them rendered nugatory. I ob-
served with contempt that in order to release a real evildoer
and dangerous member of society, or to punish alleged crimes
with the forfeiture of property, honor, and life, my superior,
who was unable to move me to an illegal acquittal of crime or
to a sentence against innocence, persuaded my associates to
do what he wanted; and frequently I saw my well-meant
dispositions of cases go up like smoke. But my associates, as
a reward for their disgraceful subserviency, received honors,
as tainted in my sight as they were speciously enticing in
theirs. In troublesome cases, when my belief in [*123] the
innocence of the accused inclined me to mercy, I often had
recourse to the law, hoping to find in it support in my uncer-
tainty; but instead of mercy I frequently found in it cruelty,
which had its origin not in the law itself but in its obsolete-
ness. The disproportion between punishment and crime often
moved me to tears. I saw (could it be otherwise?) that the
law judges deeds and does not concern itseif with their causes.
And the last case that involved considerations of this sort
compelled me to resign from the service. For, being unable
to save miserable offenders who had been dragged into crime
by the mighty hand of fate, I did not want to become a guilty
participant in their destruction. Unable to alleviate their lot,
I sought escape from cruelty and washed my hands in my
innocence.
“In our province there lived a nobleman who several years
before [*124] had resigned from the service. Here is his serv-
ice record. He began at Court as a stoker, and was promoted
to lackey, chamber lackey, then butler. I do not know what
virtues are required for advancement in the Court Service.*
But I do know that he was passionately fond of wine. After
he had been a butler for some fifteen years, he was sent to the
Heralds’ College to establish his rank. But feeling his unfitness
for affairs, he petitioned for retirement, and was rewarded
with the rank of Collegiate Assessor,? with which he came,
six years ago, to his birthplace, that is, to our province. Such
particular attachment to one’s native place often has its source
in vanity. A man of low estate who has been raised to the peer-
age, or a poor man who has acquired wealth, after shaking off
all restraint of modesty, the last and weakest [*125] root of
virtue, prefers to display his pomp and conceit in the place of
his birth.* There the assessor soon had a chance to buy a vil-
lage,* in which he settled down with his not inconsiderable
family. If a Hogarth® were born in our country, he would
find a fertile field for his caricatures in Mr. Assessor’s family.
But I am a poor artist. If I were able, with Lavater’s ® penetra-
tion, to read a man’s innermost thoughts in his features, then
I could make the picture of the assessor’s family worthy of
attention. Since I lack these qualities, I will make their ac-
tions speak for themselves, for actions are always the best in-
dices of spiritual development.
“Being of very lowly origin himself, Mr. Assessor now saw
himself as master of several hundred of his own kind. This
turned his head. He is not the only one who might justly
complain that the possession of power had turned his head.
[*126] He considered himself an exalted being, and the
peasants — cattle given to him (he almost thought his power
over them proceeded from God) to be used for work at his
arbitrary will. He was avaricious, miserly, cruel by nature,
irritable, and hence overbearing with the weak. From this
you can imagine how he treated his peasants. They had paid
a commutation tax to their old master, but their new one made
them work on his fields, took away all their land, bought all
their cattle at a price which he determined, compelled them
to work seven days a week for him, and, lest they starve, fed
them in the yard of the manor, and only once a day, at that;
though he gave a monthly allowance to a few as a special
grace. If he thought anyone was lazy, he flogged him with
switches, whips, sticks, or cat-o’-nine-tails, according to the
degree of laziness. In regard to real [*127] crimes, such as
robbery, not of him but of others, he said not a word. It looked
as though he wanted to resurrect in his village the customs
of ancient Lacedaemon or the Zaporog Sech." It so happened
that his peasants, to obtain food, robbed one traveler and killed
another. He did not surrender them to the court, but hid them,
and declared to the Government that they had run away.
He felt that it would be no profit to him to have them flogged
and sent off to hard labor for their crime. If one of his peasants
stole something from him, he had him beaten just as for laziness
or for a daring or witty answer; and in addition, he put fetters
on their feet and a yoke on their neck. I could tell you of
many more of his wise arrangements, but this will do for the
description of my hero. His spouse had full power over the
village women. Her sons and daughters were her aides in the
execution of her commands, [*128] as they were also of their
father’s. For they made it their rule not to take the peasants
from their work for any reason. For manorial servants they
had a boy they had bought in Moscow, a hairdresser for
their daughters, and an old woman who served as cook. They
had no coachman and no horses; the master always drove the
plough horses. The sons flogged the peasants with whips and
cat-o’-nine-tails. The daughters struck the faces of the women
and girls and pulled their hair. The sons in their free time dis-
ported themselves in the village and in the fields, flirting and
carrying on with girls and women, not one of whom escaped
violation. The daughters, not having any suitors, took out
their boredom on the spinning women, many of whom they
seriously injured. Judge for yourself, my friend, what must
be the end of such behavior. I have observed from a great
many examples that the Russian people are very patient and
long-suffering, [*129] but when they reach the end of their
patience, nothing can restrain them from terrible cruelty.
This is just what happened in the case of the assessor. The
occasion for it was provided by the brutal and dissolute, or
say rather the beastly act of one of his sons.
“In his village there was a good-looking peasant girl who
was betrothed to a young peasant of the same village. The
assessor's middle son took a liking to her and used every
possible means to win her love for himself; but the girl re-
mained true to the promise she had made to her sweetheart,
- a steadfastness rare but still possible among the peasantry.
The wedding was to have taken place on a Sunday. In ac-
cordance with the custom current on many landed estates,
the bridegroom’s father went with his son to the manor house
and brought two poods of bridal honey to his master. The
young ‘nobleman’ decided to use this last moment [*130]
for the gratification of his lust. He took both his brothers
with him and, having summoned the bride to the courtyard
by a strange boy, gagged her and carried her off to a shed. Un-
able to utter a sound, she struggled with all her strength
against her young master’s beastly purpose. At last, overcome
by the three of them, she had to yield to force, and the vile
monster was just about to carry out his long-cherished pur-
pose when the bridegroom, returning from the manor, en-
tered the yard, saw one of the young masters near the shed,
and guessed their evil intention. He called his father to help
him and flew faster than lightning to the shed. What a spec-
tacle presented itself to him! Just as he got there they closed
the doors of the shed, but the combined strength of the two
brothers could not stem the onrush of the maddened bride-
groom. Nearby he picked up [*131] a stake, ran into the
shed, and hit the ravisher of his bride over the back with it.
The others wanted to seize the bridegroom, but, seeing
his father running with a stake to his assistance, they aban-
doned their prey, jumped out of the shed, and ran away.
But the bridegroom caught up with one of them and broke his
head with a blow of the stake. Bent on revenge for this in-
jury, these evildoers went straight to their father and told him
that they had met the bride while passing through the village
and had jested with her, and that the bridegroom, seeing this,
had straightway fallen upon them and beaten them, with the
help of his father. As proof they showed him the one brother’s
wounded head. Infuriated by the wounding of his son, the
father burst into a rage. He ordered the three evildoers — as
he called the bridegroom, the bride, and the bridegroom’s
father — to be brought before him without delay. When they
appeared before him, the first question [*132] he asked them
was who had broken his son’s head. The bridegroom did not
deny that he had done it, and told him everything that had
happened. ‘How did you dare,’ said the old assessor, ‘to raise
your hand against your master? Even if he had spent the night
with your bride on the eve of your wedding, you should have
been grateful to him. You shall not marry her. She shall be
attached to my house, and you shall all be punished.’ After
this judgment, he turned the bridegroom over to his sons, and
ordered them to flog him mercilessly with the cat-o’-nine-tails.
He stood the scourging manfully and watched with indomi-
table fortitude as they began to subject his father to the same
torture. But he could not endure it when he saw his master’s
children starting to take his bride into the house. ‘The punish-
ment was taking place in the yard. In an instant he snatched
her from the hands of her abductors, and the two lovers, now
free, ran away from the yard. Seeing this, the master’s [*133]
sons stopped beating the old man and started to pursue them.
Seeing that they were catching up with him, the bridegroom
snatched a rail out of the fence and prepared to defend him-
self. Meanwhile the noise attracted other peasants to the manor
yard. They sympathized with the young peasant and, in-
furiated against their masters, they gathered around their
fellow to defend him. Seeing all this, the assessor himself ran
up, began to curse them, and struck the first man he met so
violently with his cane that he fell senseless to the ground.
This was the signal for a general attack. They surrounded
their four masters and, in short, beat them to death on the
spot. They hated them so much that not one wanted to miss
the chance to take part in murdering them, as they themselves
later confessed. Just at this time the chief of the country
police of that district happened to come by with a detachment
of soldiers. He [*134] was an eyewitness of part of what hap-
pened. He had the guilty persons — that is, half the village —
put under guard, and instituted an investigation which ulti-
mately reached the criminal court. The case was clearly estab-
lished, and the guilty persons confessed everything, pleading
in their defense only the barbarous acts of their masters, of
which the whole province had been cognizant. In the course
of my official duty it was incumbent upon me to pass the final
sentence of death upon the guilty persons and to commute it
to confiscation of property and lifelong penal servitude.
“Upon reviewing the case, I found no sufficient or convinc-
ing reason to condemn the offenders. The peasants who had
killed their master were guilty of murder. But was it not
forced upon them? Was not the murdered assessor himself the
cause of it? If in arithmetic a third number follows invariably
from two given ones, [*135] the consequence was equally
inevitable in this case. The innocence of the defendants was,
at least for me, a mathematical certainty. If I am going on my
way and an evildoer falls upon me and raises a dagger over my
head to strike me down, am I to be considered a murderer if I
forestall him in his evil deed and strike him down lifeless at my
feet? If a Mohock today, having won the universal contempt
he deserves, wants to revenge himself for it on me, and, meet-
ing me in a solitary place, attacks me with drawn sword to
deprive me of life or at least to wound me, am I guilty if I
draw my sword in self-defense and deliver society from a
member who disturbs its peace? Can an act be considered
prejudicial to the inviolable human rights of a fellow being
if I do it to save myself, if [*136] it prevents my destruction,
if without it my well-being would be forever undone? °
“Full as I was of such thoughts, you may imagine the tor-
ment of my soul when I reviewed this case. With my cus-
tomary frankness I communicated my thoughts to my asso-
ciates. They unanimously rose up against me. Mercy and char-
ity seemed to them a culpable defense of crime; they called
me an abettor of murder, an accomplice of murderers. In their
opinion, the safety of the home would disappear with the dis-
semination of my subversive opinions. ‘Can a nobleman,’ they
said, ‘live safely on his estate from henceforth? If those who
oppose their master’s will, or, even worse, his murderers, are
declared innocent, then obedience will vanish, domestic bonds
will be severed, and the chaos of [*137] primitive societies
will come again. Agriculture will die, its implements will be
destroyed, the fields will become deserts, overgrown with
useless weeds. Not having any authority over them, the peas-
ants will wander about in idleness and indolence, and finally
will scatter. Cities will soon feel the imperious hand of de-
struction. The citizens will lose their stomach for work,
handicraft will lose its diligence and ambition, trade will run
dry at its source, wealth will give way to misery, the most
magnificent buildings will crumble, the laws will become in-
comprehensible and inoperative. Then the mighty structure
of society will begin to fall to pieces and each part of it will
breathe its last, separate from the whole. Then the Imperial
throne, on which the strength and cohesion of society are
now based, will decay and crumble into dust. Then the ruler
of nations will be accounted merely an ordinary citizen, and
society [*138] will behold its end.’ My associates tried to
paint this picture, worthy of the brush of Satan, for the eyes
of all who knew anything of this case. ‘Our presiding judge,’
they cried, ‘thinks it right to justify murder committed by
the peasants. Ask of what origin he is! If we are not mistaken,
he used to follow the plough himself in his youth. These
newly created noblemen always have strange conceptions of
the natural rights of noblemen over their peasants. If he had
his way, he would make us all peasant proprietors, in order
to equalize his descent with ours.’ With such words my asso-
ciates intended to insult me and to make me hateful to all
society. But they were not satisfied with that. They said that
I had received a bribe from the widow of the murdered as-
sessor so that she would not be deprived of her peasants by
sentencing them to hard labor in exile, and that this was the
real reason [*139] for my strange and dangerous opinions
which were so prejudicial to all the rights of the whole gen-
try. The fools thought that their ridicule would cut me to the
quick, that their slander would insult me, that their false rep-
resentation of my good intention would distract me from it.
They did not know my heart. They did not know that I
have always faced the court of my own conscience without
trembling, that my cheeks have never burned with the crim-
son blush of a guilty conscience.
“Their notion that I had been bribed, they based upon the
fact that the assessor’s widow did not want to avenge her
husband’s death, but, prompted by her avarice and following
her husband’s rule, wanted the peasants to be freed from pun-
ishment, in order that, as she said, she might not lose her prop-
erty. She came to me with such a petition. I agreed with her
as to the remission of punishment for the murder of her hus-
band, but we differed as to the motive. She assured me that
she [*140] would give them adequate punishment herself,
and I assured her that if the murderers of her husband were
acquitted, they must never again be driven to such desperate
extremities, lest they become in very truth the criminals they
had been wrongly called.
“Soon the governor was informed of my views in this mat-
ter — that I had been trying to convert my associates to my
way of looking at it, and that they were beginning to waver
in their opinions. They were influenced, however, not by the
strength and persuasiveness of my reasoning, but by the
money of the assessor’s widow. Since the governor himself
had been brought up under the principle of the absolute
authority of the gentry over the peasants, he could not accept
my views, and he became indignant when he saw that they
were beginning to prevail in the judgment of this case, albeit
for very divers reasons. He sent for my associates, admon-
ished them, and urged upon them the wickedness of my
views, [*141] maintaining that they were an insult to the
gentry and an insult to the supreme power, in that they vio-
lated its fundamental laws. He promised a reward to those
who obeyed the law and threatened with punishment those
who did not. And soon he prevailed upon these weak judges,
who followed no principles in their decisions and had no firm-
ness of spirit, to return to their earlier opinions. I was no more
surprised at this, their second change, than I had been at their
first. It is characteristic of weak, craven, and base souls to
cower before the threats of the powers that be and to rejoice
at their gracious nod.
“Our governor, having converted my associates, apparently
flattered himself with the conviction that he could also con-
vert me. For this purpose he summoned me, as it happened,
on the morning of a holiday. He was obliged to summon me,
because I never waited upon him with those meaningless ex-
pressions of respect and forced flattery which pride [*142]
regards as a duty in subordinates and which a wise man con-
siders contemptible and disgraceful to humanity.® He pur-
posely chose a festal day, when there was a large gathering
of people at his house; he purposely chose to address me at
a public assembly, iecilise he hoped in that way to persuade
me more readily. He hoped to find me either cowardly in
soul or weak in mind. He directed his speech against both
weaknesses. I do not think it necessary to recount to you
everything to which conceit, the sense of power, and the be-
lief in his own penetration and erudition inspired his elo-
quence. His conceit I met with equanimity and calm; his show
of power, with steadfastness; his arguments with my own,
and for a long time I spoke in a cool and collected manner.
But finally my agitated heart poured out all that was pent up
in it. The more subservience I saw in those who were standing
around, the more impulsive my speech [*143] became. With
a firm voice, loud and clear, I finally exclaimed:
“Every man is born into the world equal to all others. All
have the same bodily parts, all have reason and will. Conse-
quently, apart from his relation to society, man is a being that
depends on no one in his actions. But he puts limits to his own
freedom of action, he agrees not to follow only his own will
in everything, he subjects himself to the commands of his
equals; in a word, he becomes a citizen. For what reason does
he control his passions? Why does he set up a governing au-
thority over himself? Why, though free to seek fulfillment
of his will, does he confine himself within the bounds of
obedience? For his own advantage, reason will say; for his
own advantage, inner feeling will say; for his own advantage,
wise legislation will say. Consequently, wherever being a citi-
zen is not to his advantage, he is [*144] not a citizen. Conse-
quently, whoever seeks to rob him of the advantages of citi-
zenship is his enemy. Against his enemy he seeks protection
and satisfaction in the law. If the law is unable or unwilling
to protect him, or if its power cannot furnish him immediate
aid in the face of clear and present danger, then the citizen
has recourse to the natural law of self-defense, self-preserva-
tion, and well-being. For the citizen, in becoming a citizen,
does not cease to be a man, whose first obligation, arising from
his very nature, is his own preservation, defense, and welfare.
By his bestial cruelty the assessor who was murdered by the
peasants had violated their rights as citizens. At the moment
when he abetted the violence of his sons, when he added in-
sult to the heartfelt injury of the bridal pair, when he, seeing
their opposition to his devilish tyranny, moved to punish them,
[*145] then the law that protects a citizen fell into abeyance
and its efficacy disappeared; then the law of nature was re-
born, and the power of the wronged citizen, which the posi-
tive law cannot take from him when he has been wronged,
comes into operation, and the peasants who killed the beastly
assessor are not guilty before the law. On rational grounds my
heart finds them not guilty, and the death of the assessor, al-
though violent, is just. Let no one presume to seek in reasons
of state or in the maintenance of public peace grounds for
condemning the murderers of the assessor, who expired in
the midst of his wickedness. No matter in what estate heaven
may have decreed a citizen’s birth, he is and will always re-
main a man; and so long as he is a man, the law of nature, as
an abundant wellspring of goodness, will never run dry in
him, and whosoever dares [*146] wound him in his natural
and inviolable right is a criminal. Woe to him, if the civil law
does not punish him. He will be marked as a pariah by his
fellow citizens, and may whosoever has sufficient power exact
vengeance against him for his evildoing.’
“T fell silent. The governor said not a word to me. Now
and then he gave me lowering glances charged with the fury
of impotence and the malice of vengeance. Everyone was
silent, expecting that I, the profaner of all laws, would be
put under arrest. Every now and then a murmur of disap-
proval could be heard on their servile lips. Everyone turned
his eyes away from me. It looked as though terror had seized
those who stood near me. Imperceptibly they withdrew from
me, as from one infected with a deadly plague. Weary of the
spectacle of this mixture of arrogance and basest servility, I
left this assembly of flatterers.*°
[*147] “Unable to find any means to save the innocent
homicides whom my heart acquitted, I did not want to be an
accomplice in or a witness of their execution. I petitioned for
my retirement and, having been granted it, I am now on my
way home to bewail the lamentable fate of the peasant class,
and to relieve my weariness in association with my friends.”
As he said this, we took leave of one another, and each went
his own way.
That day my journey was not successful. The horses were
poor, and had to be changed every minute. Finally, as we
were going down a low hill, the carriage axle broke, and we
could not drive any farther. I am in the habit of taking walks.
I picked up my cane and started off for the post station. But
a stroll on the highway is not very pleasant for a Petersburger,
for it is not like a promenade in the Summer Garden or in
Baba; ?? it soon tired me, and I had to sit down.
[*148] While I was sitting on a rock, drawing all sorts of
crooked figures in the sand and thinking of this and that, a
carriage rushed past me. The passenger saw me and ordered
his driver to stop — and I recognized an old acquaintance of
mine.
“What are you doing here? ” he said to me.
“I am just thinking. I have plenty of time for thinking; my
axle is broken. What’s the news? ”
“The same old rot: the weather changes with the wind,
now there’s slush, now sunshine —. But wait! Here’s news
for you: Duryndin * got married.”
“Impossible! He’s almost eighty.”
“True enough. Well, here’s a letter for you. Read it at your
leisure. ’ve got to be on my way. Good-bye! ” And we
parted.
The letter was from a friend of mine. He dearly loved
gossip and had promised to keep me supplied with it while I
was away, and he had kept his word. Meanwhile they had
fitted the carriage with a spare axle which by good luck we
had in reserve. As we drove off again, I read:
[*149] “Petersburg.
“My dear friend, |
“The other day there took place here the marriage of a
seventy-eight year old lad and a sixty-two year old lass. You
would find it hard to guess the reason for such a belated
coupling, if I didn’t tell you. Open your ears wide, my friend,
and listen. Mme. Sh., sixty-two years old and not the last
heroine of her kind, had been a widow since her twenty-fifth
year. She had been married to a merchant who had had bad
luck in business. She had a rather pretty face, and, being left
a poor orphan after her husband’s death and knowing of the
hardheartedness of his associates, she did not wish to beg them
for alms, and was determined to support herself by her own
labors. As long as the comeliness of youth shone in her face,
she was constantly employed and received generous pay from
her customers. But as soon as she noticed that her beauty was
beginning [*150] to fade, and her amorous duties were giving
way to boredom and loneliness, she took thought and, not
finding any more purchasers for her antiquated charms, began
to trade in the charms of others, who, if they did not always
have the advantage of beauty, had at least that of novelty.
Having in this manner accumulated some thousands, she took
her honorable discharge from the despised society of pro-
curers and began to Joan out on interest the money she had
acquired by her shamelessness and that of others. In time her
old profession was forgotten, and the former madam became
an indispensable personage in the society of spendthrifts.
When she had peacefully reached her sixty-second year, the
Devil prompted her to get married. All her acquaintances
were amazed. Her closest friend, N., came to see her. ‘It is
rumoured, my dear,’ she said to the gray-haired bride, ‘that
you are about to get married. I think it must be a lie. Some
joker has invented this fairy tale.’
[*151] “Sh.— ‘It’s the gospel truth. To-morrow will be
the betrothal. Come and celebrate with us.’
“N. — ‘You've lost your mind! Is your old blood hot again,
or has some milksop come to look for shelter under your
wing?’
“Sh. —‘O my dear, you do me wrong to put me on a
level with flighty young things. I’m taking a suitable hus-
band —’
“N. — ‘Yes, I know he’ll suit you. But remember, no one
ever falls in love with the likes of us, except for money.’
“Sh. — ‘I’m not taking anybody who could be false to me.
My bridegroom is sixteen years older than I am.’
“N. — ‘You're joking!’
“Sh. — ‘On my word of honor: Baron Duryndin.’
“N, — ‘It can’t be!’
“Sh. — ‘Come to-morrow evening. You'll see for yourself
that I’m not lying.’
[*152] “N.— ‘And if it is so, he’s not marrying you, but
your money.’
“Sh. — ‘But who’s going to give it to him? I shan’t so lose
my head the first night as to give him all my possessions; that
time is past long since. A gold snuffbox, some silver buckles,
and such like rubbish, which were pawned with me and are
hard to dispose of — that’s all the dowry my beloved bride-
groom will get. And if he snores, I’ll kick him out of bed.’
“N. — ‘At least he gets a snuffbox out of it. But what do
you get?’
“Sh. — ‘How is that, my dear? Nowadays it’s not a bad
thing to have a noble title, to have them call you “Your Lady-
ship,” and the stupid ones even “Your Excellency.” Besides,
I'll have someone to play cribbage with on long winter eve-
nings. But now I sit here all alone; I don’t even have the
[*153] pleasure of hearing anyone say “God bless you!” when
I sneeze. But once I have my man, every time I catch cold
I'll hear him say, “God bless you, my pet; God bless you, my
darling! ”’
“N. — ‘Good-bye, my dear.’
KRESTTSY 107
“Sh. — ‘Tomorrow’s the betrothal, and a week from to-
morrow’s the wedding.’
“N. — (Departs.)
“Sh. — (Sneezes.) ‘She’ll not be coming back. How differ-
ent it will be when I’m married!’
“Do not marvel, my friend! In this world, the wheel comes
full circle. Today the sensible is in fashion, tomorrow the
stupid. I hope you get to see a lot of Duryndins. If they do
not always distinguish themselves by their marriages, they
do it in some other way. Without its Duryndins the world
would not last three days.”
<place_11>[*154] KRESTTSY</place_11>
At Kresttsy I witnessed the parting of a father from his
children. It moved me the more deeply because I am myself
a father and may soon be parting from my own children. An
unfortunate prejudice of the gentry impels them to go into
the service. The very mention of this word makes my blood
boil! One may safely bet a thousand to one that out of a
hundred young noblemen who enter the service, ninety-eight
will become good-for-nothing scoundrels, and two, in their
old age, or, more correctly, in their decrepitude, although
they are not old in years, will become good men. The rest
advance in rank, squander or acquire property, and so on.
Now and then, when I look at my eldest son and realize that
he will soon be going into the service, or, in other [*155]
words, that the little bird will soon be leaving the nest, my
hair stands on end. Not because the service in itself corrupts
morals, but because one should not enter the service until
one’s morals are already maturely developed. Someone will
say, “But who pushes the milksops into it?” “Who? The com-
mon example. Staff officer at seventeen, colonel at twenty,
general at twenty, gentleman of the chamber, senator, gov-
-ernor, commander of an army. What father would not wish
his children, although still in their youth, to attain high rank,
in the wake of which come wealth, honor, and wisdom?” As
I look at my son, I can see this in my mind’s eye: he has be-
gun to serve and has made the acquaintance of spendthrifts,
libertines, gamblers, dandies. He has learned to dress sprucely,
to play cards, to gain a livelihood by playing cards, to talk
about everything without knowing anything, to run after
[*156] wenches, or to talk nonsense to the ladies. Fickle for-
tune, twirling on her spindleshanks,* has somehow smiled on
him, and my young son has become a famous man even before
he has started to shave his beard. He imagines he is wiser
than all the world. What good can one expect from such a
military commander or municipal governor? Tell me frankly,
O father who lovest thy son; tell me, O honest citizen, would
you not rather choke your son to death than let him go into
the service? Does it not make your heart ache, that your son,
a famous man, has nothing but contempt for men of real
worth, because it is their fate to trail behind on the road to
high rank, because they scorn to use underhanded methods?
Will you not weep to see that your beloved son with a pleas-
ant smile on his face will rob people of their property and
honor, and poison and slaughter them, not always with his
own aristocratic hands but with the paws of his favorites?
[*157] The Kresttsy nobleman looked as though he were
about fifty years old. Here and there streaks of gray showed
through his blond hair. His settled features betokened a spirit-
ual calm invulnerable to the passions. A gentle smile of un-
troubled content, born of benevolence, had marked his face
with dimples, which are so charming in women. As I entered
the room where he was sitting, he was looking at his two sons.
His eyes, eyes of kindly reasonableness, seemed to be veiled
with a light film of sadness, but sparks of sturdy confidence
and faith flashed from them. Before him stood two youths
of almost equal age, for there was but one year’s difference
between them, while they were equal in maturity of mind
and heart. For the father’s eagerness had hastened the mental
growth of the younger, while brotherly love had led the elder
to delay somewhat his progress in learning. [*158] The two
brothers had an equal comprehension of things and of the
rules of life, but nature had endowed them with different de-
grees of intellect and sensitiveness of heart. In the elder the
eyes were firm, and his imperturbable features bore witness
to an intrepid soul that would not waver in its undertakings.
The eyes of the younger were sharp, his features restless and
changeable. But the youths’ frank and engaging animation was
a sure sign of their father’s beneficent teaching. They looked
at their father with unaccustomed constraint, due to grief at
their imminent parting and not to any imposition of power or
authority upon them. Now and then teardrops fell from their
eyes. “My friends,” said the father, “today we must part,”
and, embracing them, he pressed them sobbing to his breast.
Standing motionless at the door, I had been a witness to this
spectacle for some minutes, when the father turned to me and
said: [*159] “Be my witness, kind traveler, be my witness be-
fore the world, with what a heavy heart I obey the sovereign
will of custom. In letting my children range beyond the watch-
ful care of the parental eye, my one motive is that they may
gain experience, learn to know man from his acts, and, weary
of the turmoil of worldly life, may joyfully abandon it. But
they should have a refuge from persecution, and their daily
bread, if they are in need. For this reason I am remaining on
my land. Most gracious Lord, do not let them have to wander
about seeking alms from the mighty and finding consolation
in them! Let their hearts be their comforters, and their minds
be their givers of alms! Be seated, and hearken to my words,
which should abide in your innermost souls. I repeat to you,
today we must part. With inexpressible joy [*160] I behold
the tears that water your cheeks. May this agitation of your
) Ree) souls carry my counsel to their sanctuary, so that they may
be stirred at the thought of me, and may I in my absence be
your defense from evils and sorrows! ?
“From the time that I received you from your mother’s
body into my embrace, I willed that no one else should be re-
sponsible for all the things concerned with your care. Never
did a hired nurse touch your bodies, never did a hired tutor
touch your hearts and minds. My vigilant and zealous eye
watched over you day and night lest anything harmful should
come near you; and I consider myself fortunate indeed to
have guided you up to this hour of parting from me. But do
not imagine that I want to extort from your lips any thanks
for the care I have taken of you, or any acknowledgment,
however feeble, for anything I have done for you. I was
moved by the impulse of my own [*161] interest, and what-
ever I did for you, I did for my own satisfaction. Therefore
put away the thought that you are subject to my power. You
owe me nothing. Not in reason, and much less in law, do I
want to look for the strong foundation of our union. It is
grounded in your hearts. Woe to you if you ever forget it!
My image will pursue the violator of our union of friendship,
will seek him out in his hiding place, and will cause him un-
bearable torture until he returns to the union. Once more I
say to you, you owe me nothing. Look upon me as a transient
and pilgrim, and if your heart feels any tender inclination
towards me, we shall live in friendship, that greatest blessing
on earth. If, however, your heart is not stirred, may we forget
each other as though we had never been born. — Most gracious
Father, let me never see that day, [*162] take me back to
Thy lap before that! — You owe me nothing for your food, nor
for your instruction, and least of all for your birth. For
your birth? Wherein were you responsible? Were you asked
whether you wanted to be born? Were you to be born for
your good or for your harm? Does the father or mother, in
begetting a son, know whether he will be happy or unhappy
in life? Who will say that, in entering into wedlock, he
thought of his heirs and descendants? And if he did have them
in mind, did he want to bring them into existence for the sake
of their happiness, or for the perpetuation of his name? How
can I wish good things to him whom I do not know, and
what is good? Can an indefinite wish, born in uncertainty, be
called good? The urge toward marriage explains why parents
bring children into the world. Attracted more by your moth-
er’s spiritual goodness than by the beauty of her face, I used
a sure means to kindle our mutual passion, namely, true [*163 ]
love. I won your mother for my wife. But what incited our
love? Mutual desire, satisfaction of the flesh and of the spirit.
In partaking of the joy decreed by nature, we did not think
of you. Your birth was a pleasure for us, but not for you.
The reproduction of our kind flattered our vanity; your birth
was a new and, so to speak, a sensuous union, confirming our
spiritual union. This is the source of the initial love of parents
for their children; it is strengthened by habit, by the sense of
one’s power, and by the honor reflected upon the father by
the praises earned by his son. Your mother shared my opinion
that you owed us nothing for your birth. She did not pride
herself on having carried you in her womb, did not demand
any recognition for having nourished you with her blood, did
not want any filial reverence for her pain in giving you birth,
nor for the weariness of having nursed you [*164] at her
breasts. She sought to give you a good soul, like her own, and
she wished to implant friendship in it, not duty, obligation, or
servile obedience. Fate did not permit her to see the fruit of
her planting. She left us with firmness of spirit, but she did
not want to die so soon, seeing your youth and my love. In
emulating her, we shall not lose her entirely. She will live
with us until we join her. You must know that my favorite
conversation with you is about her who gave you birth. Then
it seems as though her soul were holding converse with us,
then she is present with us, then she appears within us, then
she is still alive.” Saying this, he wiped off the tears of his
soul’s abiding grief.
“Little as you owe me for your birth, you owe me just as
little for your sustenance. When I entertain a stranger, when
I feed little birds, [*165] when I give food to a dog who licks
my hand, do I do it for their sakes? In all that I find my own
personal joy, amusement, or profit. The same motives lead
people to foster their children. When you were born into the
world, you became citizens of the society in which you live.
It was my duty to nurture you, for, if I had let you starve,
I would have been a murderer. If I took better care of you
than many do, I simply followed the dictates of my heart.
It was in my power to care well for you or to neglect you, to
save your days or to squander them, to keep you alive or let
you perish; and this proves clearly that you are not indebted
to me for being still alive. If you had died from my neglect,
as so many die, the vengeance of the law would not have pur-
sued me. But some may say that you are indebted [*166] to
me for your training and education. Did I not seek my own
profit in your virtue? The praises bestowed upon your good
behavior, judgment, knowledge, and ability, falling upon you,
are reflected upon me, as the sun’s rays are from a mirror. In
praising you, they praise me. What would it have profited me
if you had abandoned yourselves to vice, had been estranged
from learning, dull in mind, malicious, and lacking in fineness
of feeling? Not only should I have become a fellow sufferer
in your aberrations but, perhaps, a victim of your madness.
As it is, I can remain calm upon your departure; your minds
are sound, your hearts are strong, and I live in them. O friends,
sons of my heart! In begetting you, I incurred many obliga-
tions toward you, but you owe me nothing. I seek your friend-
ship and love, and if you bestow it upon me, I shall blissfully
return to the Source of life, and, in dying, I will not rebel
against [*167] leaving you forever, since I shall live in your
memories. “But if I have done my duty in your education, I must now
tell you the reason why I brought you up thus and not other-
wise, and why I taught you one thing and not another; there-
fore listen to the story of your education, that you may know
the reason for all the things which I have done for you.
“From your childhood on you have never experienced any
compulsion. Although you were guided in your actions by
my hand, you were never conscious of its direction. Your
actions were predetermined and anticipated, but I did not want
timidity or abject obedience to make you feel so much as the
weight of its finger. Hence your spirit, impatient with any un-
reasonable command, is amenable to the counsels of friendship.
If in your childhood I found that, diverted by some accidental
force, you departed from the path I had prepared for you,
[*168] I stopped you, or, better, imperceptibly led you back
into the old path, even as a stream that breaks through its
dikes is turned back within its banks by a skillful hand.®
“There was no timid tenderness in me when, as it seemed,
I did not protect you from the inclemency of the elements
and the weather. I preferred that your bodies be hardened
by momentary pain rather than that you grow soft and fat in
adult life. Therefore you often went barefooted and bare-
headed, and lay down to rest in dust and dirt, on a bench or
a stone. No less did I try to keep you from deleterious food
and drink. Work was the best seasoning for our dinner. Re-
member how joyfully we dined in a strange village when we
could not find our way [*169] home. How good the rye
bread and rustic kvas tasted to us then!
“Do not be angry with me if you are sometimes ridiculed
because you have no courtly bearing, because you stand as is
most comfortable for your body, and not as fashion or custom
prescribes, because you do not dress according to fashion-
able taste, because your hair is curled by the hand of nature,
not of the hairdresser. Do not be angry if you are neglected
in society, especially by women, because you do not know
how to flatter their beauty. But remember that you know how
to run fast, how to swim without tiring, that you can lift
weights without straining, lead a plough, dig up a garden bed,
that you have learned how to handle a scythe, axe, plane, and
chisel, that you know how to ride and shoot. Do not grieve
because you cannot leap about like clowns. You must know
that even the finest dancing represents nothing majestic, and
that, if you are ever moved by the sight of it, lust is its [*170]
real root, and the rest merely incidental. But you know how
to portray animate and inanimate nature, and nature’s king,
man. In painting you will find true pleasure, not only for the
senses, but for the mind. I have taught you music, that the
string, vibrating in harmony with your nerves, may awaken
your slumbering heart, for music, by bringing our innermost
spirit into motion, makes tenderness of heart a habit. I have
also taught you the barbarous art of fighting with the sword.
But may this art remain dormant within you, unless you are
provoked to self-defense. I trust it will not make you arrogant,
for you have a firm spirit and will not consider it an insult if
an ass kicks at you or a pig touches you with its smelly snout.
Do not be afraid to tell anyone that you know how to milk
a cow, how to cook cabbage soup and porridge, or that you
can roast a piece [*171] of meat and make it taste good. He
who knows how to do something himself will know how to
order others to do it, and will be lenient toward others’ mis-
takes, since he knows the difficulties of doing things.
“In your childhood and boyhood I did not burden your
mind with ready-made deductions and other people’s thoughts;
I did not burden your memory with useless facts. After I had
shown you the way to knowledge, you yourselves, as soon as
you became conscious of your power of reasoning, proceeded
on the road that was opened to you. Your knowledge is all the
better grounded because you have not acquired it by rote,
chattering, as the proverb says, like Jacob’s magpie.* In accord
with this principle, so long as your reasoning power was inac-
tive, I did not lay before you the concept of the Supreme
Being, much less that of Revelation. For what you would have
learned before you learned to reason would only have been
prejudice, and would have hindered independent thought.
[*172] But when I saw that in your judgment you were
guided by reason, I presented to you a sequence of concepts
which lead to the recognition of God, for I was most deeply
convinced that the ever-loving Father preferred to see two un-
corrupted souls in whom the lamp of heavenly knowledge
was not lighted by prejudice but who themselves ascended
to the Source of fire to light their lamps. Then I also put
before you the law of Revelation, without hiding from you
all that many men had said in denying it. For I wanted you
to choose yourselves between the milk and the gall, and I re-
joiced to see that you unhesitatingly lifted up the vessel of
consolation.
“In giving you scientific information, I did not neglect to
acquaint you with various nations by teaching you foreign
languages. But my first concern was that you should learn
your own language, that you should be able [*173] to express
your thoughts orally and in writing, without strain and with-
out bringing sweat to your brow. Above all, I tried to impart
to you the English,° and then the Latin language. For the elas-
ticity of the spirit of freedom, passing over into the represen-
tation of speech, trains the mind in firm conceptions, which
are so necessary in all governments. But in leaving your reason
free to guide your steps in the paths of learning, I was even
more anxiously concerned for your morals. I tried to temper
your momentary anger, and subjected to reason the lasting
anger which leads to vengeance. Vengeance! — your soul ab-
hors it, Of this natural impulse of sensient beings you have
retained only the desire for self-preservation, and have put
away the desire to return insults.
[*174] “Now the time has arrived when your senses, hav-
ing reached the peak of susceptibility but not yet the highest
understanding of its causes, are beginning to be disturbed by
every external stimulus and to produce a dangerous agitation
in your innermost being. You have now arrived at the time
when, as they say, reason becomes the determiner of action
or nonaction; or, to put it better, when the senses, hitherto un-
troubled during the happy reign of childhood, begin to feel
a stirring; or when the vital humors, having filled the vessel
of youth, begin to overflow its sides, seeking a path appro-
priate for their movement. Until now I have guarded you
against harmful sensual shocks, but I did not hide from you
under cover of ignorance the destructive consequences of de-
parting from the path of moderation in sensual enjoyments.
You saw for yourselves the shamefulness of unbridled sensual
enjoyment, [*175] and you were disgusted; you were wit-
nesses of the horrible tumult of the passions when they went
beyond their natural bounds; you saw the terrible devastation
caused by them, and you were horrified. My experience,
hovering over you like a new aegis,’ preserved you from un-
toward injury. Now you will be your own guides, and, al-
though my counsels will always be a guiding light for your
actions, since your hearts and souls are open to me, still, as
light illuminates an object less the farther it recedes from it,
so you, deprived of my presence, will feel the warmth of my
friendship but faintly. Hence I will now lay before you the
rules of individual and social life, so that, after mastering your
passions, you may not be ashamed of the acts committed under
their pressure, and may not learn what repentance is.
“The rules of individual life, insofar as they apply to you,
are concerned with your physical and [*176] moral being.
Never forget to make use of your bodily powers and sensa-
tions. Moderate exercise will strengthen without exhausting
them, and will help give you health and a long life. To this
end keep in practice the skills, arts, and crafts you have learned.
Perfection in them may some day be invaluable. The future
is unknown to us. If an unfriendly fate should rob you of
everything it has given you, you can remain rich in the mod-
eration of your desires, while supporting yourselves by the
labor of your hands. But if you neglect everything in the
day of prosperity, it will be too late to think about it in the
day of adversity. Effeminacy, idleness, and incontinence ruin
both body and spirit. For he who weakens his body by unre-
strained indulgence also exhausts the strength of his spirit.
But the rightful exercise of one’s powers strengthens body
and spirit alike. If your food palls on you and sickness knocks
at your door, jump up [*177] from the couch on which you
are pampering your senses, exercise your torpid muscles, and
you will feel an immediate renewal of your strength; go with-
out food needed in health, and hunger will sweeten your food
which had palled on you from satiety. Always remember that
a piece of bread and a dipper of water will suffice to satisfy
hunger. If the beneficent loss of external consciousness, sleep,
departs from your pillow, and you are unable to renew your
mental and bodily powers, run from your chambers, and,
having tired your limbs to the point of exhaustion, lie down
upon your couch, and you will enjoy sweet sleep.
“Be cleanly in your clothing, and keep your body clean,
for cleanliness is conducive to health, while dirtiness and
stench often imperceptibly open the way to shameful vices.
But even in this you must not be immoderate. Do not be above
[*178] lending a helping hand to raise a carriage out of a
ditch where it is stuck in the mud, or to lift up one who has
fallen; you will soil your hands, feet, and body, but will
cleanse your heart. Go into the huts of the humble, console
him who is languishing in poverty, partake of his food, and it.
will do your heart good to have brought comfort to the sor-
rowful. I repeat, you have now reached that terrible time
when the passions begin to stir, but reason is still too weak to
bridle them. For on the balance of the will, the scale of reason
without experience will rise, while the scale of the passions
will at once go far down. Equipoise can be reached only by
patient labor. Work with your body, and your passions will
not be so easily stirred up; work with your heart by practic-
ing meekness, gentleness, compassion, generosity, forgiveness,
and your passions will be directed to a good end. Work with
your mind [*179] in the practice of reading, meditation, and
the quest for truth or facts, and reason will rule your will and
passions. But do not imagine, in the elation of your mind, that
one can crush the roots of the passions, that one ought to be
entirely without passion. The root of the passions is good and
is planted by nature itself in our sensuous organism. When our
external and internal senses grow weak and dull, our passions,
too, are weakened. They arouse a wholesome energy in man,
without which he would fall into lazy sleep. A completely
passionless man is a fool and a lifeless block, incapable of do-
ing either good or evil. It is no merit to abstain from evil
thoughts when one is unable to conceive them. An armless
man cannot hurt anyone, but neither can he help a drowning
man, nor can be hold back on the shore one who is about to
cast himself into the raging sea. Hence moderation in [*180]
passion is wise; the safest way to travel is in the middle of
the road. Excess in passion is destructive; absence of passion
is moral death. As the traveler who deviates from the middle
of the road is in danger of falling into one ditch or the other,
so it is also in the path of morality. But if your passions are
directed toward a good end by experience, reason, and affec-
tion, you may drop the reins of anxious prudence, and let
them soar at will; their goal will always be greatness, and there
only will they be able to rest.
“But though I urge you not to be passionless, your youth
needs above all moderation in the passion of love. It has been
implanted in our hearts by nature, for our good. Hence it can
never err in its awakening, but only in its object and through
excess. Therefore you must take care not to be mistaken
[*181] in the object of your love, and not to mistake false
seeming for true love. With a worthy object for your love,
excess in this passion will be unknown to you. Speaking of
love, it would be natural to speak of marriage, that sacred
body of society, the rules of which are not etched in the heart
by nature, but whose sacredness arises from the basic prin-
ciples of society. This would be incomprehensible — and the
account of it, therefore, useless — both to your reason, which
is barely beginning its progress, and to your heart, which has
not yet experienced the selfish passion of love in society. If
you wish to have a concept of what marriage is, think of the
one who gave you birth. Think of me with her and you, re-
member our conversations and mutual caresses, and lay this
picture to your heart. Then you will feel a delightful [*182]
perturbation. What is it? You will understand in time, but
for the present be satisfied with perceiving it.
“Let us now briefly examine the rules of social life. They
cannot be prescribed exactly, because they are often deter-
mined by the circumstances of the moment. But in order to
make the minimum of mistakes, consult your heart in every-
thing you do. Do what it asks of you. If you follow your
heart in your youth, you will not err, if you have a good heart.
But whosoever pretends to follow reason before he has any
beard betokening experience is a fool.
“The rules of social life refer to the observance of national
customs and habits, or to observance of the law, or to the
practice of virtue. If social customs and habits are not contrary
to law, if the law sets up no obstacle to the progress of virtue,
[*183] then the observance of the rules of social life is easy.
But where does such a society exist? Every society we know
of is full of many contradictions in manners, customs, laws,
and virtue. Thence arises the difficulty of doing one’s duties
as a man and as a citizen, since they are often diametrically
opposed to one another.
“Inasmuch as virtue is the highest end of human action, its
practice should not be impeded by anything. Disregard cus-
toms and usages, disregard civil and ecclesiastical law, however
sacred they may be in human society, whenever their observ-
ance keeps you from virtue. Do not presume to defend its vio-
lation on the ground of the timidity of prudence. Without
virtue you may prosper outwardly but you can never be
happy. “By complying with the usages and customs imposed upon
us, we shall gain [*184] the approval of those among whom
we live. By carrying out the injunctions of the law, one may
gain the reputation of being an honest man. But in practicing
virtue, we shall gain universal trust, respect, and admiration,
even from those who do not wish to have such feelings for us
in their souls. When the treacherous Senate of Athens handed
the poison cup to Socrates, they trembled inwardly before
his virtue.
“Never presume to comply with a custom that is contrary
to the law. The law, however bad it is, is the bond that holds
society together. Even if the Sovereign himself should com-
mand you to violate a law, do not obey him, for he is in error,
to the detriment of himself and of society. Let him abolish the
law which he orders you to violate; then obey him, for in
Russia the Sovereign is the source of the laws.
“But if the law, or the Sovereign, or any power on earth
should tempt you to falsehood or to depart [*185] from vir-
tue, remain immovably true to it. Fear not ridicule, nor tor-
ture, nor sickness, nor exile, nor even death itself. Remain
immovable in your soul, like a rock amidst tumultuous but im-
potent waves. The fury of your tormentors will be broken
against your firmness; and if they give you over to death, they
will be laughed to scorn, while you will live unto eternity in
the memory of noble souls. First and last, beware of misnam-
ing as ‘prudence’ any weakness in action, for weakness is the
foremost enemy of virtue.*° Today you will depart from vir-
tue for one consideration or another, and tomorrow this de-
parture will seem to you to be virtue itself; and thus vice will
enthrone itself in your heart and will distort the features of
innocence in your soul and upon your countenance. .
“Virtues are either individual or social. Individual virtue
grows out of gentleness, kindness, and compassion, and its
root its always good. The impetus toward social [*186] vir-
tue frequently arises from vanity and ambition. But this should
not keep you from practicing the social virtues. The cause
they serve is what makes them important. One thinks of Cur-
tius,!? who saved his country from destructive pestilence, not
as a vainglorious or despairing man tired of life, but as a hero.
When our striving toward the social virtues has its origin in a
humane firmness of soul, then their luster is so much the
brighter. Always practice individual virtues, so that you may
be more worthy to practice the social virtues.”
“I will give you yet a few more rules of life for your guid-
ance. This above all: strive in all your actions to maintain
your self-respect, so that when, in solitude, you look inward,
you need not repent for what you have done, [*187] but may
look upon yourselves with honor.
“In following this rule you must, as far as possible, avoid
even the appearance of servility. Once you have entered the
world, you will soon learn that in society it is the custom to
call upon distinguished personages on holiday mornings: a
miserable, senseless custom which betrays a spirit of timidity
in the caller, a spirit of conceit and a weak intellect in the
personage visited. The Romans had a similar custom, which
they called ambitio, that is, ‘seeking,’ or ‘going around’; and
from this the seeking of honors came to be called ambitio, be-
cause, in calling on great personages, ambitious young men
sought for themselves a road to honors and preferment. The
same thing is being done nowadays. But I doubt if the purpose
of this custom — which was introduced among the Romans
in order that young people might learn something from con-
tacts with experienced men —has been honorably [*188]
maintained. In our days no one calls upon the mighty to seek
instruction; all come only to curry favor. Therefore let not
your feet cross the threshold that separates servility from the
performance of duty. Never visit the antechamber of a mag-
nate except in the line of duty. In the thick of the contempt-
ible mob who fawn upon him, he will then, however indig-
nantly, distinguish you in his heart from the rest.
“If death should happen to cut off my days before you have
-gained strength on the path of virtue, and the passions, in your
youth, should entice you away from the path of reason, do
not despair if, betimes, you recognize your errors. In your
very mistakes, in your self-forgetfulness, you may come to
love goodness. A life of dissipation, vaulting ambition, arro-
gance, and all the vices of youth, need not be without hope
of improvement, because these vices only glide [*189] over
the surface of the heart, without wounding it. I would rather
have you dissolute, prodigal, and rude in your early years than
avaricious, stingy, or vain, with more concern for your out-
ward appearance than anything else. A so-called systematic
tendency toward dandyism always indicates a narrow intel-
lect. If they tell you that Julius Caesar was a dandy, his dandy-
ism had a purpose. Its driving power in his youth was his
passion for women. But he would have changed instantly from
gay attire to ill-smelling rags if they would have helped him
get what he wanted.
“In a young man temporary dandyism, and indeed almost
any foolishness, is pardonable. But even if you disguise trick-
ery, lying, disloyalty, avarice, pride, [*190] vengefulness, and
bestiality under the semblance of the noblest acts of life, so
that you blind your contemporaries with the bright light of
your external glamour, and even if you do not find anyone
who loves you enough to place before you the mirror of truth,
do not imagine that you can dim the All-seeing Eye. It will
pierce through the shining mantle of your deceit, and virtue
will lay bare the blackness of your soul. Your heart will hate
it, and it will shrink from your touch like a sensitive plant —
but only for a moment, for its arrows will soon begin to
wound and torment you from afar.
“Farewell, my beloved ones, farewell, friends of my soul!
Today with a favorable wind you will launch your untried
boat from the shore. Venture forth on the waves of human
life so that you may learn how to govern yourselves. Happy
your fortune if, without suffering shipwreck, you reach the
haven for which we all long. May you be happy in your
voyage. This is my heartfelt [*191] wish. My vital powers,
exhausted by life and action, will decline and die; I shall leave
you forever, but this is my last will and testament. If out-
rageous fortune hurl upon you all its slings and arrows, if
there is no refuge left on earth for your virtue, if, driven to
extremes, you find no sanctuary from oppression, then remem-
ber that you are a man, call to mind your greatness, and
seize the crown of bliss which they are trying to take from
you. Die. As a legacy I leave you the words of the dying
Cato.** But if you have learned how to die in virtue, you
should also learn how to die in vice, and to be, as it were,
virtuous even in evil. If, forgetting my advice, you rush head-
long into wickedness, your soul, accustomed to virtue, will
be troubled, and I shall appear to you in your dreams. Arise
then from your bed and in spirit follow my apparition. If,
then, a tear falls from your [*192] eye, go back to sleep, and
you will wake up the better for it. But if, amidst your evil
doings, your soul does not stir at the thought of me, and your
eye remains dry — that is steel, that is poison. Deliver me
from that grief; deliver the earth from that disgraceful bur-
den! Be my son still! Die for virtue’s sake!”
As the old man said this, a youthful blush covered his
wrinkled cheeks, his eyes shone with hopeful joy, his counte-
nance glowed with supernatural splendor. He kissed his chil-
dren and, accompanying them to the carriage, remained firm
to the last farewell. But scarcely had the sound of the post bell
informed him that they had started, when his spirit’s strong
control gave way. Tears welled from his eyes, his breast
heaved, he stretched his arms after his departing sons, as
though he would have stopped the horses’ forward movement.
The youths, already some distance off, [*193] saw their
father’s sorrow, and sobbed so loud that the wind carried
their pitiful cries to our ears. They, too, stretched out their
arms toward their father and seemed to be calling him. The
old man was unable to bear this spectacle, his strength gave
way, and he fell into my arms. Meanwhile a hill on the road
had hidden the young men from our view. On coming to, the
old man knelt down and raised his hands and eyes to heaven.
“O Lord,” he cried, “I implore Thee, strengthen them in the
path of virtue, I implore Thee to grant them happiness. Thou
knowest, Ever-loving Father, I have never troubled Thee with
bootless prayer. I know in my soul that Thou art good and
just. The quality Thou lovest most in us is virtue; the acts of
a pure heart are the best offering to Thee.* This day I have
parted from my sons. O Lord, Thy blessing be upon [*194]
them!” He returned home troubled but firm in hope.
I could not forget the words of the Kresttsy nobleman. His
reasoning as to the invalidity of the power of parents over
children seemed to me incontrovertible. Although in a well-
ordered society it is necessary that young people respect their
elders, and inexperience respect wisdom, yet there seems to
be no reason for making parental power unlimited. If the
bond between father and son is not based on tender feelings of
the heart, it is certainly weak, and will remain weak in spite
of all legislation. If the father regards his son as his slave
and seeks the foundation of his power in legal enactments, and
if the son honors his father only for the sake of his inheri-
tance, what good is this to society? It means either a new
slave on top of all the others, or a snake in the bosom....
[*195] A father must provide for and teach his son, and is
responsible for his delinquencies until he comes of age, while
a son must feel his obligations in his heart. If he feels none,
it is the father’s fault, because he had implanted none. The
son has a right to expect assistance from his father so long
as he is helpless and under age; but when he comes of age,
this natural bond is severed. A fledgling does not seek fur-
ther aid from its parents after it has begun to find its own
food. The father and mother birds forget their young as
soon as they are grown. Such is the law of nature. Whenever
the civil laws depart from it, they beget a monstrosity. A
child loves his father, mother, or teacher until his love is
turned to another object. Let not thy heart be offended, O
father who lovest thy children; [*196] nature demands it.
Let this thought be your one consolation, that your son’s
son likewise will love his father only until he comes fully of
age. After that it will depend on you to turn his love toward
you. If you succeed in this, you will be deemed fortunate and
worthy of all honor. With such thoughts I arrived at the
post station.
<place_12>[*197] YAZHELBITSY</place_12>
Fate chose this day for my trial. I am a father and have a
tender heart for my children. For this reason the words of
the Kresttsy nobleman had moved me deeply. But while they
stirred me to the depths of my heart, they also filled me with
a certain comforting feeling of hope that our joy in our
children depends largely on ourselves. At Yazhelbitsy, how-
ever, I was destined to witness a spectacle which sank a deep
root of sorrow into my soul, with no hope of ever plucking
it out. Listen, O youth, to my story! Recognize your error,
refrain from willful ruin, and make future repentance un-
necessary.
I was driving past the cemetery. The unearthly sobs of a
man who was tearing his hair caused me [*198] to stop. As I
approached, I saw that a funeral was in progress. They were
about to lower the coffin into the grave, but the man whom I
had seen from afar tearing his hair threw himself on the coffin
and clung to it so firmly that they could not lower it into the
earth. With great difficulty they took him from the coffin,
lowered it into the grave, and hastily covered it with earth.
Then the mourner cried to those about him: “Why have
you snatched him from me? Why did you not bury me alive
with him and thereby end my grief and repentance? Know,
know that I am the murderer of my beloved son, whose dead
_body you have returned to the earth. Do not be amazed. I
did not cut short his life with the sword or with poison.
No, I did worse than that. I prepared the way for his death
before he was born, by giving him a poisoned life. I am a
murderer, like many others, but a murderer more savage
than any other. I murdered my son before [*199] his
birth. I, I alone, shortened his days by infusing slow poison
into him at his conception. It prevented the development of
his bodily powers. During his whole life he enjoyed not a
single day of health, and the spread of the wasting poison
cut off the flow of his life. No one, no one will punish me for
my wickedness!” Despair was painted on his face, and they
carried him away almost lifeless.
A sudden chill coursed through my veins. I felt numb.
It seemed to me that I heard my own sentence pronounced.’
I thought of the days of my dissolute youth. I recalled all the
times when my soul, stirred by my senses, chased after their
gratification, falsely considering the hired partner of amorous
satisfaction an object of true love. I recalled that incontinence
in passion had brought upon my body a loathsome disease.
Oh, if only it had not sent down its root more deeply! [*200]
Oh, if only it had been cut off with the waning of passion!
Having received this poison in enjoyment, we not only nourish
it within us, but bequeath it to our descendants. O my beloved
friends, O children of my soul! You do not know how I have
sinned before you. Your pallid brow is my condemnation.
I dread telling you about the disease of which you are some-
times aware. You will perhaps hate me, and your hatred will
be justified. Who can assure you and me that you do not har-
bor in your blood the hidden sting destined to bring your
days to an untimely end? ? Since I received that loathsome
poison into my body when I was fully grown, the firmness
of my members enabled me to resist its spread and struggle
against its deadly effects. But you received it before your
birth and have borne it within you as an integral part of your
being; how, therefore, can you resist [*201] its fiery ravages?
All your sicknesses are the consequence of this poisoning.
O my beloved ones, weep for the error of my youth, appeal
to medical art for aid, and, if possible, do not hate me!
But now the whole enormity of this amorous crime is re-
vealed to me. I have sinned against myself by condemning
myself, while still young, to premature old age and decrepi-
tude, I have sinned before you, poisoning your vital humours
before your birth and thereby preparing for you poor health,
and, perhaps, untimely death. I have sinned (and may this be
my punishment! ), I have sinned in my love, by marrying your
mother. Who can guarantee to me that I was not the cause of
her death? The death-dealing poison, diffused in enjoyment,
settled in her pure body and poisoned all her chaste being.
It was the more deadly [*202] for being unsuspected.
False shame kept me from informing her of it, while she took
no precautions against her poisoner, in her love for him, The
fever which carried her off may have been the fruit of the
poison I implanted in her.—O my beloved ones, how you
must hate me!
But who is to blame for the fact that this loathsome disease
causes such great devastation in all countries, not only mow-
ing down many of the present generation, but also shortening
the days of those to come? Who is to blame, if not the gov-
ernment? In licensing prostitution it not only opens the way
to many vices but also poisons the lives of its citizens. Public
women have their defenders and in some countries are under
the protection of the government. Some say that if the venal
satisfaction of amorous [*203] passion were prohibited,
violent upheavals would often be felt in society. Rape, vio-
lence, and murder would frequently take place as a result
of unsatisfied lust. They might shake society to its very foun-
dations. And so you prefer quiet and with it languishing dis-
ease and grief to agitation and with it health and manliness.
Be silent, wicked teachers; you are the hirelings of tyranny;
it always preaches peace and quiet —and casts into fetters
those who have been lulled to sleep by flattery. It even fears
agitation in others. Tyranny desires universal conformity in
thought so that it may safely enjoy its power and wallow in
voluptuousness — .* I am not surprised at your teachings. It is
characteristic of slaves to want to see everyone in fetters. An
equal fate for all alleviates their lot, while the superiority of
others burdens their mind and spirit.
<place_13>[*204] VALDAI</place_13>
This new little town was settled, they say, in the reign
of Tsar Aleksey Mikhaylovich, by Polish prisoners of war.
This town is famous for the amorous inclinations of its in-
habitants, especially of its unmarried women.
Who has not been to Valdai, who does not know the Valdai
doughnuts and painted wenches? The bold and shameless
Valdai girls stop every traveler and try to kindle his passion
in order to exploit his generosity at the cost of their chastity.
In comparing the morals of the inhabitants of this village,
which has been raised to the dignity of a city, with the morals
of other Russian cities, one might think that it was the oldest
of them all and that its lewdness was the only [*205] vestige
of its antiquity. But since it has been settled for little more
than a hundred years, one may judge how dissolute its first in-
habitants must have been.
The baths have always been and still are the place for
amorous celebrations. After arranging terms for his stay with
an obliging old woman or young fellow, the traveler stops
at the house whither he intends to bring his offering to the
universally worshiped Lada.” Night falls. The bath is already
prepared for him. The traveler disrobes and goes to the bath,
where he is met by the hostess, if she is young, or by her
daughter, or relative, or neighbor. They rub down his weary
limbs and wash the dirt from his body. They do this after re-
moving their own clothes to enkindle his desire, and he spends
the night there, losing his money, his health, and his valuable
traveling time. It has happened, they say, that a careless
traveler, drowsy with amorous [*206] exploits and wine,
has been murdered by these lustful monsters to enable them
to possess themselves of his property. I do not know whether
this is true, but I do know that the boldness of the Valdai
girls has been checked. And although they do not even now
refuse to satisfy the traveler’s wishes, they no longer display
their former brazenness.
Lake Valdai, on which this town is situated, will remain
famous in story because of the monk who sacrificed his life
for his sweetheart. About a verst and a half from the town,
in the middle of the lake, on an island, stands the Iberian
Monastery, founded by Nikon the famous Patriarch.* One of
the monks of this monastery, having visited Valdai, fell in
love with the daughter of one of its citizens. Their love soon
became mutual, and both soon strove to consummate their
desire. Having once indulged in the delights of love, [*207]
they were unable to resist their mutual desire. But their cir-
cumstances interposed a barrier to it. The lover could not
often leave his monastery, nor could his paramour visit her
gallant’s cell. But love conquered all; it turned the lovesick
monk into a fearless man and gave him almost supernatural
strength. Daily, in order to enjoy the embrace of his sweet-
heart, this new Leander would softly leave his cell the moment
night covered everything with its black mantle, and, taking
off his cassock, he would swim across the lake to the opposite
shore, where he was received into the arms of his sweet-
heart. The bath and the delights of love with it were waiting
for him, and in them he forgot the danger and difficulty of
the swim and the fear that his absence would be discovered.
A few hours before dawn he would return [*208] to his cell.
Thus he passed a long time in these dangerous swimming ex-
peditions and dispelled with nighttime joys the tedium of
his daytime imprisonment. But fate set a period to his amorous
exploits. One night, as this dauntless lover was crossing the
waves to visit his beloved, a contrary wind suddenly sprang
up as he was in the middle of his course. His whole strength
was insufficient to cope with the angry waves. In vain did he
strain his muscles to the point of exhaustion; in vain did he
raise his voice, hoping to make himself heard in his dangerous
plight. When he saw that he would not be able to reach the
shore, he decided to return to his monastery, which he hoped
to reach more easily, since the wind would now be favorable.
But he had barely turned back when the waves overcame his
wearied muscles and pulled him down into a whirlpool. In
the morning his body was found at a remote spot of the shore.
If I were writing [*209] a poem on this subject, I would
describe his sweetheart’s despair for the delectation of my
reader. But that would be superfluous here. Everyone knows
that, at least in the first moment, a woman is grieved to hear
of her lover’s death. Besides, I do not know whether this new
Hero threw herself into the lake, or whether she heated the
bath for a traveler again the next night. The chronicle of love
declares that the Valdai beauties do not die for love, save, per-
haps, in the hospital.*
The customs of Valdai have also spread to the adjoining
post station, Zimnogor’e. There the traveler gets the same
reception as at Valdai. The first thing one sees are painted
girls with doughnuts. But since my youthful days are over,
I parted speedily from the painted sirens of Valdai and Zimnogor’e,
<place_13>[*210] Edrovo!</place_13>
When I reached this settlement, I got out of my carriage.
Nor far from the highway, near the water, stood a crowd
of women and girls. By force of habit, my lifelong master,
passion, though now spent, drew my steps to the bevy of vil-
lage beauties. The crowd consisted of more than thirty
women. They were all in holiday attire, with their necks open,
their legs bare, their arms akimbo, their dresses tucked up
in front under their belts, their long shirts white, their faces
happy, their cheeks glowing with health. Natural charm, al-
though roughened by heat and cold, is delightful without any
false front of sophistication. The beauty of youth was visible
here in full splendor, on their lips smiles or hearty laughter,
and behind them rows of teeth whiter than purest ivory.
Teeth which would drive our [*211] fashionable ladies fran-
tic. Come hither, my dear Moscow and Petersburg ladies,
look at their teeth and learn from them how they keep
them white. They have no dentists.” They do not scour away
the gleam of their teeth every day with toothbrushes and pow-
der. Stand mouth to mouth with any one of them you choose:
not one of them will infect your lungs with her breath.
While yours, yes, yours may infect them with the germ...
of a disease ... I am afraid to say what disease, because, though
you may not blush, you will be infuriated. Am I not tell-
ing the truth? The husband of one of you runs after all the
sluts, and, having caught a disease, goes right on drinking, eat-
ing, and sleeping with you; another one of you is pleased to
have her own yearly, monthly, weekly, or, God forbid! daily
lovers. Having made his acquaintance today and satisfied her
desire, she does not know him tomorrow, nor [*212] does
she know that she may already have been infected by his mere
kiss. And you, my sweet maid of fifteen summers, you, per-
chance, are still pure; but I see on your brow that all your
blood is poisoned. Your father of blessed memory never left
the doctor’s hands; and milady, your mother, guiding you
upon her own estimable path, has already found a bridegroom
for you, a deserving old general, and is in a hurry to get you
married off, solely to avoid having to make a visit to an or-
phanage with you. And it’s not bad to be the wife of an old
man, for you do just as you please; and so long as you are mar-
ried, the children are all his. He will be jealous? So much the
better, for there will be a greater delight in stolen pleasures,
and you can teach him from the first night not to follow the
silly old custom of sleeping in the same room with his wife.
My dear city gossips, aunts, [*213] sisters, nieces, etc., I
had not noticed how long you had detained me. Truly, you
are not worth it. On your cheeks there is rouge, on your
heart rouge, on your conscience rouge, on your sincerity —
soot. Rouge or soot, it’s all the same. I shall gallop away from
you at full speed to my rustic beauties. True, there are some
of them who resemble you, but there are others the likes of
whom have not been heard or seen in the cities. See how all my
beauties’ limbs are round, well-developed, straight, and not
contorted. You think it funny that their feet are over eight or
even ten inches long. But, my dear niece with your five-inch
feet, stand in a row with them and run a race: who will be the
first to reach the tall birch tree that stands at the end of the
field? Ah — but — you are not up to it! And you, my dear
little sister, you, with your three-span * waist, you are pleased
to make [*214] fun of my village nymph, because her abdomen
has been allowed to grow naturally. Wait, my dear, I’ll have
my laugh at you. You have been married these ten months,
and your three-span waist is all askew. When it comes to child-
birth, you will pipe a different tune. God grant that nothing
worse than laughter may ensue. My dear brother-in-law
walks about downcast. He has already thrown all your lac-
ings into the fire. He has pulled the stays out of all your
dresses, but it is too late. Your distorted joints can’t be straight-
ened out now. Weep, my beloved brother-in-law, weep.
Our mother, following the lamentable fashion which often
leads to death in childbirth, has for many years been pre-
paring sorrow for you, sickness for her daughter, and feeble
bodies for your children. Even now this illness hovers like
a deadly weapon over her head, and if it does not cut short
your wife’s days, thank your lucky stars, [*215] and, if you
believe that God’s Providence was concerned about the mat-
ter, thank Him, too, if you wish. But here I am still with the
city ladies. That’s what custom does: one doesn’t feel like
leaving them. Indeed I would not leave you if I could per-
suade you not to paint your faces and your sincerity. And
now, good-bye!
While I was watching the village nymphs washing their
clothes, my carriage drove off. I was about to start after it,
when a girl who looked to be about twenty, but was really
only seventeen, put her wet clothes on a yoke and started off
the same way I was going. When I caught up with her, I spoke
to her.
“Isn’t it hard for you to carry such a heavy load, my
dear —? I don’t know your name.”
“My name is Anna, and my load isn’t heavy. And even if it
were, I would not ask you, sir, [*216] to help me.”
“Why so stern, Annushka dear? I mean you no harm.”
“All right, all right! We’ve seen gallants like you before.
Please go your way!”
“Truly, Anyutushka, I’m not the man you take me for
and not the sort you're talking about. I understand that they
start by kissing a girl, not by talking with her; but if I were
to kiss you, it would be just as though I were kissing my own
sister.”
“Don’t sidle up to me, if you please. I’ve heard such talk be-
fore. If you really mean no harm, what is it you want of me?”
“Dear Annushka, I wanted to know whether your father
and mother are still alive, what your circumstances are,
whether you're rich or poor, whether you’re happy, whether
ou have a fiancé?”
“What’s that to you, sir? This is the first time in my life
I’ve heard such talk.”
“From which you may judge, Anyuta, that I’m not a scoun-
drel and do not mean to insult or dishonor you. [*217] I love
women because they embody my ideal of tenderness, but
most of all I love village or peasant women, because they are
innocent of hypocrisy, do not put on the mask of pretended
love, and when they do love, love sincerely and with their
whole hearts.”
While I was saying this, the girl looked at me with eyes
wide open with amazement. How, indeed, could it have been
otherwise, for who does not know the impudence, the crude,
unchaste, and offensive jests, with which the audacious gen-
try assail the village maidens? In the eyes of old and young
nobles alike, they are simply creatures for their lordly pleas-
ure. And they treat them accordingly, especially those un-
fortunate ones subject to their commands. During the recent
Pugachev Rebellion, when all the serfs rose up in arms against
their masters, some peasants (this story is not an invention)
had tied up their master and started to carry [*218] him off
to certain death. What was the reason for this? In everything
else he was a good and charitable master, but neither the
wives nor the daughters of his peasants were safe from him.
Every night his emissaries brought him his chosen victim for
that day’s sacrifice to dishonor. It was known in the village
that he had dishonored sixty maidens, robbing them of their
purity. A detachment of soldiers that happened to pass by
rescued this barbarian from the hands of those who were
raging against him. Stupid peasants, you looked for justice
from an impostor! * But why did you not report your griev-
ance to your rightful judges? They would have condemned
the offender to civil death, and you would have remained
innocent. But now this evildoer is saved. Happy he if the sight
of imminent death has changed his way of thinking and given
a new direction to his vital humours. But, we said, the peasant
is dead to the law? No, no, he lives, he will live, if he wishes
tol [*219] “If you are not jesting, sir,” Anyuta said to me, “I
will tell you. I have no father; he died two years ago. I have
a mother and a little sister. Father left us five horses and three
cows. And there are plenty of small animals and fowl, but there
is no man in the house to do the farm work. They were going
to marry me off into a rich house, to a ten-year-old lad, but
I didn’t want that.6 What could I do with such a child? I
could not love him. And by the time he was grown up, I
would have been an old woman, and he would have been
running after others. They say that his father sleeps with
his young daughters-in-law until his sons grow up. That’s why
I didn’t want to marry into his family. I want someone my own
age. I shall love my husband, and he will love me; I’ve no
doubt of that. I don’t want to gallivant with the boys, but
I do want to get married, sir. And do you know why?”
Anyuta said, [*220] letting her eyes droop.
“Tell me, dear Anyutushka, don’t be bashful; every word
from the lips of innocence is pure.”
“Well, then, Pll tell you. A year ago last summer our
neighbor’s son married my friend with whom I always used
to go to quilting parties. Her husband loves her, and she
loves him so much that in the tenth month after their wedding
she bore him a little son. Every evening she takes him out
by the gate to give him an airing. She can’t get to see her fill
of him. And it looks as though the little fellow already loves
his mother. Whenever she says to him ‘Agoo, agoo,’ he laughs.
Tears come to my eyes every day I see him; I should love to
have a child like that myself.”
At this point I could no longer refrain from embracing
Anyuta, and kissed her with all my heart.
“See what a deceiver you are, sir! You are already playing
with me,” said Anyuta, bursting into tears. “Go away and
leave a poor orphan alone. If [*221] my father were alive
and saw this, he would give you a good beating in spite of
your being a nobleman.”
“Don’t be offended, dear Anyutushka, don’t be offended!
My kiss does not sully your virtue, which is sacred in my eyes.
My kiss is a token of my respect for you, and it was the joyous
response of my deeply moved soul. Do not be afraid of me, dear
-Anyuta, for I am not a rapacious animal like our young noble-
men who think nothing of robbing a maiden of her purity.
If I had known that my kiss would offend you, I swear in
God’s name that I would not have dared to kiss you.”
“You can see yourself, sir, that I could not help being
offended by your kiss, since all mine are meant for another.
I have promised them in advance, and I am not free to dispose
of them.”
“How charming! You have already learned how to love.
You have found another heart for your own, a fitting mate.
You will be happy. Nothing will [*222] sever your union.
You will not be surrounded by busybodies who will be watch-
ing for a chance to lure you into the nets of destruction. Your
true lover’s ear will not be open to the voice of temptation,
inciting him to violate his troth to you. But why, my dear
Anyuta, are you deprived of the pleasure of enjoying happi-
ness in your dear friend’s arms?”
“O sir, because they won’t let him off to come to us. They
demand a hundred rubles. And my mother won’t let me go,
because I’m her only helper.”
“But does he love you?”
“Indeed he does. Every evening he comes to our house and
together we watch my friend’s baby. He’d love to have a little
fellow just like that one. It will be hard for me, but I shall
have to stand it. My Vanyukha wants to go to Petersburg to
work on the boats, and he will not come back until he has
earned a hundred rubles to buy his release.”
“Do not let him go, dear Anyutushka, [*223] do not let
him go! He will be going to his ruin. There he will learn to
drink, to waste his money, to eat dainties, despise farm work,
and worst of all, he will stop loving you.”
“O sir, don’t frighten me,” said Anyuta, almost in tears.
“And it would be even worse, Anyuta, if he should take
service in a nobleman’s house. The example of the masters
infects the higher servants, these infect the lower, and from
them the pestilence of debauchery spreads to the villages.
The bad example is the real plague, for everybody does what
he sees others do.”
“Then what will become of me? I’ll never be able to marry
him. It’s time for him to get married; he’s not one to go running
about with other girls. They won’t let me go into his house-
hold; they'll marry him to someone else, and I, poor girl,
shall die of grief.” Saying this, she shed bitter tears.
“No, my dear Anyutushka, you shall marry him tomorrow.
Take me to your mother.”
[*224] “Here is our house,” she said, as she stopped.
“Please go away, for if Mother sees me with you, she’ll think
ill of me. Though she doesn’t strike me, her mere words hurt
me more than blows.”
“No, Anyuta, I'll go with you.” And, without waiting for
her answer, I walked right through the gate, up the stairs,
and into the hut. Anyuta cried after me, “Wait, sir, wait!”
But I paid no attention to her. In the hut I found Anyuta’s
mother, who was kneading dough; near her, on a bench,
sat her future son-in-law. I told her, without beating about
the bush, that I wanted her daughter to marry Ivan, and that
I had brought the means to remove the obstacle thereto.
“Thank you, sir,” said the old woman, “but there is no
longer any need for it. Vanyukha has just come to tell us
138 A JOURNEY FROM ST. PETERSBURG TO MOSCOW
that his father has agreed to let him off, to come to us. So
we'll have the wedding on Sunday.”
“Then let my promised gift [*225] be Anyuta’s dowry.”
“Thank you, no. Gentlemen do not give girls a dowry for
nothing. If you have wronged my Anyuta and are giving her
a dowry to make up for it, God will punish you for your mis-
deed, but I will not take the money. If you are a good man
and do not hurt the poor, then malicious people would think
the worst of me for taking money from you.”
- I could not sufficiently admire the noble dignity which I
had found in these simple country people. Meanwhile Anyuta
had come into the hut, and sang my praises to her mother.
I tried again to give them the money, offering it to Ivan to-
ward setting up his house, but he said to me: “I have two
hands, sir, and with them I will set up my house.” Seeing that
my presence was not very pleasant for them, I left them and
returned to my carriage.
As I drove on from Edrovo, I could not put Anyuta out
of my mind. [*226] Her innocent sincerity pleased me beyond
measure. Her mother’s noble act enchanted me. I compared this
noble mother, with her sleeves rolled up over the dough or
over her milking pail near the cow, with urban mothers. The
peasant woman refused to accept my honest, well-intended
hundred rubles, which, in proportion to her means and status,
would correspond to five, ten, fifteen thousand, or more, for
the wife of a colonel, privy councilor, major, or general. Now
if a distinguished magnate of the seventieth or — God forbid!
—the seventy-second proof were to offer the wife of a
colonel, major, privy councilor, or general, who has a pretty
or merely virtuous daughter, five, ten, or fifteen thousand
(which would be quite in proportion to my offer to the wife
of the Edrovo coachman), or if he hinted that he would give
her daughter a handsome dowry, or find her an official for
her husband, or [*227] secure her an appointment as a lady-
in-waiting —I ask you, city mothers, would not your heart
give a leap? Would you not want to see your daughter in a
gilt carriage, wearing diamonds, riding in a four-in-hand if
she now goes on foot, or in a tandem of eight in place of the
two sorry nags that draw her now? I grant that in order to
preserve custom and decorum you would not give in as easily
as chorus girls do. No, dear mothers, I give you one or two
months’ time, but no more. For if you leave the man of high
estate sighing in vain, he, being very busy with affairs of
state, will leave you so as not to waste on you the precious
time which he can better employ for the public good, A
thousand voices rise up against me and shower me with terms
of abuse: swindler, cheat, canaille, beast, and so forth. [*228]
My dear ones, calm yourselves, I am not casting aspersions
on you. Are you really all like that? Look into this mirror:
whosoever recognizes herself in it, let her scold me unmerci-
fully.” I will not enter a complaint against her either, nor
dispute her word through a lawsuit.
Anyuta, Anyuta, you have turned my head! Why did I not
make your acquaintance fifteen years ago? Your frank inno-
cence, which is proof against the audacity of passion, would
have taught me to walk in the way of chastity. Why was not
the first kiss of my life the one I pressed upon your cheek in
my soul’s ecstasy? The influence of your living virtue would
have penetrated to the depths of my heart, and I would have
escaped the shameful acts which have filled my life. I would
have kept away from the loathsome hirelings of lust, would
have honored the nuptial couch, would not have violated
the domestic bond in my carnal insatiability; [*229] virginity
would have been for me a holy of holies, and I would not have
dared to lay violent hands on it. O my Anyutushka! Be ever
near us and teach us by your unconstrained innocence. |
know that you will lead back into the way of virtue him who
has begun to turn aside, and strengthen him who is tending
to go astray. Let not your heart be troubled if a man steeped
in debauch and grown gray in shamelessness should pass by and
scorn you; do not attempt to bar his way with the solace of
your converse. His heart is already stone; his soul is encrusted
with a layer of adamant. The beneficent sting of innocent vir-
tue cannot make any real impression on him. Its point will
glide over the smooth surface of vice. Beware lest your sharp
weapon be blunted against it. But do not let the youth pass
by who is allured by the dangerous charms of beauty; catch
him in your net. He seems haughty, [*230] supercilious, im-
petuous, insolent, presumptuous, spiteful, and insulting. But
his heart will yield to your influence and will respond to your
wholesome example. Anyuta, I cannot part from you, al-
though I can already see the fourteenth milestone dividing
us. But what of the custom Anyuta told me about? They
wanted to marry her off to a ten-year-old boy. Who could
sanction such a union? Why does not the hand that guards the
law arm itself for the eradication of this evil custom?® In
Christian law marriage is a sacrament, in civil law, an agree-
ment or contract. What priest can bless an unequal marriage,
and what judge can enter it upon his register? Where there is
great disparity in ages, there can be no true marriage. It is for-
bidden by the law of nature, as a thing harmful [*231] to man,
and it ought to be forbidden by the civil law, as injurious to
society. Man and wife in society are two citizens who enter
into an agreement, confirmed by law, whereby primarily they
promise mutual satisfaction of their passion (let no one dare
to deny this first law of cohabitation and the foundation of
the marital bond, the source of the purest love, and the firm-
est foundation stone of conjugal concord), they promise to
live together, to have and to hold their worldly goods in
common, to bring up together the fruit of their passion, to live
in peace, and to avoid offending one another. Can the terms
of this agreement be satisfied if the ages are unequal? If the
husband is ten years old, and the wife is twenty-five, as often
happens among the peasantry, or if the husband is fifty and the
wife fifteen or twenty, as is the case among the gentry, can
there be any mutual satisfaction of desire? [*232] Tell me,
you aged husbands, but tell me honestly, do you deserve the
name of husband? You can kindle the fire of passion; you
cannot put it out. By the inequality of years one of the first
laws of nature is violated, and how can man-made law be
firm, if it is not based on the law of nature? Let us answer
unequivocally: it cannot. To bring up the fruits of their mu-
tual passion. But can there be any mutuality where on one
side there is a flame, and on the other, insensibility? Can there
be any fruit, if the planted tree is deprived of beneficent rain
and quickening dew? And if there ever is any fruit, it will be
shriveled, unsightly, and liable to early decay. Do not offend
one another. It is an eternally true principle that if passion is
mutually satisfied through a blissful sympathy between hus-
band and wife, [*233] the marital union is happy, and small
domestic troubles subside with the approach of joy. And when
the chill of old age draws an impenetrable, icy film over sen-
sual enjoyment, the memory of former warmth will comfort
dreary old age. One condition of the marriage contract can
be fulfilled in inequality. That of living together. But will
there be any mutuality in that? One will be an autocratic
ruler who has absolute power in his hands, the other will be a
feeble subject and a complete slave, capable only of carrying
out the master’s commands. These, Anyuta, are the virtuous
thoughts with which you have inspired me. Good-bye, my
dear Anyutushka! Your precepts will be deeply engraved in
my heart forever, and my children’s children shall inherit
them. The Khotilov post station was already in sight, but I was
still thinking of the Edrovo lass, and, in the elation of my soul,
[*234] I cried aloud: “O Anyuta! Anyuta!” The road was
rough and the horses were going at a walk. The driver heard
my exclamation and turned around, “It looks as though you’ve
taken a liking to our Anyutka, sir,” he said, smiling and ad-
justing his hat. “Yes, she’s quite a girl. You're not the only
one she’s bewitched. She carries off the honors at everything.
In our village there are a lot of beautiful girls, but they’re
not worth looking at beside her. How she can dance! She’ll
dance rings around any of them. And when she goes to reap
in the field, you can’t feast your eyes enough watching her.
Well, brother Van’ka is a lucky dog!”
“Is Ivan your brother?”
“My cousin. And a fine fellow he is! Three lads were
courting Anyutka at the same time, but Ivan cut them all
out. They tried one thing after another, but it was no good.
Vanyukha hooked her right off.” (Just then we entered the
village.) “Yes, sir! Everybody dances, but not like a minstrel.”
And he drove up to the post station.
[*235] “Everybody dances, but not like a minstrel,” I re-
peated, as I got out of the carriage. “Everybody dances, but
not like a minstrel,” I repeated again as I bent down, picked
up, and unfolded —
<place_14>[*236] KHOTILOV</place_14>
A Project for the Future. We have brought our beloved
country step by step to the flourishing condition in which it
now stands; we see science, art, and industry carried to the
highest degree of perfection which man can achieve; we see
that in our realm human reason, spreading wide its wings,
freely and unerringly soars everywhere to greatness, and
has now become the sure guardian of public law. Our heart,
too, under reason’s sovereign protection, is free to ascend in
prayer to the almighty Creator. With inexpressible joy we
can say that our country is an abode pleasing to the Deity,
because its order is not based on prejudice and superstition,
[*237] but on our inward perception of the mercy of our
common Father. Unknown to us are the hostilities which
have so often separated people on account of their religious
beliefs; unknown to us, also, is compulsion in them. Born in
this freedom, we truly regard each other as brothers, belong-
ing to the same family, and having one Father, God.
The torch of learning, enlightening our legislation, now
distinguishes it from the legislation of many countries. The
balanced separation of powers, the equality of property, de-
stroy the root even of civil discord. Moderation in punishment
causes the laws of the supreme power to be respected like the
commands of tender parents to their children, and prevents
even guileless misdeeds. Clarity in the ordinances concerning
the acquisition and protection of property prevents the out-
break of family disputes. The boundary furrow that separates
the possessions of one citizen [*238] from another is deep
and plain to ali and sacredly respected by all. Private offenses
are rare among us, and are settled amicably. Popular educa-
tion has taken pains to make us gentle, peace-loving citizens,
but above all, to make us men.
Enjoying domestic tranquillity, having no external enemies,
having brought society to the highest bliss of civic concord,
shall we be so devoid of humane feeling, devoid of pity, de-
void of the tenderness of noble hearts, devoid of brotherly
love, that we endure under our eyes an eternal reproach to
us, a disgrace to our remotest descendants —a whole third
of our comrades, our equal fellow citizens, our beloved
brothers in nature, in the heavy fetters of servitude and slav-
ery? The bestial custom of enslaving one’s fellow men, which
originated in [*239] the hot regions of Asia, a custom worthy
of savages, a custom that signifies a heart of stone and a total
lack of soul, has quickly spread far and wide over the face
of the earth. And we Slavs, sons of slava [ie., “glory”],
glorious + among earth-born generations, both in name and
deed, benighted by the darkness of ignorance, have adopted
this custom, and, to our shame, to the shame of past centuries,
to the shame of this age of reason, we have kept it inviolate
even to this day.
It is well known to you from the deeds of your fathers,
it is well known to all from our chronicles, that the wise
rulers of our people, inspired by a sincere love of all men, and
having come to understand the natural bond of civil society,
tried to put an end to this hundred-headed evil. But their
sovereign acts were nullified by that estate, then proud of its
pre-eminent position in our realm [*240] but now super-
annuated and fallen into contempt, the hereditary nobility.
Our royal ancestors were impotent, despite their scepter’s
might, to break the fetters of civil slavery. Not only were
they unable to carry out their good intentions, but, by the
machinations of the aforementioned highest estate of the
realm, they were driven to enact laws contrary to their own
judgment and inclinations. Our fathers, perhaps with heart-
felt tears, beheld these oppressors tightening the fetters and
making heavier the chains of the most useful members of so-
ciety. The agriculturists are even to this day slaves among us;
we do not recognize them as fellow citizens equal to ourselves,
and we have forgotten that they are men. O beloved fellow
citizens! O true sons of the fatherland! Look about you and
see the error of your ways! The ministers of the everlasting
God, moved by the same desire as ours for the good of society
and the happiness of man, [*241] have, in their teachings
in the name of the ever merciful God Whom they profess,
explained to you how contrary to His wisdom and love
it is to rule arbitrarily over your neighbor. They have sought
with arguments drawn from nature and from our hearts to
demonstrate to you your cruelty, injustice, and sinfulness.
Their voice still calls out loud and solemnly in the temples
of the living God: “Bethink yourselves, ye who have gone
astray; be merciful, ye who are cruel of heart! Break the fet-
ters of your brothers, open the prison of slavery, and give
your fellow men a chance to taste the sweets of community
life, for which they, like yourselves, have been destined by
the All-Merciful. They enjoy the beneficent rays of the sun
just as you do, they have the same limbs and the same senses
as you, and chey ought to have the same right to use them.”
If the servants of the Godhead have made manifest to you
[*242] the individual human iniquity of slavery, we consider
it our duty to demonstrate to you what harm it does to so-
ciety, and its injustice to the citizen. It would seem to be
superfluous, since the spirit of philosophy has been abroad
so long, to search out and repeat arguments in favor of the
essential equality of man, and hence of citizens. To him who
has grown up under the protection of liberty, who is filled
with generous sentiments and not with prejudices, the normal
emotions of his heart are proofs of this fundamental equality.
But it is the misfortune of mortals on earth to go astray in the
full light of day, to fail to see that which is right before their
eyes. When you were young, they taught you at school the
foundations of natural and civil law. Natural law showed you
men hypothetically outside of society, who had received from
nature the same constitution, [*243] hence possessed the same
rights, and consequently were equal in every way, no man be-
ing subject to any other. Civil law showed you men who had
exchanged unlimited freedom for the right to enjoy freedom
in peace. But though all have accepted restrictions upon their
freedom and submitted their acts to regulation, yet all, because
in a state of nature they would have been equal from birth,
must still be equal in the limitations set to their natural free-
dom. And consequently no one is subject to any one else. The
sovereign power in society is the law, because it is one and the
same for all. But what was the impelling force that caused
men to establish a social order and voluntarily restrict their
freedom of action? Reason will say, “Their own good”; the
heart will say, “Their own good”; the incorruptible civil
law will say, “Their own good.” We live in a society which
has already passed through many stages of progress; there-
fore [*244] we have forgotten its original condition. But
consider all new nations, and, if we may so put it, all societies
in a state of nature. First, they regard enslavement as a crime;
second, they subject only criminals or the enemy to the yoke
of slavery. If we keep these concepts in mind, we will realize
how far we have strayed from the aim of society, how far re-
moved we still are from the ideal of social happiness. All that
we have said is familiar to you; you have imbibed it with your
mother’s milk. Only the prejudice of the moment, only selfish
greed (let not my words offend you! ), only greed blinds us
and makes us seem like madmen raving in darkness.
But who among us wears the fetters, who feels the burden
of slavery? The agriculturist! The man who feeds us in our
leanness and satisfies our hunger, who gives us health and
prolongs our life, [*245] without having the right to dispose
of what he cultivates nor of what he produces. But who has
a greater right to a field than the man who cultivates it? Let
us imagine that men have come into a wilderness to establish
a community. Mindful of their need of sustenance, they divide
up the uncultivated land. Who deserves a share in this divi-
sion? Is it not he who knows how to plough the land, he who
has the strength and determination requisite for the task?
The land will be useless to a child, an old man, a weak, sick,
or lazy man. It will remain a wilderness, and the wind will
not rustle any grain growing upon it. If it is useless to the
owner, it is equally useless to society, for the owner cannot
render the surplus to society when he does not even have
what he needs for himself. Hence, in primitive society, he who
was able to cultivate his field had a proprietary right to it, and,
by virtue of cultivating it, [*246] had the exclusive enjoyment
of it. But how very far we have departed from the primitive
social relation to property! With us, he who has the natural
right to it is not only completely excluded from it, but, while
working another’s field, sees his sustenance dependent on
another’s power! To your enlightened minds these truths can-
not be incomprehensible, but your acts, in the application of
these truths, are impeded, as we have already said, by preju-
dice and self-interest. Even so, can your hearts, which are
full of love for humanity, prefer self-interest to the sentiments
that soothe the heart? But wherein does your profit consist?
Can a country in which two thirds? of the citizens are de-
prived of their civil rights and to some extent are dead to
the law to be called happy? Can the civic condition of the
peasant in Russia be called happy? Only an insatiable blood-
sucker will say that the peasant [*247] is happy, for he has
no conception of a better state of affairs.
We shall now try to refute these brutal rules of the mighty,
as our predecessors once unsuccessfully sought to do by their
acts.
Civic happiness may present itself to us in various forms.
A country is happy, they say, if peace and order reign in it.®
It seems to be happy when the fields do not lie fallow and
when proud buildings rise in the cities. It is said to be happy
when it extends the sway of its arms and rules far and wide
abroad, not only by force, but by its influence over the
opinions of others. But all these manifestations of happiness
may be called external, ephemeral, fleeting, partial, and imagi-
nary.
Let us look at the valley which spreads out before our
view. What do we see? [*248] A great military camp. Silence
reigns everywhere in it. All the warriors stand in their places.
The most precise order may be seen in their ranks. One order,
one motion of the commander’s hand, sets the whole camp in
motion, and moves it in perfect order. But can we say the
soldiers are happy? Having been turned into puppets by the
strictness of military discipline, they are deprived even of the
freedom of motion, the distinguishing characteristic of animate
beings. They know only the commander’s orders, think only
what he wants them to think, and move where he orders them
to. So all-powerful is the commander’s control over the might-
iest force in the country. United they can do anything,
while disunited and as individuals they graze, like cattle,
wherever the shepherd pleases. Organization at the expense
of freedom is as inimical to our happiness as are fetters them-
selves. One hundred slaves, fettered to the benches of the
ship [*249] which is propelled by their oars, live in peace and
order; but look into their hearts and souls. There is torment,
grief, despair. Often would they exchange life for death, but
even that is denied them. To end their suffering would be hap-
piness, but happiness and slavery do not belong together,
hence they must live. Let us not, therefore, be blinded by the
outward peace and order of a country; let us not consider
it happy merely for these superficial reasons. Always look into
the hearts of your fellow citizens. If you find calm and peace
in them, then you may say in very truth that they are
happy. Having despoiled America, having fertilized its fields with
the blood of its natives, the Europeans put a stop to their
murders for the sake of new profit. The deserted fields of
that hemisphere, newly created by the mighty convulsions of
nature, felt the plough that racked its vitals. The grass that
had grown on rich [*250] meadows and withered away un-
used felt its blades mowed down by sharp scythes. Down
from the hills fell the proud trees that had shaded their sum-
mits from time immemorial. Barren forests and useless thickets
were transformed into fruitful fields, covered with hundreds
of plants native to America or successfully domesticated
there. The rich meadows were trampled by innumerable cattle,
destined for man’s food and labor. Everywhere may be seen
the cultivator’s constructive hand, everywhere the appearance
of well-being and external signs of order. But whose mighty
arm is it that urges grudging, lazy nature to give her fruits
in such abundance? Having massacred the Indians at a swoop,
the raging Europeans, the preachers of peace in the name of the
God of truth, the teachers of meekness and charity, by ac-
quiring slaves through purchase have grafted the cold-blooded
[*251] murder of slavery upon the root of the furious murder
of conquest. These unfortunate victims from the torrid banks
of the Niger and Senegal, torn from their homes and families,
transported to foreign lands, groaning under the heavy yoke
of authority, tear up the fertile fields of the America that
scorns their labors. And we call this land of destruction happy
because its meadows are not overgrown with thorns and its
fields abound in plants of every variety. We call that country
happy, where one hundred haughty citizens wallow in lux-
ury, while thousands have no secure subsistence nor proper
protection against heat and cold. Oh, that these prosperous
lands might become wilderness again! Oh, that thorns and
thistles might send their roots down deep and destroy all the
precious products of America! Tremble, my beloved ones,
lest they say of you: “Change the name, and the story may
be told of you.” 
[*252] Even now we marvel at the enormous size of the
Egyptian buildings. The incomparable pyramids will for a
long time bear witness to the daring architecture of the Egyp-
tians. But why were these foolish heaps of stone erected? For
the burial of the haughty Pharaohs. ‘These vainglorious rulers,
thirsting for immortality, wanted even after their demise to be
externally distinguished from their people. Thus the immen-
sity of these structures, useless as they were to the people, is
palpable proof of their enslavement. In the ruins of decayed
cities where the general welfare once ruled, we find the ruins
of schools, hospitals, hostelries, aqueducts, theaters, and
similar buildings; whereas in the cities where “I,” and not
““we,” was supreme, we find the ruins of superb royal palaces,
vast stables, and parks for animals, Let us compare the two:
our choice will not be difficult.
[*253] What indeed do we discover in the glory of con-
quest? Sound, fury, boastfulness, and exhaustion. I would
compare such glory with the balloons invented in the eight-
eenth century; ° made of silk fabric and quickly filled with
hot air, they ascend with the speed of sound to the extreme
limits of the ether. But what constituted their power is
constantly seeping out through the fine interstices of the
fabric, the weight which had been borne upward begins to
sink again, and that which has taken whole months of labor,
care, and expense to prepare can amuse the spectators for only
a few hours.
But let us ask what the conqueror longs for, what he is seek-
ing as he devastates populous countries or subjects wilder-
nesses to his dominion. We may obtain an answer from the
most savage of them all, from Alexander, called the Great, but
in truth great, not in his deeds, [*254] but in the power of
his spirit and in destruction. “O Athenians!” he exclaimed,
“how greatly I deserve your praise!” Fool! Look at the road
you have traveled. The fierce whirlwind of your progress,
roaring over your realm, draws its inhabitants into its vortex,
and, gathering up the whole power of the state in its onrush,
leaves behind it only desert and dead void. You fail to realize,
O savage boar, that when you have devastated your own land
by your victories, you will find nothing in the conquered
one to give you pleasure. If you have acquired a desert, it
will become a grave for your fellow citizens, in which they
will disappear; in settling the new desert, you will turn a
fertile land into a sterile one. What shall it profit you to con-
vert a desert into settlements, if in so doing you cause other
settlements to be deserted? But if you have acquired an
inhabited country, count your murders, and tremble with
horror. You must root out [*255] all the hearts that have
come to hate you in your terrible progress, for you must
not expect to be loved by those who have been driven to
fear you. After the destruction of the manly citizens, there
will remain only timid souls, submissive to you and ready to
accept the yoke of slavery; but even in them the hatred born
of your crushing victory will take deep root. Do not deceive
yourself: the fruit of your conquest will be murder and
hatred. You will live in the memory of future generations as
a scourge: ® you yourself will be tortured by the thought that
your new slaves detest you and pray for your death.
But, to return to our more immediate concern with the
condition of the agriculturists, we find it most harmful to
society. It is harmful because it prevents the increase of prod-
ucts and population, harmful by its example, and dangerous
in the unrest it creates. Man, motivated by self-interest,
[*256] undertakes that which may be to his immediate or
later advantage, and avoids that from which he expects no
present or future gain. Following this natural instinct, every-
thing we do for our own sake, everything we do without
compulsion, we do carefully, industriously, and well. On
the other hand, all that-we do not do freely, all that we do not
do for our own advantage, we do carelessly, lazily, and all
awry. Thus we find the agriculturists in our country. The
field is not their own, the fruit thereof does not belong to
them. Hence they cultivate the land lazily and do not care
whether it goes to waste because of their poor work. Compare
this field with the one the haughty proprietor gives the work-
er for his own meager sustenance. The worker is unsparing
in the labors which he spends on it. Nothing distracts him
from his work. The savagery of the weather [*257] he over-
comes bravely; the hours intended for rest he spends at work;
he shuns pleasure even on the days set aside for it. For he
looks after his own interest, works for himself, is his own
master. Thus his field will give him an abundant harvest;
while all the fruits of the work done on the proprietor’s
demesne will die or bear no future harvest; whereas they
would grow and be ample for the sustenance of the citizens,
if the cultivation of the fields were done with loving care,
if it were free.
But if forced labor brings smaller harvests, crops which
fail to reach the goal of adequate production also stop the
increase of the population. Where there is nothing to eat,
there will soon be no eaters,’ for all will die from exhaustion.
Thus the enslaved field, by giving an insufficient return,
starves to death the citizens for whom nature had intended
her superabundance. But this is not the only thing in slavery
that interferes with abundant life. [*258] To insufficiency
of food and clothing they have added work to the point of
exhaustion. Add to this the spurns of arrogance and the abuse
of power, even over man’s tenderest sentiments, and you see
with horror the pernicious effects of slavery, which differs
from victory and conquest only by not allowing what vic-
tory cuts down to be born anew. But it causes even greater
harm. It is easy to see that the one devastates accidentally and
momentarily, the other destroys continuously over a long
period of time; the one, when its onrush is over, puts an end
to its ravages, the other only begins where the first ends, and
cannot change except by upheavals which are always. dan-
gerous to its whole internal structure.
But nothing is more harmful than to see forever before
one the partners in slavery, master and slave.* On the one side
there is born conceit, on the other, servile fear. There can be
no bond between them other than [*259] force. And this,
concentrated in a small range, extends its oppressive auto-
cratic power everywhere, But the champions of slavery, who,
though they hold the sharp edge of power in their hands, are
themselves cast into fetters, become its most fanatical preach-
ers. It appears that the spirit of freedom is so dried up in
the slaves that they not only have no desire to end their suf-
ferings, but cannot bear to see others free. They love their
fetters, if it is possible for man to love his own ruination.®
I think I can see in them the serpent that wrought the fall of
the first man. The examples of arbitrary power are infec-
tious. We must confess that we ourselves, armed with the mace
of courage and the law of nature for the crushing of the hun-
dred-headed monster that gulps down the food prepared
for the people’s general sustenance — we ourselves, perhaps,
have been misled into autocratic acts, and, although our in-
tentions have always been good and [*260] have aimed at the
general happiness, yet our arbitrary behavior cannot be justi-
fied by its usefulness. Therefore we now implore your for-
giveness for our unintentional presumption.
Do you not know, dear fellow citizens, what destruction
threatens us and in what peril we stand? All the hardened
feelings of the slaves, not given vent by a kindly gesture of
freedom, strengthen and intensify their inner longings. A
stream that is barred in its course becomes more powerful in
proportion to the opposition it meets. Once it has burst the
dam, nothing can stem its flood. Such are our brothers whom
we keep enchained. They are waiting for a favorable chance
and time.* The alarum bell rings. And the destructive force
of bestiality breaks loose with terrifying speed. Round about
us we shall see sword and poison. Death and fiery desolation
will be the meed [*261] for our harshness and inhumanity.
And the more procrastinating and stubborn we have been
about the loosening of their fetters, the more violent they will
be in their vengefulness. Bring back to your memory the
events of former times. Recall how deception roused the slaves
to destroy their masters. Enticed by a crude pretender," they
hastened to follow him, and wished only to free themselves
from the yoke of their masters; and in their ignorance they
could think of no other means to do this than to kill their
masters. They spared neither sex nor age. They sought more
the joy of vengeance than the benefit of broken shackles.
This is what awaits us, this is what we must expect. Danger
is steadily mounting, peril is already hovering over our heads.
Time has already raised its scythe and is only awaiting an
opportunity. The first demagogue or humanitarian who rises
up [*262] to awaken the unfortunates will hasten the scythe’s
fierce sweep. Beware!
But if the terror of destruction and the danger of the loss
of property can move those among you who are weak, shall
we not be brave enough to overcome our prejudices, to sup-
press our selfishness, to free our brothers from the bonds of
slavery, and to re-establish the natural equality of all? ” Know-
ing the disposition of your hearts, I am sure that you will be
convinced more readily by arguments drawn from the human
heart than by the calculations of selfish reason, and still less
by fears of danger. Go, my dear ones, go to the dwellings of
your brothers and proclaim to them the change in their lot.
Proclaim with deep feeling: “Moved to pity by your fate,
sympathizing with our fellow men, having come to recognize
your equality, and convinced that our interests are mutual,
we have come to embrace [*263] our brothers. We have
abandoned the haughty discrimination which for so long a
time has separated us from you, we have forgotten the in-
equality that has existed between us, we rejoice now in our
mutual victory, and this day on which the shackles of our
fellow citizens are broken shall become the most famous day
in our annals. Forget our former injustice to you, and let us
sincerely love one another.”
Such will be your utterance; deep down in your hearts
you already hear it. Do not delay, my dear ones. Time flies;
our days go by and we do nothing. Let us not end our lives
merely fostering good intentions which we have not been
able to carry out. Let not our posterity take advantage of this,
win our rightful crown of glory, and say contemptuously
of us: “They had their day.”
That is what I read in the mud-stained paper which |
[*264] picked up in front of the post hut as I left my carriage.
Upon entering the hut I asked who were the travelers who
had stopped there immediately before me. “The last traveler,”
the postilion told me, “was a man about fifty years old; ac-
cording to his traveling permit he was going to Petersburg.
He forgot and left a bundle of papers here, and I’m forward-
ing them to him right now.” I asked the postilion to let me
look through the papers, and, unfolding them, I discovered
that the piece I had found belonged with them. By means of
a good tip I persuaded him to let me have the papers. Upon
examining them I found that they belonged to a dear friend
of mine; hence I did not consider their acquisition a theft. Up
to the present, he has never asked me to return them, but has
left me free to do with them what I pleased.
While they were changing my horses, I examined with
great [*265] interest the papers I had acquired. I found a
large number of articles in the same vein as the one I had
read. Everywhere I recognized the spirit of a charitable man;
everywhere I saw a citizen of the future. It was clear above all
else that my friend was deeply disturbed by the inequality
of the estates. A whole bundle of papers and drafts of laws re-
ferred to the abolition of serfdom in Russia. But my friend,
realizing that the supreme power was not strong enough to
cope with a sudden change of opinions, had outlined a pro-
gram of temporary legislation leading to a gradual emancipa-
tion of the agriculturists in Russia. I will sketch here the
main lines of his scheme. The first law provides for the dis-
tinction between rural and domestic serfdom. The latter is
abolished first of all, and the landlords are forbidden to take
into their houses any peasant or anybody registered in the
last census as a village dweller. If a landlord [*266] takes a
peasant into his house as a servant or artisan, he at once be-
comes free. Peasants are to be allowed to marry without ask-
ing their masters’ permission. Marriage license fees are pro-
hibited. The second law has to do with the property and
protection of the peasants. They shall own individually the
plot that they cultivate, for they shall pay the head tax them-
selves. Property acquired by a peasant shall belong to him,
and no one shall arbitrarily deprive him of it. The peasant is
to be reinstated as a citizen. He shall be judged by his peers,
that is, in courts in which manorial peasants, among others,
are to be chosen to serve. The peasant shall be permitted to
acquire real estate, that is, to buy land. He may without hin-
drance obtain his freedom by paying his master [*267] a
fixed sum to release him. Arbitrary punishment without due
process of law is prohibited. “Avaunt, barbarous custom; per-
ish, power of the tigers!” says our legislator. — Thereupon
follows the complete abolition of serfdom.
Among the many decrees referring to the restoration of
the highest possible degree of equality to all citizens, I found
the Table of Ranks. How anomalous it is, how out of keep-
ing with modern times, anyone may see for himself. But the
bell in the harness bow of the shaft horse began to tinkle and
called me for my departure; so I decided that it would be
better to consider what is more profitable for a traveler by
post — whether to let the horses go at a trot or at an amble,
whether it is better for a post horse to trot or to gallop
than to occupy myself with that which does not exist.
<place_15>[*268] VYSHNY VOLOCHOK</place_15>
I never pass this new town without stopping to look at the
locks of its canal. The first man to whom it occurred to emu-
late nature in her benefactions and to put a river to work,
thus bringing all the ends of a territory into closer communi-
cation, is worthy to be remembered by the most distant pos-
terity. When the presently existing powers decay from natural
and moral causes, when their golden fields are overgrown with
thorns, when adders, serpents, and toads make their nests in
the ruins of the magnificent palaces of their haughty rulers,
then the curious traveler will find eloquent remains of their
greatness in commerce. The Romans built great roads and
aqueducts whose durability is justly admired even to the pres-
ent day, [*269] but they had no conception of inland water-
ways such as we now have in Europe. Because of our long
winters and hard frosts, we shall never have roads such as
the Romans had, but our canals will not soon silt up, even
without proper care. It has been no small source of pleasure for me to watch the
Vyshny Volochok Canal full of barges carrying grain and
other goods as they got ready to pass through the locks for
the rest of their voyage to Petersburg. Here one could see
the true wealth of the soil and the agriculturist’s superabun-
dance, here one could see in its full glory the mighty mover of
human actions, self-interest. But if at first glance my spirit
was delighted at the sight of this prosperity, at second thoughts
my joy soon waned. For I remembered that in Russia many
agriculturists were not working for themselves, and that thus
the abundance of the earth in many districts [*270] of Russia
bears witness only to the heavy lot of its inhabitants. My
satisfaction was transformed into indignation such as I feel
when in summer time I walk down the customs pier and look
at the ships that bring us the surplus of America and its pre-
cious products, such as sugar, coffee, dyes, and other things,
not yet dry from the sweat, tears, and blood that bathed them
in their production. “Remember,” my friend once said, “that the coffee in your
cup, and the sugar dissolved in it, have deprived a man like
yourself of his rest, that they have been the cause of labors
surpassing. his strength, the cause of tears, groans, blows, and
abuse. Now dare to pamper your gullet, hard-hearted wretch! ”
The sight of his disgust as he said this shook me to the depths
of my soul. My hand trembled, and I spilled the coffee.
[*271] But you, O inhabitants of Petersburg, who feed on
the superabundance of the fertile districts of your country,
whether at magnificent banquets, or at a friendly feast, or
alone, as your hand raises the first piece of bread meant to
nourish you, stop and think. Might I not say the same things
to you about it that my friend said to me about the products
of America? Have not the fields on which it grew been en-
riched by sweat, tears, and groans? You are fortunate if the
piece of bread for which you hungered was made from grain
grown on what is called crown land, or at least on a field that
pays its proprietor a commutation tax. But woe to you if
it is made of grain that comes from a nobleman’s granary!
Upon it are grief and despair, upon it is made manifest the
curse of the Almighty, who in His anger said: “Cursed be
the earth in its fruits.” * [*272] Beware lest ye be poisoned by
the food ye covet. The bitter tears of the poor lie heavy on
it. Put it away from your lips, and fast, for that may be a
sincere and wholesome fast.
The story of a certain landed proprietor proves that man
for the sake of his personal advantage forgets humanity
towards his fellow man, and that to find an example of hard-
heartedness we need not go to far-off countries nor seek mira-
cles through thrice-nine lands; they take place before our eyes
in our own country. A certain man who, as they say in the vernacular, did not
make his mark in the government service, or who did not
wish to make it there, left the capital, acquired a small village
of one or two hundred souls, and determined to make his liv-
ing by agriculture. He did not apply himself to the plough
but intended most vigorously [*273] to make all possible use
of the natural strength of his peasants by applying them to
the cultivation of the land. To this end he thought it the
surest method to make his peasants resemble tools that have
neither will nor impulse; and to a certain extent he actually
made them like the soldiers of the present time who are com-
manded in a mass, who move to battle in a mass, and who
count for nothing when acting singly. To attain his end he
took away from his peasants the small allotment of plough
land and the hay meadows which noblemen usually give them
for their bare maintenance, as a recompense for all the forced
labor which they demand from them. In a word, this noble-
man forced all his peasants and their wives and children to
work every day of the year for him. Lest they should starve,
he doled out to them a definite [*274] quantity of bread,
known by the name of monthly doles. Those who had no fam-
ilies received no doles, but dined according to the Lacedae-
monian custom, together, at the manor, receiving thin cabbage
soup on meat days, and on fast days bread and kvas, to fill
their stomachs. If there was any real meat, it was only in Easter
Week. These serfs also received clothing befitting their condition.
Their winter boots, that is, bast shoes, they made for them-
selves; leggings they received from their master; while in sum-
mer they went barefooted. Naturally these serfs had no cows,
horses, ewes, or rams. Their master did not withhold from
these serfs the permission, but the means to have them. Who-
ever was a little better off and ate sparingly, kept a few chick-
ens, which the master [*275] sometimes took for himself, pay-
ing for them as he pleased. With such an arrangement it is not surprising that agricul-
ture in Mr. So-and-So’s village was in a flourishing condition.
Where the crops were a failure elsewhere, his grain showed a
fourfold return; when others had a good crop, his grain had
a tenfold return or better. In a short time he added to his two
hundred souls another two hundred as victims of his greed,
and, proceeding with them just as with the first, he increased
his holdings year after year, thus multiplying the number of
those groaning in his fields. Now he counts them by the thou-
sand and is praised as a famous agriculturist.
Barbarian! You do not deserve to bear the name of citizen.
What good does it do the country that every year a few
thousand more bushels of grain are grown, if those who pro-
duce it are valued on a par with the ox whose job it is [*276]
to break the heavy furrow? Or do we think our citizens happy
because our granaries are full and their stomachs empty? Or
because one man blesses the government, rather than thou-
sands? The wealth of this bloodsucker does not belong to
him. It has been acquired by robbery and deserves severe pun-
ishment according to law. Yet there are people who, looking
at the rich fields of this hangman, cite him as an example of
perfection in agriculture. And you wish to be called merciful,
and you bear the name of guardians of the public good! In-
stead of encouraging such violence, which you regard as the
source of the country’s wealth, direct your humane vengeance
against this enemy of society. Destroy the tools of his agricul-
ture, burn his barns, silos, and granaries, and scatter their
ashes over the fields where he practiced his tortures; stigma-
tize [*277] him as a robber of the people, so that everyone
who sees him may not only despise him but shun his approach
to avoid infection from his example.
<place_16>[*278] Vydropusk</place_16>
Here I again took up my friend’s papers. Into my hands
fell a draft of a law for the abolition of court ranks,
A Project for the Future. In order to restore gradually
the natural and civil equality which had been violated in so-
ciety, our ancestors considered it by no means unimportant
to curtail the rights of the nobility. Though at first useful to
the country through its personal merits, its inherited rights
subsequently weakened its achievements: the root, sweet in
its planting, ultimately produced a bitter fruit. In place of
bravery, conceit and selfishness were enthroned; instead of
nobility of soul and generosity, servility and lack of self-con-
fidence, those true devourers of greatness. Living among
[*279] such small souls and impelled toward pettiness by
their flattery of hereditary virtues and merits, many rulers
imagined that they were gods, and that everything they
touched became good and radiant. Such, indeed, ought to be
the effect of our acts, but only for the public good. In such
a delusion of grandeur, the rulers came to think that their
slaves and attendants who constantly stood around in their
presence took on something of their luster, that the royal
radiance was refracted, so to speak, in these new crystals, and
appeared magnified and even more brilliantly reflected. While
their minds were thus gone astray, the rulers set up their court
idols, who, like true little theatrical gods, obey the whistle or
the rattle. Let us review the ranks of court offices, and with
a smile of compassion turn away from those who boast about
their services, though we should weep [*280] when we see
them preferred to those of real merit. My lord steward, my
master of the horse, and even my groom and coachman, my
cook, cupbearer, falconer, and his subaltern hunters, my gen-
tlemen of the bedchamber, he who shaves me, he who combs
the hair on my head, he who wipes the dust and dirt from my
shoes, not to mention many others, are made equal or even
superior to those who serve their country with their spiritual
and physical strength, sparing for its sake neither their health
nor blood, happy even to die for the glory of their country.
What good does it do you that cleanliness and neatness reign
in my house? Will you satisfy your hunger the better because
my food is prepared better than yours and because wine from
all the corners of the universe flows in my goblets? Can you
find shelter against the inclemency of the weather on your
journey because my coach of state is gilded and my horses
are sleek? [*281] Will your fields produce a better crop, will
your meadows be greener if they are trampled over for my
entertainment in the hunt? You will smile compassionately.
But many another, in his just indignation, will say to us: “He
who supervises your palace, he who heats it, he who blends
the hot spiciness of southern plants with the cold viscosity of
northern fats to please your weary stomach and jaded taste,
he who makes the sweet juice of the African grape foam in
your goblet, he who greases the wheels of your chariot and
feeds and waters your horses, he who in your name wages
bloody war against the beasts of the forest and the birds of
the air — all these parasites, all these pamperers of your con-
ceit, and many others of their ilk, rank above me, who have
shed [*282] streams of blood on the battlefield, who have lost
the most essential limbs of my body in defending your cities
and palaces (where your cowardice was cloaked by a sem-
blance of majesty and valor); above me, who have sacrificed
the days of joy, of youth, and of pleasure in order to save the
smallest farthing, so that, as far as possible, the common bur-
den of taxation might be lightened; who have neglected my
own estate, while working day and night to find means to pro-
mote the general welfare; who have slighted kindred, friends,
and the union of heart and blood, in order to proclaim in
court true justice in your name, that you might be loved.
Our hair grows white in our exploits, our strength is exhausted
in our undertakings, and at the brink of the grave we barely
earn your good will, while these calves that are fatted at the
_udders of luxury and vice, these bastard sons of the father-
land, will inherit our property.”
[*283] This and even more will many of you say, and
justly so, What shall we, the lords of power, reply? We shall
veil our humiliation in hard indifference, but our eyes will
shoot forth flames of wrath against those who have said these
things. Such frequently are our answers to proclamations of
the truth. And let no one be surprised to see even the best
among us dare to reply thus, for even the best of rulers lives
with flatterers, converses with flatterers, sleeps in flattery, and
walks in adulation. And flattery and adulation make him deaf,
blind, and unfeeling. But let no such reproach fall upon us. Having hated flat-
tery from our childhood, we have turned our heart away from
its poisonous sweetness even to this day, and now a new proof
of our love and devotion to you shall be made manifest. We
now abolish the equation of the Court Service to the Military
and [*284] Civil Service. Let the custom that to our shame
has existed for so many years now be expunged from memory.
Only real worth and real merit, only work for the public
good shall receive the rewards and distinctions of meritorious
Service. In lifting from our heart this intolerable burden which has
oppressed us for so long, we shall explain to you our reasons
for abolishing the ranks that were so offensive to real service
and merit. You have been told, and our ancestors held the
same view, that the Imperial throne, whose strength is rooted
in the opinion of the citizens, must be distinguished by ex-
ternal splendor, so that the thought of its grandeur may re-
main whole and inviolable. Hence the pompous external dis-
play of the rulers of nations, hence the herd of slaves that
surround them. Everyone must admit that narrow minds and
petty souls are impressed by external splendor. But the more
enlightened a nation is, [*285] the greater the number of
enlightened individuals, the less do appearances matter. Numa
could convince the still rude Romans that the nymph Egeria
guided him in his legislation.» The weak Peruvians readily
believed Manco Capac when he told them that he was the son
of the sun and that his laws came from heaven.2 Mohammed
was able to deceive the nomadic Arabs with his delirious
dreams. All of them made use of appearances; even Moses re-
ceived the tablets of the law upon a mountain amidst flashes
of lightning. Nowadays, however, one who would beguilingly
persuade needs not glittering outward show, but, so to speak,
glittering argument, seeming conviction. Nowadays he who
would strengthen his message from on high should seek to
give it the appearance of utility, and thereby he will reach all.
But of what use is external pomp to us, who direct all our
powers toward the well-being of each and every one of our
subjects? Is not our countenance radiant [*286] with the
utility of our decrees issued for the good of the country?
Everyone who looks at us will see our benevolence, will see
his own advantage in our acts, and will bow to us not as to a
tyrant striding in terror, but as to a sovereign enthroned in
goodness. If the ancient Persians had always been ruled be-
nevolently, they would not have invented Ahriman, the hate-
ful principle of evil. But if ostentatious show is useless to us,
how dangerous to the country its instruments can be! Their
one duty in our service being our satisfaction, how inventive
they will be in striving to please us. Our every wish will be
anticipated; they will not allow us to conceive a wish — in-
deed, not a thought — without having it realized. Look with
fear upon the effects of such servility. Shaken in its principles,
the firmest soul [*287] will lend an ear to this enticing flat-
tery, and will fall asleep. Thus the sweet sorcery enmeshes our
mind and heart. Other people’s sorrows and wrongs hardly
seem to us as important as passing indispositions,; we think it
unseemly or disgusting to bewail them and indeed we forbid
complaints about them. The most painful griefs and wounds,
even death itself, will appear to us as inevitable results of the
course of events; and, seen only, as it were, behind a dark
curtain, will scarcely be able to arouse in us that momentary
emotion which theatrical representations produce. For it is
not into our breast that the dart of disease and the sting of
evil have penetrated, and it is not in our breast that they are
trembling. This is a feeble picture of all the ruinous consequences of
royal pomp. Are we not truly blessed if we have managed to
protect ourselves from the perversion of our good intentions?
Are we not truly blessed if we have blocked this infectious
example? Firm in our good intentions, [*288] firm against
temptation from without, firm in the moderation of our de-
sires, we shall prosper anew and shall be an example to the
most distant posterity of how power can be joined with liberty
for mutual advantage.
<place_17>[*289] TORZHOK</place_17>
At the post station here I met a man who was on his way to
Petersburg to present a petition. It consisted of a request for
permission to set up a free printing press in this town. I told
him that no such permission was necessary, since this freedom
had been granted to all.* But what he really wanted was free-
dom from censorship, and here are his reflections on the
subject. Everyone in our country is now permitted to own and oper-
ate a printing press, and the time has passed when they were
afraid to grant this permission to private individuals, and when,
because in free printing offices false statements might be
printed, they renounced the general good and this useful insti-
tution. Now anybody may have the tools of printing, but
that which may be printed is still under watch and ward. The
censorship has become the nursemaid [*290] of reason, wit,
imagination, of everything great and enlightened. But where
there are nurses, there are babies and leading strings, which
often lead to crooked legs; where there are guardians, there
are minors and immature minds unable to take care of them-
selves. If there are always to be nurses and guardians, then
the child will walk with leading strings for a long time and
will grow up to be a cripple. Mitrofanushka ? will always be
a minor, will not take a step without his valet, and will not
be able to manage his inheritance without a guardian. Every-
where these are the consequences of the usual censorship, and
the sterner it is, the more disastrous are its consequences. Let
us listen to Herder: *
The best means of promoting good is noninterference, per-
mission to work for a good cause,* freedom of thought. Any
inquisition is harmful to the realm of learning: it makes the air
stifling and smothers [*291] the breath. A book that has to pass
through ten censorships before it sees the light of day is no
longer a book, but a creature of the Holy Inquisition, very often
a mutilated unfortunate, beaten with rods, gagged, and always
a slave. . . . In the province of truth, in the kingdom of thought
and spirit, no atl power can or should pass judgment; the
government cannot do it, much less its hooded censor.® In the
realm of truth he is not a judge, but a party, like the author... .
All improvement can take place only through enlightenment;
neither hand nor foot can move without head and brain... .
The better grounded a state is in its principles, the better or-
dered and the brighter and stronger in itself, the less danger it
incurs of being moved and swayed by the winds of shifting
opinion, by any pasquinade of an overwrought [*292] writer;
all the more readily, then, it will grant freedom of thought and
(with some allowance for its situation and condition)* freedom
166 A JOURNEY FROM ST. PETERSBURG TO MOSCOW
of writing, through which truth will ultimately be victorious.
Only tyrants are suspicious; only secret evildoers are fearful.
An open-hearted man, who does good and is firm in his prin-
ciples, lets anything be said about himself. He walks in the light
of day and turns to his own advantage even the worst lies of
his enemies. . . . All monopolies of thought are harmful... .
The ruler of a state must be almost without any favorite opinion
of his own in order that he may be able to embrace, tolerate,
refine, and direct toward the general welfare the opinions of
everyone in his state: hence great rulers are so rare.
Having recognized the usefulness of printing, the govern-
ment has made it open to all; having further recognized that
control of thought might invalidate its good intention in grant-
ing freedom to set up presses, it turned over the [*293] cen-
sorship or inspection of printed works to the Department of
Public Morals. Its duty in this matter can only be the pro-
hibition of the sale of objectionable works. But even this cen-
sorship is superfluous. A single stupid official in the Depart-
ment of Public Morals may do the greatest harm to enlighten-
ment and may for years hold back the progress of reason: he
may prohibit a useful discovery, a new idea, and may rob
everyone of something great. Here is an example on a small
scale. A translation of a novel is brought to the Department
of Public Morals for its imprimatur. The translator, following
the author, in speaking of love calls it “the tricky god.” The
censor in uniform and in the fullness of piety strikes out the
expression, saying, “It is improper to call a divinity tricky.”
He who does not understand should not interfere. If you want
fresh air, remove the smoky brazier; if you want light, remove
[*294] that which obscures it; if you do not want the child
to be timid, throw the rod out of the school. In a house where
whips and sticks are in fashion, the servants are drunkards,
thieves, and worse.
Let anyone print anything that enters his head. If anyone
finds himself insulted in print, let him get his redress at law.
Tam not speaking in jest. Words are not always deeds, thoughts
are not crimes. These are the rules in the Instruction for a
New Code of Laws.” But [*295] an offense in words or in
print is always an offense. Under the law no one is allowed to
libel another, and everyone has the right to bring suit. But if
one tells the truth about another, that cannot, according to
the law, be considered a libel. What harm can there be if books
are printed without a police stamp? Not only will there be
no harm; there will be an advantage, an advantage from the
first to the last, from the least to the greatest, from the Tsar
to the last citizen.
The usual rules of the censorship are: to strike out, blot
out, prohibit, tear, burn everything that is opposed to natural
religion and Revelation, everything in opposition to the gov-
ernment, every personal reflection, everything contrary to
public morality, order, and peace. Let us examine this more
closely. When a fool in his raving saith, not only in his heart,
but with a loud voice, “There is no God,” there is heard upon
the lips of all the fools a loud [*296] and fleeting echo, “There
is no God, there is no God.” But what of it? The echo is a
sound that strikes the air, sets it vibrating, and disappears. It
seldom leaves a mark upon the mind, and then only a faint
one, and never any trace upon the heart. God will ever be
God, perceived even by those who do not believe in Him.
But if you think that the Supreme Being will be offended by
blasphemy, can an official of the Department of Public Morals
be His chosen attorney? The Almighty will not give a power
of attorney to one who shakes a rattle or sounds the tocsin.
The hurler of thunder and lightning, Whom all the elements
obey, the agitator of hearts beyond the limits of the universe,
will disdain to be avenged even by the king himself, who
imagines himself to be His vicegerent upon earth. Who can
be the judge in an offense against the Eternal Father? The real
offender against God is he who imagines that he can sit in
judgment on an offense against Him. It is he who will be an-
swerable before Him.
[*297] The dissenters from the revealed religion have so
far done more harm in Russia than those who do not acknowl-
edge the existence of God, the atheists. There are not many
of the latter among us, because few among us are concerned
about metaphysics. The atheist errs in metaphysics; the dis-
senter in crossing himself with only two fingers.* Dissenters
or raskolniki is our name for all those Russians who in an
manner depart from the common doctrine of the Greek
Church. There are many of them in Russia; hence they are
allowed to hold divine services. But why should not every
aberration be permitted to be out in the open? The more open
it is, the quicker it will break down. Persecutions have only
made martyrs; cruelty has been the support of the Christian
religion itself. The consequences of schisms are sometimes
harmful. Prohibit them. They are propagated by example.
Destroy the example. A printed book will not cause a raskol’-
mik to throw himself into the fire, but a moving example
will. To prohibit foolishness is to encourage it. Give it
[*298] free rein; everyone will see what is foolish and what
is wise. What is prohibited is coveted. We are all Eve’s chil-
dren.
But in prohibiting freedom of the press, timid governments
are not afraid of blasphemy, but of criticism of themselves.
He who in moments of madness does not spare God, will not
in moments of lucidity and reason spare unjust power. He
who does not fear the thunders of the Almighty laughs at
the gallows. Hence freedom of thought is terrifying to gov-
ernments. The freethinker who has been stirred to his depths
will stretch forth his audacious but mighty and fearless arm
TORZHOK 169
against the idol of power, will tear off its mask and veil, and
lay bare its true character. Everyone will see its feet of clay;
everyone will withdraw the support which he had given it;
power will return to its source; the idol will fall. But if power
is not seated in the fog of contending opinions, if its throne
is founded on sincerity and true love of the common weal,
[*299] will it not rather be strengthened when its foundation
is revealed? And will not the true lover be loved more truly?
Mutuality is a natural sentiment, and this instinct is deeply
implanted in our nature. A solid and firm building needs only
its own foundation; it has no need of supports and buttresses.
Only when it is weakened by old age does it have need of
lateral support. Let the government be honest and its leaders
free from hypocrisy; then all the spittle and vomit will return
their stench upon him who has belched them forth; but the
truth will always remain pure and immaculate. He whose
words incite to revolt (in deference to the government, let
us so denominate all firm utterances which are based on truth
but opposed to the ruling powers). is just as much a fool as he
who blasphemes God. Let the government proceed on its
appointed path; then it will not be troubled by the empty
sound of calumny, even as the Lord of Hosts [*300] is not
disturbed by blasphemy. But woe to it if in its lust for power
it offends against truth. Then even a thought shakes its foun-
dations; a word of truth will destroy it; a manly act will scat-
ter it to the winds.
A personal attack, if it is unjustly offensive, is a libel. A
personal attack which states the truth is as admissible as truth
itself. If a blinded judge judges unjustly, and a defender of
innocence puolicizes his unjust decision and shows up his
wiles and injustice, that will be a personal attack, but one that
is permissible; if he calls him a venal, false, stupid judge, that
is a personal attack, but it is admissible. But if he begins to call
him dirty names and slanders him with offensive words such
as one hears in the marketplace, that is a personal attack, but
168 A JOURNEY FROM ST. PETERSBURG TO MOSCOW
will disdain to be avenged even by the king himself, who
imagines himself to be His vicegerent upon earth. Who can
be the judge in an offense against the Eternal Father? The real
offender against God is he who imagines that he can sit in
judgment on an offense against Him. It is he who will be an-
swerable before Him.
[*297] The dissenters from the revealed religion have so
far done more harm in Russia than those who do not acknowl-
edge the existence of God, the atheists. There are not many
of the latter among us, because few among us are concerned
about metaphysics. The atheist errs in metaphysics; the dis-
senter in crossing himself with only two fingers.* Dissenters
or raskoP niki is our name for all those Russians who in any
manner depart from the common doctrine of the Greek
Church. There are many of them in Russia; hence they are
allowed to hold divine services. But why should not every
aberration be permitted to be out in the open? The more open
it is, the quicker it will break down. Persecutions have only
made martyrs; cruelty has been the support of the Christian
religion itself. The consequences of schisms are sometimes
harmful. Prohibit them. They are propagated by example.
Destroy the example. A printed book will not cause a raskol’-
mik to throw himself into the fire, but a moving example
will. To prohibit foolishness is to encourage it. Give it
[*298] free rein; everyone will see what is foolish and what
is wise. What is prohibited is coveted. We are all Eve’s chil-
dren.
But in prohibiting freedom of the press, timid governments
are not afraid of blasphemy, but of criticism of themselves.
He who in moments of madness does not spare God, will not
in moments of lucidity and reason spare unjust power. He
who does not fear the thunders of the Almighty laughs at
the gallows. Hence freedom of thought is terrifying to gov-
ernments. The freethinker who has been stirred to his depths
will stretch forth his audacious but mighty and fearless arm
TORZHOK 169
against the idol of power, will tear off its mask and veil, and
lay bare its true character. Everyone will see its feet of clay;
everyone will withdraw the support which he had given it,
power will return to its source; the idol will fall. But if power
is not seated in the fog of contending opinions, if its throne
is founded on sincerity and true love of the common weal,
[*299] will it not rather be strengthened when its foundation
is revealed? And will not the true lover be loved more truly?
Mutuality is a natural sentiment, and this instinct is deeply
implanted in our nature. A solid and firm building needs only
its own foundation; it has no need of supports and buttresses.
Only when it is weakened by old age does it have need of
lateral support. Let the government be honest and its leaders
free from hypocrisy; then all the spittle and vomit will return
their stench upon him who has belched them forth; but the
truth will always remain pure and immaculate. He whose
words incite to revolt (in deference to the government, let
us so denominate all firm utterances which are based on truth
but opposed to the ruling powers). is just as much a fool as he
who blasphemes God. Let the government proceed on its
appointed path; then it will not be troubled by the empty
sound of calumny, even as the Lord of Hosts [*300] is not
disturbed by blasphemy. But woe to it if in its lust for power
it offends against truth. Then even a thought shakes its foun-
dations; a word of truth will destroy it; a manly act will scat-
ter it to the winds.
A personal attack, if it is unjustly offensive, is a libel. A
ersonal attack which states the truth is as admissible as truth
itself. If a blinded judge judges unjustly, and a defender of
innocence publicizes his unjust decision and shows up his
wiles and injustice, that will be a personal attack, but one that
is permissible; if he calls him a venal, false, stupid judge, that
is a personal attack, but it is admissible. But if he begins to call
him dirty names and slanders him with offensive words such
as one hears in the marketplace, that is a personal attack, but
172 A JOURNEY FROM ST. PETERSBURG TO MOSCOW
surface is smooth, but the ooze that lies at the bottom is grow-
ing turbid and dims the transparency of the water.
As he bade me good-bye, the critic of the censorship handed
me a small copybook. Reader, if you are not afraid of being
bored, read what lies before you. But if by any chance you
yourself belong to the Censorship Committee, turn the page
and hurry past.
    
</book>
