<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<excerpt>
A Journey from St. Petersburg to Moscow 
by Alexander Radishchev

LYUBANI

I suppose it is all the same to you, whether I travelled in summer or winter, especially since it is not uncommon for travellers to travel both summer and winter, starting out in a sleigh and returning in a wheel carriage. The corduroy road wore out my sides. I crawled out of the kibitka, and started on foot. . . .

A few steps from the road I noticed a peasant who was ploughing his field. It was warm; I looked at my watch: it was twenty minutes to one. I left the city on Saturday, so it was Sunday then. The peasant that was ploughing evidently belonged to a landowner that did not receive any tax from him. The peasant was ploughing with great care; evidently the field did not belong to the master. He was turning the plough with remarkable ease.

"God aid you! " I said as I approached the ploughman, who did not stop but finished the furrow he had begun.

"God aid you! " I repeated.

"Thank you, sir! " said the ploughman as he cleaned the ploughshare and transferred the plough to a new furrow.

"You are, of course, a Raskolnik [religious dissident], since you work on Sunday. "

"No, sir, I make the correct sign of the cross," he said, and showed me his three fingers put together; "but God is merciful and does not want a person to starve, as long as he has a family and sufficient strength."

"Have you not any time to work during the week, that you work on a Sunday, and at that in a great heat?"

"In the week, sir, there are six days, and we have to work for the manor six times a week, and in the evening we haul the hay from the meadows, if the weather is good; and on holidays the women and girls go to the woods to gather mushrooms and berries. God grant a rain this evening," he added as he made the sign of the cross." Sir, if you have any peasants, they are praying for the same."

" I have no peasants, my friend; and so nobody curses me. Have you a large family?"

"Three sons and three daughters. My eldest is ten years old."

"How do you manage to get enough grain, if you have only the Sundays to yourself ? "

"Not only the Sundays,-- the nights are ours too. We need not starve, if we are not lazy. You see, one horse is resting; and when this one gets tired, I'll take the other, and that's the way I make my work count."

"Do you work the same way for your master?

" No, sir! It would be sinful to work the same way; he has in his fields one hundred hands for one mouth, and I have but two hands for seven mouths, if you count it up. If you were to work yourself to death at your master's work, he would not thank you for it. . . . But, sir, you would not want to be in my hide ! " 

In the meantime the ploughman hitched another horse to his plough and, bidding me good-bye, began a new furrow.

The conversation with this agriculturist awakened a multitude of thoughts in me. Above all, I thought of the inequality of the peasant's condition. I compared the crown peasants with those of the proprietors. Both live in villages, but while the first pay a stated tax, the others have to be ready to pay whatever the master wishes. The first are judged by their peers; the others are dead to the laws, except in criminal matters. That thought made all my blood boil. 

Tremble, cruelhearted landlord! On the brow of every one of your peasants I see your condemnation written!

Tears flowed from my eyes, and in this condition the post horses brought me to the next station.

MEDNOE 

Twice every week all of the Russian Empire is informed that N. N. or B. B. is unable or unwilling to pay what he has borrowed, taken or what is demanded from him. The borrowed money has been gambled away, traveled away, spent away, eaten away, drunk away, given away or has perished in fire and water. Or N. N. or B. B. has in some other way gone into debt or incurred an obligation. Any case will do for the announcement which reads: At ten o clock this morning, on order of the county court or city magistrate, the real estate of retired captain T... consisting of house no. X, in such and such a district and six male and female souls, will be sold at auction. The sale will take place at said house. Interested parties may view the property in advance. 

Everyone is interested in a bargain. The day and hour of the sale has arrived. Buyers are assembling from all around. In the hall where the sale is to take place, the condemned are standing motionless. An old man of 75 years, leaning on a elmwood cane, is anxious to find out into whose hands his fate will pass, who will close his eyes. He served with the Master’s father in the Crimean campaign under Field Marshal Munnich. At the battle of Frankfurt he carried his wounded master off the field of battle on his shoulders. Returning home, he became the tutor for his young master. In [the master's] childhood, he had saved the boy from drowning, jumping into the river into which he had fallen while crossing on a ferry, and putting his life at risk, pulled him out. In [the master's] youth he had bailed him out of prison where he had been confined for his debts incurred while serving as a junior officer. 

An old women, 80 years of age, the old man’s wife, was the wet nurse for the mother of the young master: she was the young man’s nanny and had been the housekeeper up until the very moment when she was brought out for this auction. In all the years of her service she never wasted anything of the master’s, never thought of her own profit in any way, never lied, and if she ever gave occasion for annoyance it was only on account of her simple hearted scruples. 

A woman 40 years of age, a widow, was the wet nurse for the young master. And even now she still feels a certain tenderness toward him. Her blood flows in his veins. She is his second mother: he owes his life to her even more than to his natural mother. The latter had conceived him in a light-hearted moment, and had taken no part in his infancy. His nurses brought him up. They part with him as if with a son. 

A young woman, 18 year of age, her daughter and the granddaughter of the old couple. Wild beast, monster, reprobate! Look at her, look at her crimson cheeks, at the tears pouring from her enchanting eyes. Was it not you who, failing to entrap her innocence through flattery and enticement or to shake her steadfastness with threat, finally resorted to deceit. Having married her to your companion in treachery, your took his place and partook of the pleasure, which she had disdained to share with you. She found out about your deceit. Her bridegroom touched no more her bed, and you, deprived of the object of your desire, turned to force. Four scoundrels, executors of your will, holding her arms and legs--- No! Let us go no further. On her brow is sorrow, in her eyes despair. She is holding the infant, the sorrowful fruit of your deceit or violence, and the living image of his lascivious father. Having given birth to him, she began to forget his father’s savagery, and her heart began to feel tenderness toward the baby. She is afraid that he will fall into the hands of another like his father. The infant... your son, barbarian, your blood. Or do you think that there is no obligation when there is no church ceremony? Do you think that the blessing given at your order to the hired preacher of the word of God has confirmed their union? Do you think that forced marriage in God’s church can be called matrimony? The Almighty despises force, and delights in the wishes of the heart; they alone are uncorrupted. O, how many acts of fornication and seduction are committed in the name of the father of joys and the comforter of sorrows in the presence of his witnesses, unworthy of their office! 

A youth of twenty five, her wedded husband, companion and confidant of his master, who has now repented of his services. In his pocket is a knife. He grasps it tightly; it is not hard to guess his thoughts. Fruitless zeal! You will go to another. The hand of your master, hanging constantly above the head of the slave will bend your neck to any service. Hunger, chill, torment and heat – all of this will stand against you. Your mind is alien to noble thoughts. You do not know how to die. You will bend and will become a slave in spirit as well as law. And if you take it into your mind to resist, you will die an agonizing death in chains. There is no justice over you both. If your tormentor does not wish to punish you himself he will become your accuser. He will turn you over to the city justice. Justice! Where the accused has almost no power to defend himself! Let us pass over the other unfortunates brought out for sale. 

Barely had the dreaded hammer let out its hollow thud when the four unfortunates learned their fate – tears, sobs and moans pierced the ears of the entire assembly. . . . Having lived many years in each other’s embrace, these unfortunates because of this abominable auction will feel the anguish of parting. . . . My heart is so troubled that I jump up from amid the assembly and give the last pennies from my wallet to the unfortunates.

KEDROVO
When I reached this settlement, I got out of my carriage, for far from the highway, near the water, stood a crowd of women and girls. By force of habit, my lifelong master, passion, though now spent, drew my steps to the bevy of village beauties. The crowd consisted of more than thirty women. They were all in holiday attire, with their necks open, their legs bare, their arms akimbo, their dresses tucked up in front under their belts, their long shirts white, their faces happy, their cheeks glowing with health. Natural charm, although roughened by heat and cold, is delightful without any false front of sophistication. The beauty of youth was visible here in full splendor, on their lips smiles or hearty laughter, and behind them rows of teeth whiter than purest ivory. Teeth which would drive our fashionable ladies frantic. Come hither, my dear Moscow and Petersburg ladies, look at their teeth and learn from them how they keep them white. They have no dentists. They do not scour away the gleam of their teeth every day with toothbrushes and powder. Stand mouth to mouth with any one of them you choose: not one of them will infect your lungs with her breath. While yours, yes, yours may infect them with the germ . . . of a disease . . . I am afraid to say what disease, because, though you may not blush, you will be infuriated. Am I not telling the truth? The husband of one of you runs after all the sluts, and, having caught a disease, goes right on drinking, eating, and sleeping with you; another one of you is pleased to have her own yearly, monthly, weekly, or, God forbid! daily lovers. Having made his acquaintance today and satisfied her desire, she does not know him tomorrow, nor does she know that she may already have been infected by his mere kiss. And you, my sweet maid of fifteen summers, you, per chance, are still pure; but I see on your brow that all your blood is poisoned. Your father of blessed memory never left the doctor's hands; and milady, your mother, guiding you upon her own estimable path, has already found a bridegroom for you, a deserving old general, and is in a hurry to get you married off, solely to avoid having to make a visit to an orphanage with you. And it's not bad to be the wife of an old man, for you do just as you please; and so long as you are married, the children are all his. He will be jealous? So much the better, for there will be a greater delight in stolen pleasures, and you can teach him from the first night not to follow the silly old custom of sleeping in the same room with his wife.
My dear city gossips, aunts,  sisters, nieces, etc., I had not noticed how long you had detained me. Truly, you are not worth it. On your cheeks there is rouge, on your heart rouge, on your conscience rouge, on your sincerity— soot. Rouge or soot, it's all the same. I shall gallop away from you at full speed to my rustic beauties. True, there are some of them who resemble you, but there are others the likes of whom have not been heard or seen in the cities. See how all my beauties' limbs are round, well-developed, straight, and not contorted. You think it funny that their feet are over eight or even ten inches long. But, my dear niece with your five-inch feet, stand in a row with them and run a race: who will be the first to reach the tall birch tree that stands at the end of the field? Ah—but—you are not up to it! And you, my dear little sister, you, with your three-span waist, you are pleased to make fun of my village nymph, because her abdomen has been allowed to grow naturally. Wait, my dear, I'll have my laugh at you. You have been married these ten months, and your three-span waist is all askew. When it comes to child birth, you will pipe a different tune. God grant that nothing worse than laughter may ensue. 
My dear brother-in-law walks about downcast. He has already thrown all your lacings into the fire. He has pulled the stays out of all your dresses, but it is too late. Your distorted joints can't be straightened out now. Weep, my beloved brother-in-law, weep. Our mother, following the lamentable fashion which often leads to death in childbirth, has for many years been preparing sorrow for you, sickness for her daughter, and feeble bodies for your children. Even now this illness hovers like a deadly weapon over her head, and if it does not cut short your wife's days, thank your lucky stars,  and, if you believe that God's Providence was concerned about the matter, thank Him, too, if you wish. But here I am still with the city ladies. That's what custom does: one doesn't feel like leaving them. Indeed I would not leave you if I could persuade you not to paint your faces and your sincerity. And now, good-bye!
While I was watching the village nymphs washing their clothes, my carriage drove off. I was about to start after it, when a girl who looked to be about twenty, but was really only seventeen, put her wet clothes on a yoke and started off the same way I was going. When I caught up with her, I spoke to her.
"Isn't it hard for you to carry such a heavy load, my dear—?  I don't know your name."
"My name is Anna, and my load isn't heavy. And even if it were, I would not ask you, sir,  to help me."
"Why so stern, Annushka dear? I mean you no harm."
"All right, all right! We've seen gallants like you before. Please go your way!"
"Truly, Anyutushka, I'm not the man you take me for and not the sort you're talking about. I understand that they start by kissing a girl, not by talking with her; but if I were to kiss you, it would be just as though I were kissing my own sister."
"Don't sidle up to me, if you please. I've heard such talk before. If you really mean no harm, what is it you want of me? "
"Dear Annushka, I wanted to know whether your father and mother are still alive, what your circumstances are, whether you're rich or poor, whether you're happy, whether you have a fiance?"
"What's that to you, sir? This is the first time in my life I've heard such talk."
"From which you may judge, Anyuta, that I'm not a scoundrel and do not mean to insult or dishonor you. I love women because they embody my ideal of tenderness; but most of all I love village or peasant women, because they are innocent of hypocrisy, do not put on the mask of pretended love, and when they do love, love sincerely and with their whole hearts."
While I was saying this, the girl looked at me with eyes wide open with amazement. How, indeed, could it have been otherwise, for who does not know the impudence, the crude, unchaste, and offensive jests, with which the audacious gentry assail the village maidens? In the eyes of old and young nobles alike, they are simply creatures for their lordly pleasure. And they treat them accordingly, especially those unfortunate ones subject to their commands. During the recent Pugachev Rebellion, when all the serfs rose up in arms against their masters, some peasants (this story is not an invention) had tied up their master and started to carry him off to certain death. What was the reason for this? In everything else he was a good and charitable master, but neither the wives nor the daughters of his peasants were safe from him. Every night his emissaries brought him his chosen victim for that day's sacrifice to dishonor. It was known in the village that he had dishonored sixty maidens, robbing them of their purity. A detachment of soldiers that happened to pass by rescued this barbarian from the hands of those who were raging against him. Stupid peasants, you looked for justice from an impostor!  But why did you not report your grievance to your rightful judges? They would have condemned the offender to civil death, and you would have remained innocent. But now this evildoer is saved. Happy he if the sight of imminent death has changed his way of thinking and given a new direction to his vital humors. But, we said, the peasant is dead to the law? No, no, he lives, he will live, if he wishes to!
"If you are not jesting, sir," Anyuta said to me, "I will tell you. I have no father; he died two years ago. I have a mother and a little sister. Father left us five horses and three cows. And there are plenty of small animals and fowl, but there is no man in the house to do the farm work. They were going to marry me off into a rich house, to a ten-year-old lad, but I didn't want that. What could I do with such a child? I could not love him. And by the time he was grown up, I would have been an old woman, and he would have been running after others. They say that his father sleeps with his young daughters-in-law until his sons grow up. That's why I didn't want to marry into his family. I want someone my own age. I shall love my husband, and he will love me; I've no doubt of that. I don't want to gallivant with the boys, but I do want to get married, sir. And do you know why?" Anyuta said, letting her eyes droop.
"Tell me, dear Anyutushka, don't be bashful; every word from the lips of innocence is pure."
"Well, then, I'll tell you. A year ago last summer our neighbor's son married my friend with whom I always used to go to quilting parties. Her husband loves her, and she loves him so much that in the tenth month after their wedding she bore him a little son. Every evening she takes him out by the gate to give him an airing. She can't get to see her fill of him. And it looks as though the little fellow already loves his mother. Whenever she says to him 'Agoo, agoo,' he laughs. Tears come to my eyes every day I see him; I should love to have a child like that myself."
At this point I could no longer refrain from embracing Anyuta, and kissed her with all my heart. "See what a deceiver you are, sir! You are already playing with me," said Anyuta, bursting into tears. "Go away and leave a poor orphan alone. If my father were alive and saw this, he would give you a good beating in spite of your being a nobleman."
"Don't be offended, dear Anyutushka, don't be offended! My kiss does not sully your virtue, which is sacred in my eyes. My kiss is a token of my respect for you, and it was the joyous response of my deeply moved soul. Do not be afraid of me, dear Anyuta, for I am not a rapacious animal like our young noble men who think nothing of robbing a maiden of her purity. If I had known that my kiss would offend you, I swear in God's name that I would not have dared to kiss you."
"You can see yourself, sir, that I could not help being offended by your kiss, since all mine are meant for another. I have promised them in advance, and I am not free to dispose of them."
"How charming! You have already learned how to love. You have found another heart for your own, a fitting mate. You will be happy. Nothing will sever your union. You will not be surrounded by busybodies who will be watching for a chance to lure you into the nets of destruction. Your true lover's ear will not be open to the voice of temptation, inciting him to violate his troth to you. But why, my dear Anyuta, are you deprived of the pleasure of enjoying happiness in your dear friend's arms?"
"O sir, because they won't let him off to come to us. They demand a hundred rubles. And my mother won't let me go, because I'm her only helper."
"But does he love you?"
"Indeed he does. Every evening he comes to our house and together we watch my friend's baby. He'd love to have a little fellow just like that one. It will be hard for me, but I shall have to stand it. My Vanyukha wants to go to Petersburg to work on the boats, and he will not come back until he has earned a hundred rubles to buy his release."
"Do not let him go, dear Anyutushka,  do not let him go! He will be going to his ruin. There he will learn to drink, to waste his money, to eat dainties, despise farm work, and worst of all, he will stop loving you."
"O sir, don't frighten me," said Anyuta, almost in tears.
"And it would be even worse, Anyuta, if he should take service in a nobleman's house. The example of the masters infects the higher servants, these infect the lower, and from them the pestilence of debauchery spreads to the villages. The bad example is the real plague, for everybody does what he sees others do."
"Then what will become of me? I'll never be able to marry him. It's time for him to get married; he's not one to go running about with other girls. They won't let me go into his household; they'll marry him to someone else, and I, poor girl, shall die of grief." Saying this, she shed bitter tears.
"No, my dear Anyutushka, you shall marry him tomorrow. Take me to your mother."
"Here is our house," she said, as she stopped. "Please go away, for if Mother sees me with you, she'll think ill of me. Though she doesn't strike me, her mere words hurt me more than blows."
"No, Anyuta, I'll go with you." And, without waiting for her answer, I walked right through the gate, up the stairs, and into the hut. Anyuta cried after me, "Wait, sir, wait!" But I paid no attention to her. In the hut I found Anyuta's mother, who was kneading dough; near her, on a bench, sat her future son-in-law. I told her, without beating about the bush, that I wanted her daughter to marry Ivan, and that I had brought the means to remove the obstacle thereto.
"Thank you, sir," said the old woman, "but there is no longer any need for it. Vanyukha has just come to tell us that his father has agreed to let him off, to come to us. So we'll have the wedding on Sunday."
"Then let my promised gift be Anyuta's dowry."
"Thank you, no. Gentlemen do not give girls a dowry for nothing. If you have wronged my Anyuta and are giving her a dowry to make up for it, God will punish you for your misdeed, but I will not take the money. If you are a good man and do not hurt the poor, then malicious people would think the worst of me for taking money from you."
I could not sufficiently admire the noble dignity which I had found in these simple country people. Meanwhile Anyuta had come into the hut, and sang my praises to her mother. I tried again to give them the money, offering it to Ivan toward setting up his house, but he said to me: "I have two hands, sir, and with them I will set up my house." Seeing that my presence was not very pleasant for them, I left them and returned to my carriage.
As I drove on from Edrovo, I could not put Anyuta out of my mind. Her innocent sincerity pleased me beyond measure. Her mother's noble act enchanted me. I compared this noble mother, with her sleeves rolled up over the dough or over her milking pail near the cow, with urban mothers. The peasant woman refused to accept my honest, well-intended hundred rubles, which, in proportion to her means and status, would correspond to five, ten, fifteen thousand, or more, for the wife of a colonel, privy councilor, major, or general. Now if a distinguished magnate of the seventieth or—God forbid! —the seventy-second proof were to offer the wife of a colonel, major, privy councilor, or general, who has a pretty or merely virtuous daughter, five, ten, or fifteen thousand (which would be quite in proportion to my offer to the wife of the Edrovo coachman), or if he hinted that he would give her daughter a handsome dowry, or find her an official for her husband, or  secure her an appointment as a lady in-waiting—I ask you, city mothers, would not your heart give a leap? Would you not want to see your daughter in a gilt carriage, wearing diamonds, riding in a four-in-hand if she now goes on foot, or in a tandem of eight in place of the two sorry nags that draw her now? I grant that in order to preserve custom and decorum you would not give in as easily as chorus girls do. No, dear mothers, I give you one or two months' time, but no more. For if you leave the man of high estate sighing in vain, he, being very busy with affairs of state, will leave you so as not to waste on you the precious time which he can better employ for the public good. A thousand voices rise up against me and shower me with terms of abuse: swindler, cheat, canaille, beast, and so forth. My dear ones, calm yourselves, I am not casting aspersions on you. Are you really all like that? Look into this mirror: whosoever recognizes herself in it, let her scold me unmercifully. I will not enter a complaint against her either, nor dispute her word through a lawsuit.
Anyuta, Anyuta, you have turned my head! Why did I not make your acquaintance fifteen years ago? Your frank innocence, which is proof against the audacity of passion, would have taught me to walk in the way of chastity. Why was not the first kiss of my life the one I pressed upon your cheek in my soul's ecstasy? The influence of your living virtue would have penetrated to the depths of my heart, and I would have escaped the shameful acts which have filled my life. I would have kept away from the loathsome hirelings of lust, would have honored the nuptial couch, would not have violated the domestic bond in my carnal insatiability; virginity would have been for me a holy of holies, and I would not have dared to lay violent hands on it. O my Anyutushka! Be ever near us and teach us by your unconstrained innocence. I know that you will lead back into the way of virtue him who has begun to turn aside, and strengthen him who is tending to go astray. Let not your heart be troubled if a man steeped in debauch and grown gray in shamelessness should pass by and scorn you; do not attempt to bar his way with the solace of your converse. His heart is already stone; his soul is encrusted with a layer of adamant. The beneficent sting of innocent virtue cannot make any real impression on him. Its point will glide over the smooth surface of vice. Beware lest your sharp weapon be blunted against it. But do not let the youth pass by who is allured by the dangerous charms of beauty; catch him in your net. He seems haughty, supercilious, impetuous, insolent, presumptuous, spiteful, and insulting. But his heart will yield to your influence and will respond to your wholesome example. Anyuta, I cannot part from you, although I can already see the fourteenth milestone dividing us.
But what of the custom Anyuta told me about? They wanted to marry her off to a ten-year-old boy. Who could sanction such a union? Why does not the hand that guards the law arm itself for the eradication of this evil custom? In Christian law marriage is a sacrament, in civil law, an agreement or contract. What priest can bless an unequal marriage, and what judge can enter it upon his register? Where there is great disparity in ages, there can be no true marriage. It is forbidden by the law of nature, as a thing harmful to man, and it ought to be forbidden by the civil law, as injurious to society. Man and wife in society are two citizens who enter into an agreement, confirmed by law, whereby primarily they promise mutual satisfaction of their passion (let no one dare to deny this first law of cohabitation and the foundation of the marital bond, the source of the purest love, and the firmest foundation stone of conjugal concord), they promise to live together, to have and to hold their worldly goods in common, to bring up together the fruit of their passion, to live in peace, and to avoid offending one another. Can the terms of this agreement be satisfied if the ages are unequal? If the husband is ten years old, and the wife is twenty-five, as often happens among the peasantry, or if the husband is fifty and the wife fifteen or twenty, as is the case among the gentry, can there be any mutual satisfaction of desire?  Tell me, you aged husbands, but tell me honestly, do you deserve the name of husband? You can kindle the fire of passion; you cannot put it out. By the inequality of years one of the first laws of nature is violated, and how can man-made law be firm, if it is not based on the law of nature? Let us answer unequivocally: it cannot. To bring up the fruits of their mutual passion. But can there be any mutuality where on one side there is a flame, and on the other, insensibility. Can there be any fruit, if the planted tree is deprived of beneficent rain and quickening dew ? And if there ever is any fruit, it will be shriveled, unsightly, and liable to early decay. Do not offend one another. It is an eternally true principle that if passion is mutually satisfied through a blissful sympathy between husband and wife, the marital union is happy, and small domestic troubles subside with the approach of joy. And when the chill of old age draws an impenetrable, icy film over sensual enjoyment, the memory of former warmth will comfort dreary old age. One condition of the marriage contract can be fulfilled in inequality. That of living together. But will there be any mutuality in that? One will be an autocratic ruler who has absolute power in his hands, the other will be a feeble subject and a complete slave, capable only of carrying out the master's commands. These, Anyuta, are the virtuous thoughts with which you have inspired me. Good-bye, my dear Anyutushka! Your precepts will be deeply engraved in my heart forever, and my children's children shall inherit them.
The Khotilov post station was already in sight, but I was still thinking of the Edrovo lass, and, in the elation of my soul, I cried aloud: "O Anyuta! Anyuta!" The road was rough and the horses were going at a walk. The driver heard my exclamation and turned around. "It looks as though you've taken a liking to our Anyutka, sir," he said, smiling and adjusting his hat. "Yes, she's quite a girl. You're not the only one she's bewitched. She carries off the honors at everything. In our village there are a lot of beautiful girls, but they're not worth looking at beside her. How she can dance! She'll dance rings around any of them. And when she goes to reap in the field, you can't feast your eyes enough watching her. Well, brother Van'ka is a lucky dog!" "Is Ivan your brother?"
"My cousin. And a fine fellow he is! Three lads were courting Anyutka at the same time, but Ivan cut them all out. They tried one thing after another, but it was no good. Vanyukha hooked her right off." (Just then we entered the village.) "Yes, sir! Everybody dances, but not like a minstrel." And he drove up to the post station.
GORODNYA

As I drove into this village, my ears were assailed not by the melody of verse, but by a heart-rending lament of women, children, and old men. Getting out of my carriage, I sent it on to the post station, for I was curious to learn the cause of the disturbance I had noticed in the street.

Going up to one group of people, I learned that a levy of recruits was the cause of the sobs and tears of the people crowded together there. From many villages, both crown and manorial, those who were to be drafted into the army had come together here.

In one group an old woman fifty years of age, holding the head of a lad of twenty, was sobbing. "My dear child to whose care are you committing me? To whom will you entrust the home of your parents? I, your poor old mother, will have to wander about begging. . . .

Near the old woman stood a grown girl. She, too, was sobbing. "Farewell, friend of my heart; farewell, my shining sun. I, your betrothed, will never know comfort or joy again. . . .

The lad said to them:  "Stop weeping, stop rending my heart. Our Sovereign calls us to service. The lot fell on me. It is the will of God. Those not fated to die will live. Perhaps I will come home to you. . . .

From another group standing nearby I heard altogether different words. Amidst them I saw a man of about thirty, of medium size, standing erect and looking happily at the peopole around him.

"The Lord has heard my prayers," he said. "The tears of an unfortunate man have reached the Comforter of all men. Now I shall at least know that my lot may depend on my own good or bad behavior. Heretofore it depended on the arbitrary whims of a woman. I am consoled by the thought that hereafter I shall not be flogged without a fair trial!" . . .

From this unfortunate man I went to a group in which I saw three men fettered in the strongest irons. . . . I asked one of the bystanders who, to judge from his uniform, was a government clerk: "No doubt you have put them in such heavy fetters because you are afraid they will run away?"

"You guessed it. They belonged to a landed proprietor who needed money for a new carriage and got it by selling them to crown peaants, to be levied into the army."

I said:  "My friend, you are mistaken. Crown peasants can't purchase their brothers."

"It isn't done in the form of a sale. Having by agreement received the money, the master sets these unfortunates free; they are presumed to be 'voluntarily' registed as crown peasants of the commune which paid the money for them; and the commune, by commmon consent, sends them to be soldiers. They are now being taken with their emancipation papers to be registered in our commune."

Free men, who have committed no crime, are fettered, and sold like cattle! O laws! Is this not an open mockery? Oh, if the slaves weighted down with fetters, raging in their despair, would, with the iron that bars their freedom, crush our heads, the heads of their inhuman masters, and redden their fields with our blood! What would the country lose by that? . . .



THE DECREE PUNISHING RADISHCHEV, SEPTEMBER 4, 1790  

Catherine, having read Radishchev's Journey--"every page of it," she said--concluded that he was advocating "the immoral example of contemporary France." Radishchev was brought to trial. Here is the crucial portion of the resultant decree. 
Aleksandr Radishchev, collegiate councillor [kollezhskii sovetnik] and chevalier of the Order of Saint Vladimdr, has been found guilty of a crime violating his oath and the duties of a subject, by the publication of a book entitled A Journey from Saint Petersburg to Moscow, filled with the most harmful reasonings which disturb the public tranquillity, lessen the respect due the authorities, strive to arouse among the people resentment against authority and against their superiors, and filled, finally, with insulting and violent expressions against the tsarist dignity and power; he has committed, moreover, a deceitful act by adding, after censorship, many pages to this book, published by his own printing shop, which fact he did freely acknowledge. For this crime he has been sentenced to death by the criminal court of the Saint Petersburg guberniia, and then by our Senate, on the basis of the state laws; and although he deserves this sentence of death by the enormity of his crime and the strict application of the law, as designated above, we, nevertheless, following our principle of tempering justice with mercy ... free him from forfeiting his life and command instead that he be deprived of his rank, the insignia of the Order of Saint Vladimir, and of the dignity of a nobleman, and that he be exiled to Siberia to the frontier settlement of Ilimsk [north of Irkutsk] for a continuous term of ten years. 

</excerpt>